<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text><book id="b.OBA" allLangs="no"><chapter id="b.OBA.1"><verse id="b.OBA.1.1" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko te kite a Oparia. Ko te kupu tenei a te Ariki, a Ihowa, mo Eroma; Kua tae mai he korero i a Ihowa, kua oti ano he karere te unga ki nga tauiwi, hei mea, Whakatika, kia whakatika atu hoki tatou ki a ia ki te whawhai
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Sự hiện thấy của Áp-đia. Chúa Giê-hô-va phán về Ê-đôm như vầy: chúng ta có nghe lời rao từ Ðức Giê-hô-va, và một sứ giả được sai đi giữa các nước rằng: Các ngươi hãy dấy lên! Chúng ta hãy dấy lên nghịch cùng dân nầy đặng đánh trận với nó!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Prophétie d`Abdias. Ainsi parle le Seigneur, l`Éternel, sur Édom: -Nous avons appris une nouvelle de la part de l`Éternel, Et un messager a été envoyé parmi les nations: Levez-vous, marchons contre Édom pour lui faire la guerre! -
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						[Ny fahitan'i Obadia ny amin'ny handravana an'i Edoma mbamin'ny jentilisa sasany noho ny ratsy nataony tamin'ny Isiraely, ary ny hampiorenana ny fanjakan'i Jehovah any Ziona] Ny fahitan'i Obadia. Izao no lazain'i Jehovah Tompo ny amin'i Edoma: Nahare filazana avy tamin'i Jehovah izahay, Ary nisy iraka nalefa ho any amin'ny jentilisa hanao hoe: Mitsangàna, aoka isika hitsangana hanafika azy!
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Abdiás látása. Így szól az Úr Isten Edomról:  Hírt hallottunk az Úrtól! És hírnök küldetett a népekhez: keljetek fel és támadjunk reá haddal!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Umbono kaObhadiya. Itshilo iNkosi uYehova ngokusingisele kwelakwaEdom, ukuthi, Sive udaba oluvela kuYehova, kuthunywe isigidimi ezintlangeni sokuthi, Suka nime, sisukele phezulu kulo, silwe nalo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">오바댜의 묵시라 주 여호와께서 에돔에 대하여 이같이 말씀하시니라 우리가 여호와께로 말미암아 소식을 들었나니 곧 사자가 열국 중에 보내심을 받고 이르기를 너희는 일어날지어다 우리가 일어나서 그로 더불어 싸우자 하는 것이니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Abdijo regėjimas. Taip sako Viešpats Dievas apie Edomą: (Girdėjome žinią iš Viešpaties, pasiuntinys pasiųstas į tautas, ragina: “Pakilkime, eikime prieš jį į karą!”)
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Видение Авдия. Так говорит Господь Бог об Едоме: весть услышали мы от Господа, и посол послан объявить народам: „вставайте, ивыступим против него войною!"
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Inilah ramalan Obaja; ia menyampaikan pesan TUHAN Yang Mahatinggi mengenai bangsa Edom: TUHAN telah mengirim utusan-Nya kepada bangsa-bangsa, dan kita telah mendengar pesan yang dibawanya sebagai berikut, "Bersiaplah untuk berperang! Marilah kita berangkat menyerang Edom.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Ang panan-awon ni Abdias. Kini mao ang giingon sa Ginoong Jehova mahatungod sa Edom: Kami nakabati mga balita gikan kang Jehova, ug usa ka sinugo gipadala sa taliwala sa mga nasud, nga nagaingon: Manindog kamo, ug manindog kita sa pagpakiggubat batok kaniya.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အရှင်ထာဝရဘုရားသည် ဧဒုံပြည်ကို ရည်မှတ် ၍ မိန့်တော်မူသည်ကား၊ ထာဝရဘုရား ကြွေးကြော်တော် မူသံကို ငါတို့သည် ကြားကြ၏။ သင်တို့ထ၍ ဧဒုံပြည်ကို တိုက်ခြင်းငှါ စစ်ချီကြလော့ဟု၊ တပါးအမျိုးသားတို့ထံသို့ သံတမန်ကို စေလွှတ်တော်မူပြီ။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Aßan aßin li quicßutbesîc chiru laj Abdías saß li visión xban li Dios chirixeb laj Edom: Xkabi resil li quixye li Kâcuaß. Jun li takl cô saß eb li jalan tenamit chixyebal reheb: —Cauresihomak êrib ut yôkeb chi pletic riqßuineb laj Edom.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Videnie Obadiášovo: Takto hovorí Pán Hospodin o Edomovi: Počuli sme povesť od Hospodina, a posol je poslaný medzi národy, ktorý hovorí: Vstaňte, a nože vstaňme proti nemu do boja!
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						यो ओबदियाको दर्शन हो। परमप्रभु मेरा मालिकले एदोमको विषयमा यसो भन्नुहुन्छः हामीले परमप्रभु परमेश्वरबाट एउटा विवरण सुन्यौ। देशहरूमा एउटा राजदूत पठाइएको थियो। उनले भने, “आऊ, एदोमको बिरूद्ध युद्ध गरौ।”
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Utvara Avdijeva. Ovako veli Gospod Gospod za edomsku: Čusmo glas od Gospoda, i glasnik bi poslan k narodima: Ustajte, da ustanemo na nju u boj.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Obadias' syn. Så sier Herren, Israels Gud, om Edom: En tidende har vi hørt fra Herren, og et bud er sendt ut blandt hedningefolkene: Stå op og la oss reise oss til strid mot det! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Ovadya'nın görümü. Egemen RAB'bin Edom için söyledikleri: RAB'den bir haber aldık: Uluslara gönderdiği haberci, "Gelin, Edom'la savaşalım!" diyor. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						رؤيا عوبديا. هكذا قال السيد الرب عن ادوم. سمعنا خبرا من قبل الرب وأرسل رسول بين الامم. قوموا ولنقم عليها للحرب.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Visão de Abdias. Assim diz o Senhor Deus a respeito de Edom: Temos ouvido novas da parte do Senhor, e por entre as nações foi enviado um mensageiro a dizer: Levantai-vos, e levantemo-nos contra ela para a guerra.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">visio Abdiae haec dicit Dominus Deus ad Edom auditum audivimus a Domino et legatum ad gentes misit surgite et consurgamus adversum eum in proelium</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ορασις Αβδιου. Ουτω λεγει Κυριος ο Θεος περι του Εδωμ Ηκουσαμεν αγγελιαν παρα Κυριου και μηνυτης απεσταλη προς τα εθνη, Εγερθητε και ας εγερθωμεν εναντιον αυτου εις πολεμον.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Die gesig van Obadja. So sê die Here HERE aangaande Edom: Ons het 'n tyding van die HERE gehoor, en 'n boodskapper is uitgestuur onder die nasies om te sê: Staan op, en laat ons klaarmaak om teen hom te veg!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Mesaj pwofèt Abdyas sou peyi Edon. Men mesaj Seyè a te ban mwen: Nou te tande mesaj Seyè a te bay la. Li te voye mesaj li a nan tout nasyon yo pou di yo: Annavan! Leve non! Ann mache pran Edon! Ann al goumen avè l'
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Sự hiện thấy của Áp - đia . Chúa_Giê - hô-va phán về Ê - đôm như_vầy : chúng_ta có nghe lời rao từ Ðức_Giê - hô-va , và một sứ_giả được sai đi giữa các nước rằng : Các ngươi hãy dấy lên ! Chúng_ta hãy dấy lên nghịch cùng_dân nầy đặng đánh trận với nó !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						חזון עבדיה כה אמר אדני יהוה לאדום שמועה שמענו מאת יהוה וציר בגוים שלח קומו ונקומה עליה למלחמה׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">The vision of Obadiah. This is what the Lord Yahweh says about Edom. We have heard news from Yahweh, and an ambassador is sent among the nations, saying, "Arise, and let's rise up against her in battle.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఓబద్యాకు కలిగిన దర్శనము. ఎదోమును గురించి ప్రభువగు యెహోవా సెలవిచ్చునది. యెహోవాయొద్ద నుండి వచ్చిన సమాచారము మాకు వినబడెను. ఎదోము మీద యుద్ధము చేయుదము లెండని జనులను రేపుటకై దూత పంపబడియున్నాడు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Авдиевото видение: - Така казва Господ Иеова за Едом: Чухме известие от Господа И вестител се изпрати при народите да каже -  Станете, и да се вдигнем против него на бой.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Prikazen Obadijeva. Tako pravi Gospod Jehova o Edomu: Oznanilo smo slišali GOSPODOVO in poslanec je bil poslan med narode: „Vstanite in vzdignimo se v boj zoper njega!“
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						رویای عوبدیا.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Obadias Obadias's Syn. Så siger den Herre HERREN til Edom: Fra HERREN har jeg hørt en Tidende: Et Bud er sendt ud blandt Folkene: Rejs jer til Kamp imod det!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Obadjan näky. Herra, Herra sanoo Edomista näin: Me olemme kuulleet  sanoman Herralta, ja sanansaattaja on lähetetty kansakuntiin: "Nouskaa,  nouskaamme sotaan sitä vastaan!"
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						俄 巴 底 亞 得了 耶和華 的 默示 。 論以 東說 、 我 從 耶和華 那 裡聽見 信息 、 並有 使者 被 差往 列國 去 、 說 、 起來罷 、 一同 起 來與 以 東爭戰
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Obadiya bangando neeya: Rabbi, Koy Beero sanno neeya Edom boŋ: Iri du baaru Rabbi do, I na diya donton dumi cindey game ra a ma ne: «Kaa, iri ma tun ka koy ka kay a se da wongu.» 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						俄 巴 底 亞 得 了 耶 和 華 的 默 示 。 論 以 東 說 、 我 從 耶 和 華 那 裡 聽 見 信 息 、 並 有 使 者 被 差 往 列 國 去 、 說 、 起 來 罷 、 一 同 起 來 與 以 東 爭 戰 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						ओबद्याह का दर्शन।। हम लोगों ने यहोवा की ओर से समाचार सुना है, और एक दूत अन्यजातियों में यह कहने को भेजा गया है:
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Vidění Abdiášovo. Takto praví Panovník Hospodin o zemi Idumejské: Pověst jsme slyšeli od Hospodina, a legáta k národům vyslaného: Nuže, povstaňmež k boji proti ní.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Vizio de Obadja.  Tiele diras la Sinjoro, la Eternulo, pri Edom: Diron ni auxdis de la Eternulo, kaj kuriero estas sendita al la nacioj: Levigxu, ni iru milite kontraux lin.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Vegimi i Abdias. Kështu thotë Zoti, Zoti, për Edomin: "Ne kemi dëgjuar një mesazh nga Zoti dhe një ambasador është dërguar midis kombeve për të thënë: "Lëvizni dhe të ngrihemi kundër tij për të luftuar".
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Visione di Abdia. Così dice il Signore Dio per Edom: Udimmo un messaggio da parte del Signore e un araldo è stato inviato fra le genti: «Alzatevi, marciamo contro Edom in battaglia»
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Vitrun Óbadía. Svo segir Drottinn Guð um Edóm: Vér höfum fengið vitneskju frá Drottni, og boðberi er sendur meðal þjóðanna: "Af stað! Vér skulum halda af stað til þess að herja á hann!" 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						हा ओबद्याचा दृष्टांन्त आहे. परमेश्वर, माझा प्रभू अदोमाबद्दल पुढील प्रढील प्रमाणे म्हणाला: आम्ही परमेश्वर देवाकडून हकिगत ऐकली. राष्ट्रांकडे दूत पाठविला गेला. तो म्हणाला, “आपण अदोमाविरुध्द लढण्यास जाऊ या.”
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						オバデヤの幻。主なる神はエドムについてこう言われる、われわれは主から出たおとずれを聞いた。ひとりの使者が諸国民のうちにつかわされて言う、「立てよ、われわれは立ってエドムと戦おう」。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						La visión de Abdías: Así ha dicho el Señor Jehovah acerca de Edom (hemos escuchado de parte de Jehovah la noticia de que ha sido enviado un mensajero a las naciones, diciendo: "¡Levantaos! ¡Levantémonos contra él en batalla!")
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwanu waa wixii la tusay Cobadyaah. Sayidka Rabbiga ahu sidan buu dalka Edom ka leeyahay: Annagu Rabbiga xaggiisa ayaannu war ka maqalnay, oo farriinwade ayaa quruumaha dhexdooda loo soo diray, isagoo leh, War kaca, oo kaalaya aan dadka Edom dagaal ugu kacnee.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						TOUPA PATHIANIN Edom tungtang ah hichiin a chi: TOUPA kianga kipan thu ka theia, namte lakah palai sawl ahi, Thou unla, kidouna ah amah dou dingin i kuan ding uh, chiin.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಓಬದ್ಯನ ದರ್ಶನವು. ಕರ್ತನಾದ ದೇವರು ಎದೋಮನ್ನು ಕುರಿತು ಹೀಗೆ ಹೇಳುತ್ತಾನೆ--ಕರ್ತನಿಂದ ಸುದ್ಧಿಯನ್ನು ಕೇಳಿದ್ದೇವೆ; ಅನ್ಯಜನಾಂಗಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ರಾಯ ಭಾರಿಯು ಕಳುಹಿಸಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿದ್ದಾನೆ; ಏಳಿರಿ, ಅದಕ್ಕೆ ವಿರೋಧವಾಗಿ ಯುದ್ಧಕ್ಕೆ ಏಳುವ!
					</lang><lang id="English">
						The vision of Obadiah. Thus saith the Lord GOD concerning Edom; We have heard a rumour from the LORD, and an ambassador is sent among the heathen, Arise ye, and let us rise up against her in battle.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">De Oppermachtige HERE liet Obadja in een visioen de toekomst van het land Edom (A) zien. "De HERE heeft mij laten weten", zei hij, "dat Hij een bode naar de volken heeft gestuurd met het bevel: 'Luister! U moet uw troepen naar Edom sturen en het vernietigen!</lang><lang id="Croatian">Viđenje Obadijino. Ovako govori Jahve Gospod Edomu! Čuli smo vijest od Jahve, glasnik bi poslan k narodima: "Ustajte! Na nj u boj krenimo!"</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Widzenie Abdyjaszowe. Tak mówi panujący Pan o ziemi Edomskiej: Słyszeliśmy wieść od Pana i od posła wysłanego do narodów: Ruszcie się, a powstaómy przeciwko niemu ku bitwie,
					</lang><lang id="Thai">นิมิตของโอบาดีห์ องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าพระเจ้าตรัสเกี่ยวด้วยเรื่องเอโดมดังนี้ว่า เราได้ยินข่าวลือจากพระเยโฮวาห์ ทูตคนหนึ่งถูกส่งไปท่ามกลางบรรดาประชาชาติให้พูดว่า "จงลุกขึ้นเถิด ให้เราลุกไปทำสงครามกับเมืองเอโดม"</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ang pangitain ni Obadias. Ganito ang sabi ng Panginoong Dios tungkol sa Edom, Kami ay nakarinig ng mga balita na mula sa Panginoon, at isang sugo ay sinugo sa mga bansa, na nagsasabi, Magsibangon kayo, at tayo'y mangagtindig laban sa kaniya sa pakikipagbaka. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 オバデヤ の 幻 。 主な る 神 は エドム に つ い て こう 言 わ れ る 、 われわれ は 主 から 出 た おとずれ を 聞 い た 。 ひとり の 使者 が 諸 国民 の うち に つかわ さ れ て 言 う 、 「 立て よ 、 われわれ は 立 っ て エドム と 戦 お う 」 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഔബദ്യാവിന്റെ ദര്‍ശനം. യഹോവയായ കര്‍ത്താവു എദോമിനെക്കുറിച്ചു ഇപ്രകാരം അരുളിച്ചെയ്യുന്നു; നാം യഹോവയിങ്കല്‍നിന്നു ഒരു വര്‍ത്തമാനം കേട്ടിരിക്കുന്നു; ജാതികളുടെ ഇടയില്‍ ഒരു ദൂതനെ അയച്ചിരിക്കുന്നു; എഴുന്നേല്പിന്‍ ; നാം അവളുടെ നേരെ യുദ്ധത്തിന്നു പറപ്പെടുക.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Proorocia lu Obadia. Aşa vorbeşte Domnul Dumnezeu despre Edom: -,,Noi am auzit o veste din partea Domnului, şi un sol a fost trimes cu ea printre neamuri, zicînd: ,,Sculaţi-vă, să mergem împotriva Edomului ca să ne războim cu el!`` -
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Dies ist das Gesicht Obadjas. So spricht der HERR HERR von Edom: Wir haben vom HERRN gehört, daß eine Botschaft unter die Heiden gesandt sei: Wohlauf, und laßt uns wider sie streiten.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Detta är Obadjas syn.  Så säger Herren, HERREN om Edom: Ett budskap hava vi hört från HERREN, och en budbärare är utsänd bland folken: »Upp, ja, låt oss stå upp och strida mot det!»
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">นิมิต ของ โอ บาดีห์ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า พระเจ้า ตรัส เกี่ยว ด้วย เรื่อง เอ โดม ดังนี้ ว่า เรา ได้ยิน ข่าว ลือ จาก พระ เยโฮวาห์ ทูต คน หนึ่ง ถูก ส่ง ไป ท่ามกลาง บรรดา ประชาชาติ ให้ พูด ว่า " จง ลุก ขึ้น เถิด ให้ เรา ลุก ไป ทำ สงคราม กับ เมือง เอ โดม "</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						1
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.2" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Nana, kua oti koe te mea e ahau kia iti i roto i nga tauiwi: nui atu te whakahawea ki a koe
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nầy, ta đã khiến ngươi làm nhỏ giữa các nước. Ngươi bị khinh dể lắm.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Voici, je te rendrai petit parmi les nations, Tu seras l`objet du plus grand mépris.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Indro, hataoko tsinontsinona eo amin'ny firenena ianao, Eny, ho fanazimbazimba indrindra ianao.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ímé, kicsinynyé tettelek a népek között; felettébb útálatos  vagy.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Yabonani, ndikwenze wamncinane ezintlangeni, udelekile kakhulu.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">여호와께서 가라사대 내가 너를 열국 중에 미약하게 하였으므로 네가 크게 멸시를 받느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						“Aš padariau tave mažą tarp tautų, tu būsi labai niekinamas.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Вот, Я сделал тебя малым между народами, и ты в большом презрении.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Dan kepada Edom, TUHAN berkata, "Engkau Kubuat lemah, sehingga dihina oleh semua bangsa
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ania karon, gihimo ko ikaw nga diyutay sa taliwala sa mga nasud: ikaw ginatamay sa hilabihan gayud.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင့်ကို တပါးအမျိုးသားတို့တွင် ယုတ်မာစေခြင်း ငှါ ငါစီရင်သဖြင့်၊ သင်၏အသရေသည် အလွန်ရှုတ်ချ ခြင်းရှိလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Li Kâcuaß Dios quixye reheb laj Edom li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú: —Lâin tincuisi lê cuanquil chiruheb li jalan tenamit. Ut tzßektânanbilakex chic xbaneb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Hľa, učinil som ťa malým medzi národami; opovržený si veľmi.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						“एदोम, म तिमीलाई सब भन्दा सानो देश बनाई दिनेछु। मानिसहरूले तिमीलाई घृणा गर्नेछन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Gle, učiniću te malim medju narodima, bićeš vrlo prezren.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Se, liten vil jeg gjøre dig blandt hedningefolkene; du skal bli dypt foraktet. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Edom'a, "Bak, seni uluslar arasında küçük düşüreceğim, Herkes seni hor görecek" diyor. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						اني قد جعلتك صغيرا بين الامم. انت محتقر جدا.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Eis que te farei pequeno entre as nações; serás muito desprezado.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">ecce parvulum te dedi in gentibus contemptibilis tu es valde</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ιδου, σε κατεστησα μικρον μεταξυ των εθνων εισαι καταπεφρονημενος σφοδρα.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Kyk, Ek het jou klein gemaak onder die nasies, jy is baie verag.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Men sa Seyè a di moun peyi Edon yo: Mwen pral fè peyi nou an vin tou fèb nan mitan lòt nasyon yo. Tout moun pral meprize nou nèt
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nầy , ta đã khiến ngươi làm nhỏ giữa các nước . Ngươi bị khinh_dể lắm .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						הנה קטן נתתיך בגוים בזוי אתה מאד׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Behold, I have made you small among the nations. You are greatly despised.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నేను అన్యజనులలో నిన్ను అల్పు నిగా చేసితిని, నీవు బహుగా తృణీకరింపబడుదువు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Ето, направих те малък между народите; Ти си много презрян.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Glej, majhnega sem te storil med narodi, silno si zaničevan.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						هان من تو راکوچکترین امت‌ها گردانیدم و تو بسیار خوارهستی.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Se, ringe har jeg gjort dig blandt Folkene, såre foragtet er du.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Katso, vähäiseksi minä teen sinut kansojen seassa, ylen halveksittu  olet sinä oleva.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						我 使 你 以東 在 列國 中 為 最 小 的 、 被 人 大大 藐視
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 «Guna, ay ga ni ciya ikayna fo dumi cindey game ra, I ga donda nin gumo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						我 使 你 以 東 在 列 國 中 為 最 小 的 、 被 人 大 大 藐 視 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						उठो! हम उस से लड़ने को उठें! मैं तुझे जातियों में छोटा कर दूंगा, तू बहुत तुच्छ गिना जाएगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Aj, způsobím to, abys byl nejšpatnější mezi národy, a abys byl v náramném pohrdání.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Vidu, Mi faris vin malgranda inter la nacioj; vi estas tre malestimata.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Ja, unë do të të bëj të vogël midis kombeve; ti do të jesh shumë i përbuzur.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ecco, ti faccio piccolo fra le nazioni, tu sei molto spregevole
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Sjá, ég vil gjöra þig lítinn meðal þjóðanna, þú munt verða mjög fyrirlitinn. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						“अदोम, मी तुला लहान राष्ट्र करीन. लोक तुझा खूप तिरस्कार करतील.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						見よ、わたしはあなたを国々のうちで小さい者とする。あなたはひどく卑しめられる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						"He aquí, te empequeñeceré entre las naciones; serás muy menospreciado
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Bal eega, quruumaha dhexdooda waan idinku yareeyey, oo si weyn baa laydiin quudhsaday.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Ngai dih, namte lakah ka hohhih neuta hi: nakpia muhsitna na omta hi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇಗೋ, ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಅನ್ಯಜನಾಂಗಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಹೀನವಾಗಿ ಮಾಡಿದ್ದೇನೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Behold, I have made thee small among the heathen: thou art greatly despised.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Ik zal u klein maken onder de volken en u zult diep worden veracht.</lang><lang id="Croatian">"Jer gle, učinit ću te najmanjim među narodima, prezrenim veoma.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Oto cię maluczkim uczynię między narodami, ty będziesz bardzo wzgardzony.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ดูเถิด เราได้กระทำเจ้าให้เล็กท่ามกลางบรรดาประชาชาติ ให้เจ้าเป็นที่ดูหมิ่นอย่างมาก</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Narito, ginawa kitang maliit sa mga bansa: ikaw ay lubhang hinamak. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 見 よ 、 わたし は あなた を 国々 の うち で 小さ い 者 と する 。 あなた は ひど く 卑しめ られ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഞാന്‍ നിന്നെ ജാതികളുടെ ഇടയില്‍ അല്പമാക്കിയിരിക്കുന്നു; നീ അത്യന്തം ധിക്കരിക്കപ്പെട്ടിരിക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						,,Iată, te voi face mic printre neamuri, vei fi cel mai dispreţuit.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Siehe, ich habe dich gering gemacht unter den Heiden und sehr verachtet.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Se, jag skall göra dig ringa bland folken, djupt föraktad skall du bliva.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ดูเถิด เรา ได้ กระทำ เจ้า ให้ เล็ก ท่ามกลาง บรรดา ประชาชาติ ให้ เจ้า เป็น ที่ ดูหมิ่น อย่าง มาก</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						2
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.3" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Kua oti koe te tinihanga e te whakapehapeha o tou ngakau, e koe e noho na i nga kapiti o te kamaka, kei runga na tona nohoanga; e mea na i roto i tona ngakau, Ko wai hei whakahoki iho i ahau ki raro ki te whenua
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Hỡi ngươi là kẻ ở trong khe vầng đá, trong nơi cao, ngươi nói trong lòng mình rằng: Ai sẽ có thể xô ta xuống đất? sự kiêu ngạo của lòng ngươi đã lừa dối ngươi.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						L`orgueil de ton coeur t`a égaré, Toi qui habites le creux des rochers, Qui t`assieds sur les hauteurs, Et qui dis en toi-même: Qui me précipitera jusqu`à terre?
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ny avonavon'ny fonao no namitaka anao, Ry ilay monina ao an-tsefatsefaky ny harambato, Any amin'ny fonenana avo, Sady manao anakampo hoe: Iza no hampivarina ahy ho eny an-tany?
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Szíved kevélysége csalt meg téged, ki szikla-hasadékokban lakozol, kinek lakóhelye magasan van, a ki mondja az õ szívében: Ki vonhatna le engem  a síkra?!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ukukhukhumala kwentliziyo yakho kukulukuhlile, wena uhleliyo emfanteni wengxondorha, okhaya liphezulu, othi entliziyweni yakhe, Ngubani na oya kundihlisela ehlabathini?
					</lang><lang id="Korean">바위 틈에 거하며 높은 곳에 사는 자여 네가 중심에 이르기를 누가 능히 나를 땅에 끌어내리겠느냐 하니 너의 중심의 교만이 너를 속였도다</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tavo širdies išdidumas apgavo tave, kuris gyveni uolose, kurio buveinė yra aukštai kalnuose. Tu galvoji: ‘Kas gali nustumti mane?’
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Гордость сердца твоего обольстила тебя; ты живешь в расселинах скал, на возвышенном месте, и говоришь в сердце твоем: „кто низринет меня на землю?"
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Engkau tertipu oleh hatimu yang angkuh. Ibukotamu adalah gunung batu yang kuat; tempat tinggalmu di puncak gunung yang tinggi. Karena itu kamu berpikir, Siapa yang sanggup menjatuhkan Aku
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ang pagpalabilabi sa imong kasing-kasing naglimbong kanimo, Oh ikaw nga nagpuyo sa mga liki sa pangpang, kang kansang puloy-anan atua sa itaas; nga nagaingon sa sulod sa iyang kasing-kasing: Kinsa ba ang makapahulog kanako ngadto sa yuta?
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ကျောက်ကြားတို့၌နေ၍ မြင့်သောအရပ်ကို ခိုလှုံလျက်၊ ငါ့ကို မြေသို့ အဘယ်သူ နှိမ့်ချနိုင်သနည်းဟု အောက်မေ့သောသူ ဖြစ်သောကြောင့်၊ သင်၏မာနသည် သင့်ကို လှည့်စားပြီ။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Xebalakßi êrib êjunes xban lê kßetkßetil. Xeyîb lê naßaj toj saß xbên li tzûl saß xyânkeb li nînki pec ut nequeye saß êchßôl, ¿Ani ta biß târûk tâtaßok ke arin? Arin mâ ani tânumtâk saß kabên, chanquex.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Pýcha tvojho srdca ťa oklamala, oj, ty, ktorý bývaš v skalných rozsadlinách, vo svojom vysokom bydlisku, ktorý hovoríš vo svojom srdci: Kto ma strhne na zem?!
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिम्रो आफ्नो घमण्डले तिमीलाई धोका दिएकोछ। तिमी अग्लो पहडहरूको गुफामाहरू बस्नेछौ। तिम्रो घर पहाको अग्लाईमा छ र तिमी आफ्नो मनमा भन्छौ कि ‘मलाई कसैले पनि तल जमीनमा खसाल्न सक्तैंन।’”
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ponos srca tvog prevari te, tebe, koji živiš u raselinama kamenim, u visokom stanu svom, i govoriš u srcu svom: Ko će me oboriti na zemlju?</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Ditt hjertes overmot har dåret dig, du som bor i fjellkløfter, i din høie bolig, du som sier i ditt hjerte: Hvem vil styrte mig ned til jorden? 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    "Kaya kovuklarında yaşayan, Evini yükseklerde kuran sen! Yüreğindeki gurur seni aldattı. İçinden, 'Beni kim yere indirebilir?' diyorsun. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						تكبر قلبك قد خدعك ايها الساكن في محاجئ الصخر رفعة مقعده القائل في قلبه من يحدرني الى الارض.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						A soberba do teu coração te enganou, ó tu que habitas nas fendas do penhasco, na tua alta morada, que dizes no teu coração: Quem me derrubará em terra?
					</lang><lang id="Latin">superbia cordis tui extulit te habitantem in scissuris petrae exaltantem solium suum qui dicit in corde suo quis detrahet me in terram</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Η υπερηφανια της καρδιας σου ηπατησε σε τον κατοικουντα εν τοις κοιλωμασι των κρημνων, του οποιου η κατοικια ειναι υψηλη, οστις λεγει εν τη καρδια αυτου, Τις θελει με καταβιβασει εις την γην;
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Die vermetelheid van jou hart het jou bedrieg, o jy wat woon in die rotsklowe, op hoë plekke bly, en in jou hart sê: Wie sal my op die aarde neerwerp?
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Se awogans nou ki fè nou pèdi tèt nou. Nou bati kapital nou sou tèt gwo wòch yo. Nou moute kay nou byen wo nan mòn yo. Epi n'ap di nan kè nou: Ki moun ki ka fè nou desann la a
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Hỡi ngươi là kẻ ở trong khe vầng đá , trong nơi cao , ngươi nói trong lòng mình rằng : Ai sẽ có_thể xô ta xuống đất ? sự kiêu_ngạo của lòng ngươi đã lừa_dối ngươi .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						זדון לבך השיאך שכני בחגוי סלע מרום שבתו אמר בלבו מי יורדני ארץ׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">The pride of your heart has deceived you, you who dwell in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation is high, who says in his heart, 'Who will bring me down to the ground?'</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అత్యున్నతమైన పర్వతములమీద ఆసీనుడవైయుండి కొండ సందులలో నివసించువాడానన్ను క్రిందికి పడ ద్రోయగలవాడె వడని అనుకొనువాడా, నీ హృదయపు గర్వముచేత నీవు మోసపోతివి.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Измамила те е гордостта на твоето сърце, Тебе, който живееш в цепнатините на канарите, Тебе, чието жилище е на високо, Който казваш в сърцето си -  Кой ще ме свали на земята?
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Prevzetnost srca tvojega te je premotila, ki prebivaš v razpoklinah skalnih, sedež imaš na višavi in v srcu svojem govoriš: Kdo me potegne na tla?
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						‌ای که در شکافهای صخره ساکن هستی و مسکن تو بلند می‌باشد و در دل خود می‌گویی کیست که مرا به زمین فرود بیاورد، تکبر دلت، تورا فریب داده است.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Dit Hjertes Hovmod bedrog dig, du, som bor i Klippekløft, som troner i det høje og siger i Hjertet: "Hvo kan styrte mig til Jorden?"
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sinun sydämesi ylpeys on pettänyt sinut, joka asut kallionrotkoissa,  istut korkealla ja sanot sydämessäsi: "Kuka voi syöstä minut maahan?"
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						住 在 山 穴中 、 居所 在 高處 的 阿 、 你 因 狂傲 自欺 、 心裡說 、 誰能將 我 拉下 地 去 呢
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ni bina boŋbeera no ka ni fafagu, Ya nin kaŋ goono ga goro tondey kortimey ra, Nin kaŋ ni nangora go hala beene tondey boŋ, Nin kaŋ goono ga ne ni bina ra: ‹May no g'ay zumandi?› 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						住 在 山 穴 中 、 居 所 在 高 處 的 阿 、 你 因 狂 傲 自 欺 、 心 裡 說 、 誰 能 將 我 拉 下 地 去 呢 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						हे पहाड़ों की दरारों में बसनेवाले, हे ऊंचे स्थान में रहनेवाले, तेरे अभिमान ने तुझे धोखा दिया है; तू मन में कहता है,
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Pýcha srdce tvého zklamá tě, ó ty, kterýž bydlíš v rozsedlinách skalních, v převysokém obydlí svém, říkaje v srdci svém: Kdož by mne strhl na zem?
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						La fiereco de via koro delogis vin; logxante en la fendegoj de rokoj, sur via alta sidejo, vi diras en via koro: Kiu depusxos min sur la teron?
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Krenaria e zemrës sate të ka mashtruar, o ti që banon në të çarat e shkëmbinjve, ku ke bërë banesën tënde të lartë, që thua në zemrën tënde: "Kush do të më zbresë për tokë?"
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						L'orgoglio del tuo cuore ti ha esaltato, tu che abiti nei crepacci rocciosi, delle alture fai la tua dimora e dici in cuor tuo: «Chi potrà gettarmi a terra?»
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Hroki hjarta þíns hefir dregið þig á tálar, þú sem átt byggð í klettaskorum og situr í hæðum uppi, sem segir í hjarta þínu: "Hver getur steypt mér niður til jarðar?" 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तुझ्या गर्वाने तुला मूर्ख बनविले. उंच कड्यावरील गुहांत तू राहतोस. तुझे घर टेकडीवर उंच ठिकाणी आहे. म्हणून स्वत:शी म्हणतोस, ‘मला कोणीही खाली जमिनीवर आणू शकत नाही.”‘
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						岩のはざまにおり、高い所に住む者よ、あなたの心の高ぶりは、あなたを欺いた。あなたは心のうちに言う、「だれがわたしを地に引き下らせる事ができるか」。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						La soberbia de tu corazón te ha engañado a ti que habitas en las hendiduras de la peña, en tu morada elevada; a ti que decías en tu corazón: '¿Quién me hará caer a tierra?
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwiinna qararka dillaacyadooda ku hoyda oo hoygoodu meesha sare ku yaal, waxaa idin khiyaanay kibirka qalbigiinna, oo waxaad qalbiga iska tidhaahdaan, Bal yaa dhulka nagu soo ridi kara?
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Aw nang, suangpi kitam kala teng, mun sang luah, Kuan ahia lei a hohke sak ding? lungsima chipa, na lungtang kisaktheihna in nang a hoh khemta hi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನೀನು ಬಹಳವಾಗಿ ತಿರಸ್ಕರಿಸಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿದ್ದೀ. ಬಂಡೆಯ ಬಿರುಕು ಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ವಾಸಮಾಡುವವನೇ, ಉನ್ನತದಲ್ಲಿ ನಿವಾಸ ಮಾಡಿಕೊಂಡವನೇ--ಯಾರು ನನ್ನನ್ನು ನೆಲಕ್ಕೆ ಇಳಿಸ ಬಲ್ಲರೆಂದು ತನ್ನ ಹೃದಯದಲ್ಲಿ ಅನ್ನುವವನೇ, ನಿನ್ನ ಹೃದಯದ ಗರ್ವವು ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಮೋಸಗೊಳಿಸಿದೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						The pride of thine heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation is high; that saith in his heart, Who shall bring me down to the ground?
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">U bent trots, omdat u in die hoge, ontoegankelijke rotskloven woont. U bluft: 'Wie zou ons hier ooit kunnen bereiken?'</lang><lang id="Croatian">Uznositost srca tvoga zavela te, tebe što živiš u pećinama kamenim, u visoku stanu svojemu, i u srcu svome zboriš: 'Tko li će me na zemlju skinuti?'</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Pycha serca twego zdradziła cię, o ty! który mieszkasz w rozpadlinach skalnych, w wysokiem mieszkaniu twojem, który mówisz w sercu swojem: Któż mię na ziemię ściągnie?
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ความเห่อเหิมแห่งใจของเจ้าได้ล่อลวงเจ้าเอง เจ้าผู้ซึ่งอาศัยอยู่ในซอกหิน ที่อาศัยของเจ้าอยู่สูง เจ้ารำพึงอยู่ในใจว่า "ผู้ใดจะให้เราลงมายังพื้นดิน"</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Dinaya ka ng kapalaluan ng iyong puso, Oh ikaw na tumatahan sa mga bitak ng bato, na ang tahanan ay matayog; na nagsasabi sa kaniyang puso, Sinong magbababa sa akin sa lupa? 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 岩 の はざま に お り 、 高 い 所 に 住 む 者 よ 、 あなた の 心 の 高ぶり は 、 あなた を 欺 い た 。 あなた は 心 の うち に 言 う 、 「 だれ が わたし を 地 に 引き下 ら せ る 事 が でき る か 」 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						പാറപ്പിളര്‍പ്പുകളില്‍ പാര്‍ക്കുംന്നവനും ഉന്നതവാസമുള്ളവനും ആര്‍ എന്നെ നിലത്തു തള്ളിയിടും എന്നു ഹൃദയത്തില്‍ പറയുന്നവനുമായവനേ, നിന്റെ ഹൃദയത്തിന്റെ അഹങ്കാരം നിന്നെ ചതിച്ചിരിക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Căci mîndria inimii tale te -a dus în rătăcire, pe tine, care locuieşti în crăpăturile stîncilor, şi domneşti în înălţime; de aceea, tu zici în tine însuţi: ,,Cine mă va arunca la pămînt?``
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Der Hochmut deines Herzens hat dich betrogen, weil du in der Felsen Klüften wohnst, in deinen hohen Schlössern, und sprichst in deinem Herzen: Wer will mich zu Boden stoßen?
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ditt hjärtas övermod har bedragit dig, där du sitter ibland bergsklyftorna i den höga boning och säger i ditt hjärta: »Vem kan störta mig ned till jorden?»
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ความ เห่อเหิม แห่ง ใจ ของ เจ้า ได้ ล่อลวง เจ้า เอง เจ้า ผู้ ซึ่ง อาศัย อยู่ ใน ซอก หิน ที่ อาศัย ของ เจ้า อยู่ สูง เจ้า รำพึง อยู่ ใน ใจ ว่า " ผู้ ใด จะ ให้ เรา ลง มายัง พื้น ดิน "</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						3
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.4" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ahakoa i rite tou kakenga ki to te ekara, ahakoa i hanga e koe tou kohanga ki nga whetu, ka whakahokia iho koe e ahau i reira, e ai ta Ihowa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Dầu ngươi lên cao như chim ưng, dầu ngươi lót ổ giữa các ngôi sao, ta cũng sẽ xô ngươi xuống khỏi đó, Ðức Giê-hô-va phán vậy!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Quand tu placerais ton nid aussi haut que celui de l`aigle, Quand tu le placerais parmi les étoiles, Je t`en précipiterai, dit l`Éternel.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Na dia miakatra tahaka ny voromahery aza ianao Ka mametraka ny akaninao eny amin'ny kintana, Dia havariko avy eny ianao, hoy Jehovah.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ha oly magasra szállnál is,  mint a sas, és ha a csillagok közé raknád is fészkedet: onnan is levonnálak, ezt mondja az Úr.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ukuba uthe wakhela phezulu njengexhalanga, nokuba ithe indlu yakho yabekwa phakathi kweenkwenkwezi, ndokuhlisa nalapho;  utsho uYehova.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">네가 독수리처럼 높이 오르며 별 사이에 깃들일지라도 내가 거기서 너를 끌어내리리라 나 여호와가 말하였느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Nors pakiltum aukštai kaip erelis ir sukrautum sau lizdą tarp žvaigždžių, ir iš ten nustumsiu tave!­sako Viešpats.­
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Но хотя бы ты, как орел, поднялся высоко и среди звезд устроил гнездо твое, то и оттуда Я низрину тебя, говорит Господь.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Meskipun kaubuat rumahmu setinggi sarang burung rajawali, dan setinggi bintang-bintang di langit, engkau pasti akan Kujatuhkan
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Bisan ikaw nagabatog sa kahitas-an ingon sa agila, ug bisan ang imong salag igapahamutang sa taliwala sa mga bitoon, gikan diha hulogon ko ikaw, nagaingon si Jehova.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်သည် ရွှေလင်းတကဲ့သို့ ကိုယ်ကို ချီးမြှောက် ၍၊ ကြယ်တို့တွင် အသိုက်ကို လုပ်သော်လည်း၊ ထိုအရပ်မှ သင့်ကို ငါနှိမ့်ချမည်ဟု ထာဝရဘုရား မိန့်တော်မူ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Usta nequeyîb lê naßaj toj takecß joß nak naxyîb xsoc li cßuch, abanan toj aran texintau chak. Ut usta têyîb lê naßaj toj saß xyânkeb li chahim, abanan toj aran texincubsi chak, chan li Kâcuaß.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Keby si si spravil vysoko jako orol, a keby si položil svoje hniezdo medzi hviezdami, aj odtiaľ ťa strhnem, hovorí Hospodin.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						परमेश्वर परमप्रभु भन्नुहुन्छ, “यद्यपि तिमीले चील जस्तै माथि उड्‌यौ, अनि आफ्नो गुँड ताराहरूको बीचमा बनायौ भने पनि, म तिमीलाई त्यहाँबाट तल ल्याउँनेछु।”
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Da podigneš visoko kao orao i medju zvezde da metneš gnezdo svoje, odande ću te oboriti, govori Gospod.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Om du bygger høit som ørnen og setter ditt rede blandt stjerner, vil jeg styrte dig ned derfra, sier Herren. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Kartal gibi yükselsen de, Yuvanı yıldızlar arasında kursan da, Oradan indireceğim seni" diyor RAB. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ان كنت ترتفع كالنسر وان كان عشّك موضوعا بين النجوم فمن هناك احدرك يقول الرب.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Embora subas ao alto como águia, e embora se ponha o teu ninho entre as estrelas, dali te derrubarei, diz o Senhor.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">si exaltatus fueris ut aquila et si inter sidera posueris nidum tuum inde detraham te dicit Dominus</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Εαν μετεωρισθης ως αετος και εαν θεσης την φωλεαν σου αναμεσον των αστρων, και εκειθεν θελω σε καταβιβασει, λεγει Κυριος.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Al woon jy so hoog soos die arend en al was jou nes tussen die sterre gestel--daarvandaan sal Ek jou neerwerp, spreek die HERE.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nou te mèt bati kay nou byen wo tankou nich malfini, nou te mèt mete nich nou byen wo tankou si li te nan mitan zetwal yo, m'ap voye nou jete anba, m'ap fè nou desann. Se Seyè a menm ki di sa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Dầu ngươi lên cao như chim ưng , dầu ngươi lót_ổ giữa các ngôi_sao , ta cũng sẽ xô ngươi xuống khỏi đó , Ðức_Giê - hô-va phán vậy !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אם תגביה כנשר ואם בין כוכבים שים קנך משם אורידך נאם יהוה׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Though you mount on high as the eagle, and though your nest is set among the stars, I will bring you down from there," says Yahweh.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						పక్షిరాజు గూడంత యెత్తున నివాసము చేసికొని నక్షత్రములలో నీవు దాని కట్టినను అచ్చటనుండియు నేను నిన్ను క్రింద పడవేతును; ఇదే యెహోవా వాక్కు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Ако и да се издигнеш като орел И поставиш гнездото си между звездите, И от там ще те сваля, казва Господ.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Čeprav bi se visoko vznesel kakor orel in ako bi bilo med zvezdami postavljeno gnezdo tvoje: te potegnem doli od tam, govori GOSPOD.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						خداوند می‌گوید: اگرچه خویشتن را مثل عقاب بلند سازی و آشیانه خودرا در میان ستارگان بگذاری من تو را از آنجا فرودخواهم آورد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Bygger du end højt som Ørnen, er end din Rede blandt Stjerner, jeg styrter dig ned derfra, så lyder det fra HERREN.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Vaikka tekisit pesäsi korkealle niinkuin kotka ja vaikka sen sija  olisi tähtien välissä, minä syöksen sinut sieltä alas, sanoo Herra.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						你 雖如 大鷹高飛 、 在 星宿 之 間 搭窩 、 我 必從 那 裡 拉下 你來．這是 耶和華 說的
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Baa day ni ga ziji beene sanda zeeban cine, Baa ni fito go handariyayzey game ra ga sinji, Baa noodin kal ay ma ye ka ni zumandi ganda.» Yaadin no Rabbi ci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						你 雖 如 大 鷹 高 飛 、 在 星 宿 之 間 搭 窩 、 我 必 從 那 裡 拉 下 你 來 ． 這 是 耶 和 華 說 的 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						कौन मुझे भूमि पर उतार देगा? परन्तु चाहे तू उकाब की नाईं ऊंचा उड़ता हो, वरन तारागण के बीच अपना घोंसला बनाए हो, तौभी मैं तुझे वहां से नीचे गिराऊंगा, यहोवा की यही वाणी है।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Bys pak vysoko udělal jako orlice, nýbrž bys mezi hvězdami položil hnízdo své, i odtud strhnu tě, praví Hospodin.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed se vi ecx levigxus tiel alte, kiel aglo, aux se vi arangxus vian neston inter la steloj, ecx de tie Mi jxetos vin malsupren, diras la Eternulo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Edhe sikur ti të ngrihesh lart si një shqiponjë dhe ta vije folenë tënde midis yjeve, unë do të të zbres nga atje lart", thotë Zoti.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Anche se t'innalzassi come un'aquila e collocassi il tuo nido fra le stelle, di lassù ti farei precipitare, dice il Signore
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þótt þú sætir hátt eins og örninn og byggðir hreiður þitt meðal stjarnanna, þá steypi ég þér þaðan niður, - segir Drottinn. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						परमेश्वर, देव, असे म्हणतो, “जरी तू गरुडाप्रमाणे वर जातोस, आणि ताऱ्यांमध्यो घरटे बांधतोस, तरी मी तुला खाली आणील.”
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						たといあなたは、わしのように高くあがり、星の間に巣を設けても、わたしはそこからあなたを引きおろすと主は言われる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Aunque remontes vuelo como águila y entre las estrellas pongas tu nido, de allí te haré descender, dice Jehovah
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						In kastood meel kore fuushaan sida gorgorka, iyo in kastoo buulkiinna laga dhiso xiddigaha dhexdooda, halkaas waan idinka soo dejin doonaa, ayaa Rabbigu leeyahay.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Mu bangin sangpi ah leng tou mah lechin, na bu leng aksi laka seh hiomahleh, huai akipan ka hohla khe mai ding. TOUPAN a chi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನೀನು ಹದ್ದಿನಂತೆ ಏರಿಕೊಂಡು ನಿನ್ನ ಗೂಡನ್ನು ನಕ್ಷತ್ರಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಇಟ್ಟರೂ ಅಲ್ಲಿಂದ ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಇಳಿಸುವೆನೆಂದು ಕರ್ತನು ಅನ್ನುತ್ತಾನೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Though thou exalt thyself as the eagle, and though thou set thy nest among the stars, thence will I bring thee down, saith the LORD.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Bedrieg uzelf niet! Al vloog u zo hoog als een arend en bouwde u een nest tussen de sterren, Ik zou u daar vandaan naar beneden laten tuimelen", zegt de HERE.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Da se vineš k'o orao, gnijezdo sviješ među zvijezdama, i odande skinut ću te" - riječ je Jahvina.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Choćbyś się wywyższył jako orzeł, owszem, choćbyś między gwiazdami położył gniazdo twoje, i stamtąd cię stargnę, mówi Pan.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">แม้ว่าเจ้าเหินขึ้นไปสูงเหมือนนกอินทรี แม้ว่ารังของเจ้าอยู่ในหมู่ดวงดาวทั้งหลาย เราจะฉุดเจ้าลงมาจากที่นั่น พระเยโฮวาห์ตรัสดังนี้แหละ</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Bagaman ikaw ay pailanglang sa itaas na parang aguila, at bagaman ang iyong pugad ay malagay sa gitna ng mga bituin, aking ibababa ka mula roon, sabi ng Panginoon. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 たと い あなた は 、 わし の よう に 高 く あが り 、 星 の 間 に 巣 を 設け て も 、 わたし は そこ から あなた を 引きおろ す と 主 は 言 わ れ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നീ കഴുകനേപ്പോലെ ഉയര്‍ന്നാലും, നക്ഷത്രങ്ങളുടെ ഇടയില്‍ കൂടുവെച്ചാലും, അവിടെനിന്നു ഞാന്‍ നിന്നെ ഇറക്കും എന്നു യഹോവയുടെ അരുളപ്പാടു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Dar chiar dacă ai locui tot atît de sus ca vulturul, chiar dacă ţi-ai aşeza cuibul între stele, tot te voi arunca jos şi de acolo, zice Domnul``.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Wenn du gleich in die Höhe führest wie ein Adler und machtest dein Nest zwischen den Sternen, dennoch will ich dich von dort herunterstürzen, spricht der HERR.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Om du än byggde ditt näste så högt uppe som örnen, ja, om det än bleve förlagt mitt ibland stjärnorna, så skulle jag dock störta dig ned därifrån, säger HERREN.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">แม้ ว่า เจ้า เหิน ขึ้น ไป สูง เหมือน นก อินทรี แม้ ว่า รัง ของ เจ้า อยู่ ใน หมู่ ดวง ดาว ทั้งหลาย เรา จะ ฉุด เจ้า ลง มา จาก ที่ นั่น พระ เยโฮ วาห์ตรัส ดังนี้ แหละ</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						4
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.5" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Me i tae he kaitahae ki a koe, he kaipahua ranei i te po, taukiri e, tou ngaromanga! e kore ranei ratou e tahae, kia maha ra ano nga mea ma ratou? me i tae he kaiwhawhaki karepe ki a koe, e kore ranei etahi karepe e whakatoea e ratou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ngươi bị hủy diệt là thể nào! Nếu kẻ trộm hay là kẻ cướp ban đêm đến ngươi, thì há chẳng chỉ cướp lấy vừa đủ mà thôi sao? Nếu những người hái nho đến cùng ngươi, há chẳng để sót lại một vài buồng nho sao?
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Si des voleurs, des pillards, viennent de nuit chez toi, Comme te voilà dévasté! Mais enlèvent-ils plus qu`ils ne peuvent? Si des vendangeurs viennent chez toi, Ne laissent-ils rien à grappiller?...
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Raha, tahìny misy mpangalatra, na jiolahy alina, tonga ao aminao, (Indrisy, fongotra ianao!) Moa tsy izay hahafa-po azy ihany va no hangalariny ? Raha tahìny misy mpioty voaloboka tonga ao aminao, Moa tsy hamela voaloboka sisa hotsimponina va izy?
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						tolvajok  törnének reád, avagy éjjeli rablók, (hogy elpusztíttattál!), nem [annyit] lopnának-é, [a mennyi] elegendõ?! Ha szõlõszedõk jönnének reád, nem hagynának-é gerezdeket?!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ukuba amasela ebethe eza kuwe, ukuba amanyangaza ebethe eza ebusuku (hayi, ukunqunyulwa kwakho!), ebengayi kuba anele na?  Ukuba babethe beza kuwe abavuni beediliya, babengayi kushiya okungabhikicwayo na?
					</lang><lang id="Korean">혹시 도적이 네게 이르렀으며 강도가 밤중에 네게 이르렀을지라도 그 마음에 만족하게 취하면 그치지 아니하였겠느냐 혹시 포도를 따는 자가 네게 이르렀을지라도 그것을 얼마쯤 남기지 아니하였겠느냐 네가 어찌 그리 망하였는고</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jei vagys ir plėšikai įsilaužtų pas tave nakčia, argi jie nepaimtų, kiek jiems užtenka? Taip, tu nukentėsi! Jei vynuogių rinkėjai ateitų pas tave, argi jie nepaliktų kelių uogų?
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Не воры ли приходили к тебе? не ночные ли грабители, что ты так разорен? Но они украли бы столько, сколько надобно им. Если бы проникли к тебе обиратели винограда, то и они разве не оставили бы несколько ягод?
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Pencuri atau perampok yang datang di waktu malam, hanya mengambil yang diingininya. Orang yang memetik anggur di kebun, selalu menyisakan beberapa buah. Tetapi engkau disapu habis oleh musuh-musuhmu
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kong ang mga kawatan ming-anha kanimo, kong ang mga tulisan sa kagabhion (daw unsa ang imong pagkalaglag!), dili ba sila mangawat lamang hangtud nga sila adunay igo alang kanila? kong ang mga magpupopo sa parras ming-abut kanimo, dili ba nila biyaan ang halagdawon nga mga ubas?
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ညဉ့်အခါ သူခိုးထားပြတို့သည် သင်ရှိရာသို့ လာ လျှင်၊ စိတ်ပြေလောက်အောင်သာ ခိုးယူကြလိမ့်မည် မဟုတ်လော။ စပျစ်သီးကို ဆွတ်သောသူတို့သည် လာ လျှင်၊ သူတပါးလိုက်၍ ဆွတ်စရာဘို့ ကြွင်းစေကြလိမ့်မည် မဟုတ်လော။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Li Kâcuaß quixye: —Us raj chokß êre nak aj êlkß ta teßchâlk chiru kßojyîn chi elkßâc êriqßuin. Teßxcßam raj caßaj cuiß li joß qßuial teßraj. Ut cui teßxsicß li ru li uvas, ¿ma incßaß ta biß teßxcanab raj caßchßinak chic êre? Abanan, eb li xicß nequeßiloc êre, teßchâlk ut teßxsach êru chi junaj cua.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Keby prišli zlodeji na teba, keby lupiči vnoci - Oj, aký si zničený! -, či nenakradnú iba toľko, čo im je dosť? Keby prišli poberači hrozien na teba, či by nezanechali paberkov?
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमी साँच्चै नै सर्वनाश हुनेछौ! हेर यदि कुनै चोर तिमी कहाँ आए, जब राती डाकु आए, तिनीहरू आफ्नो निम्ति यथेष्ट हुने मात्र लुटेर जानेछ। यदि तिम्रो दाखको बारीमा दाख चोर्न आए दाख टिपी सकेपछि उसले पनि आफ्नो पछाडी केही नकेही छोडेर जान्छ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Kako si oplenjen?! Da su došli k tebi kradljivci ili lupeži noću, ne bi li pokrali koliko im je dosta? Da su došli k tebi berači vinogradski, ne bi li ostavili pabiraka?</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Om tyver kom til dig eller røvere om natten - å, hvor du blir tilintetgjort! - mon de da vilde stjele mere enn det de trengte? Om det kom til dig folk som vilde høste din vin, vilde de da ikke levne en efterhøst? 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    "Hırsızlar ya da haydutlar gece sana gelselerdi, Yalnızca gereksindiklerini çalmazlar mıydı? Üzüm toplayanlar bağına girseydi, Birkaç salkım bırakmazlar mıydı? Ama seni ne felaketler bekliyor; 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ان أتاك سارقون او لصوص ليل. كيف هلكت. أفلا يسرقون حاجتهم. ان أتاك قاطفون أفلا يبقون خصاصة.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Se a ti viessem ladrões, ou roubadores de noite (como estás destruído!), não furtariam somente o que lhes bastasse? se a ti viessem os vindimadores, não deixariam umas uvas de rabisco?
					</lang><lang id="Latin">si fures introissent ad te si latrones per noctem quomodo conticuisses nonne furati essent sufficientia sibi si vindemiatores introissent ad te numquid saltim racemos reliquissent tibi</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Εαν κλεπται ηρχοντο προς σε, εαν λησται δια νυκτος-πως εξηλειφθης-δεν ηθελον αρπασει το αρκουν εις αυτους; εαν τρυγηται ηρχοντο προς σε, δεν ηθελον αφησει επιφυλλιδας;
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 As daar diewe, as daar nagrowers na jou gekom het--hoe is jy vernietig! --sou hulle nie net soveel gesteel het as wat vir hulle genoeg was nie? As daar druiwesnyers na jou gekom het, sou hulle nie die na-oes laat oorbly het nie?
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Lè vòlò antre lakay moun lannwit pou piye, yo annik pran sa yo bezwen. Lè moun ap ranmase rekòt rezen, yo toujou kite dèyè pou moun k'ap vin grapiye yo. Men, gade jan lènmi ravaje nou nèt ale non
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ngươi bị hủy_diệt là thể_nào ! Nếu kẻ_trộm hay_là kẻ_cướp ban_đêm đến ngươi , thì há chẳng chỉ cướp lấy vừa đủ mà thôi sao ? Nếu những người hái nho đến_cùng ngươi , há chẳng để sót lại một_vài buồng nho sao ?
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אם גנבים באו לך אם שודדי לילה איך נדמיתה הלוא יגנבו דים אם בצרים באו לך הלוא ישאירו עללות׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">"If thieves came to you, if robbers by night--oh, what disaster awaits you--wouldn't they only steal until they had enough? If grape pickers came to you, wouldn't they leave some gleaning grapes?</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						చోరులే గాని రాత్రి కన్నము వేయువారే గాని నీ మీదికి వచ్చినయెడల తమకు కావలసినంతమట్టుకు దోచుకొందురు గదా. ద్రాక్ష పండ్లను ఏరువారు నీయొద్దకు వచ్చినయెడల పరిగె యేరు కొనువారికి కొంత యుండనిత్తురుగదా; నిన్ను చూడగా నీవు బొత్తిగా చెడిపోయియున్నావు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Ако дойдеха крадци при тебе, Или разбойници през нощ, (Как биде изтребен ти!) Нямаше ли да заграбят само колкото им е доволно? Ако гроздоберци дойдеха при тебе, Нямаше ли да оставят пабирък?
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ako bi prišli k tebi tatje ali razbojniki po noči, – kako si pokončan! – ali bi ne kradli, dokler bi jim bilo dovolj? Če bi trgači prišli k tebi, ali bi vsaj paberka ne popustili?
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اگر دزدان یا غارت کنندگان شب نزد تو آیند، (چگونه هلاک شدی )؟ آیا بقدرکفایت غارت نمی کنند؟ و اگر انگورچینان نزد توآیند آیا بعضی خوشه‌ها را نمی گذارند؟
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Du skulde vel ikke have Tyve til Gæster, natlige Voldsmænd? Hvor er du lagt øde; de stjæler jo alt, hvad de lyster! Du skulde vel ikke have Høstmænd i Vingården? Efterslæt levner de ikke!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Jos varkaat tulisivat kimppuusi, jos yölliset rosvot, kuinka voisit  tulla niin hävitetyksi: eivätkö he varastaisi vain sen, mitä  tarvitsevat? Jos viininkorjaajat tulisivat luoksesi, eivätkö he jättäisi  jälkikorjuuta?
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						盜賊 若 來 在 你 那裡 、 或強盜 夜間而來 、 （ 你 何 竟 被 剪除 ） 豈 不 偷 竊 直 到 彀了 呢 ． 摘葡萄 的 若來 到 你 那裡 、 豈 不 剩下 些 葡萄 呢
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 «Doŋ d'i ne zayyaŋ wala cin ra komkoyaŋ no ka kaa ni do, (kaari nin, ni halaci!) Manti haŋ kaŋ ga wasa i se no i ga zay? Da reyzin* kosukoyaŋ kaa ni do, Manti i ga fay da reyzin izeyaŋ kaŋ borey ga koobu? 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						盜 賊 若 來 在 你 那 裡 、 或 強 盜 夜 間 而 來 、 （ 你 何 竟 被 剪 除 ） 豈 不 偷 竊 直 到 彀 了 呢 ． 摘 葡 萄 的 若 來 到 你 那 裡 、 豈 不 剩 下 些 葡 萄 呢 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						यदि चोर- डाकू रात को तेरे पास आते, (हाय, तू कैसे मिटा दिया गया है!) तो क्या वे चुराए हुए धन से तृप्त होकर चले न जाते? और यदि दाख के तोड़नेवाले तेरे पास आते, तो क्या वे कहीं कहीं दाख न छोड़ जाते?
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Kterak jsi popléněn? Zdali zloději přišli na tebe? Zdali loupežníci noční? Zdaliž by kradli přes spotřebu svou? Kdyby ti, kteříž zbírají víno, přišli na tebe, zdaž by nepozůstavili aspoň paběrků?
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						CXu sxtelistoj venis al vi, aux noktaj rabistoj? kiamaniere vi estas tiel ruinigita? ili sxtelus nur tiom, kiom suficxus por ili. Se vinberkolektantoj venus al vi, ili restigus ja forgesitajn berojn.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						"Po të të vinin natën cuba ose kusarë, si do të shkatërroheshe! A nuk do të vidhnin aq sa u mjafton? Po të të vinin vjelësit e rrushit, a nuk do të linin disa vile për të mbledhur?
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Se entrassero da te ladri o predoni di notte, - come sarebbe finita per te! - non ruberebbero quanto basta loro? Se vendemmiatori venissero da te, non ti lascerebbero forse se non qualche grappolo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Ef þjófar koma að þér eða ræningjar á náttarþeli - hversu ert þú í eyði lagður -, stela þeir þá ekki, þar til er þeim nægir? Ef vínlestursmenn ráðast á þig, skilja þeir þá ekki eftir neinn eftirtíning? 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तुझा खरोखरीच नाश होईल. तुझ्याकडे चोर येतील. रात्री लुटारु येतील, ते चोर त्यांना पाहिजे ते सर्व नेतील. तुझ्या मळ्यातील द्राक्षे तोडताना मजूर काही द्राक्षे मागे ठेवतात.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						もし盗びとがあなたの所に来、強盗が夜きても、彼らは、ほしいだけ盗むではないか。ああ、あなたは全く滅ぼされてしまう。もしぶどうを集める者があなたの所に来たなら、彼らはなお余りの実を残さないであろうか。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Si hubieran venido a ti ladrones o asaltantes de noche, ¿no te habrían robado lo que les bastase? Si hubiesen venido a ti vendimiadores, ¿no habrían dejado siquiera rebuscos? Pero, ¡cómo has sido arrasado
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Haddii tuugag idiin soo dhici lahaayeen ama haddii shufto habeennimo idin miri lahayd, sow wax idinkama xadi lahayn jeeray wax ku filan la tagaan? (Sidee baad u ba'deen!) Haddii kuwa canabka gura idiin iman lahaayeen, sow kama tegi lahayn canab xaaxaab ah?
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Na kiangah gutate, suamhatte zanin hongpai le uh, (himan nak hih natel chia: ) a deih zah un a gu kei ding ua hia? na kiangah grep la khommite hongpai le uh, grep lak ding khenkhatte a nuse kei ding ua hia?
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಕಳ್ಳರು ನಿನ್ನ ಬಳಿಗೆ ಬಂದಿದ್ದರೆ ಸುಲುಕೊಳ್ಳುವವರು ರಾತ್ರಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಬಂದಿದ್ದರೆ ಎಷ್ಟೋ ಹಾಳಾಗುತ್ತಿದ್ದಿಯಲ್ಲಾ! ಅವರು ತಮಗೆ ಸಾಕಾಗುವಷ್ಟು ಕದ್ದುಕೊಳ್ಳುವರಲ್ಲವೋ? ದ್ರಾಕ್ಷೇಹಣ್ಣನ್ನು ಕೂಡಿಸುವ ವರು ನಿನ್ನ ಬಳಿಗೆ ಬಂದಿದ್ದರೆ ಅವರು ಕೆಲವು ದ್ರಾಕ್ಷೇ ಹಣ್ಣನ್ನು ಬಿಡುವರಲ್ಲವೋ?
					</lang><lang id="English">
						If thieves came to thee, if robbers by night, (how art thou cut off!) would they not have stolen till they had enough? if the grapegatherers came to thee, would they not leave some grapes?
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">"Het zou voor u veel beter zijn geweest als er 's nachts dieven waren gekomen om u te beroven. Want die zouden niet alles hebben meegenomen. U zou er zelfs meer bij gebaat zijn als uw wijngaarden waren geplunderd. Want dan zou altijd nog een restant zijn overgebleven.</lang><lang id="Croatian">"Dođu li k tebi lupeži il' kradljivci noćni, kako li ćeš biti oplijenjen! Neće li te okrasti po miloj volji? Dođu li trgači k tebi, zar će i pabirka ostaviti?</lang><lang id="Polish">
						O jakożeś zniszczony! Izaliż złodzieje przyszli na cię? Izali zbójcy nocni? Izaliby kradli nad potrzebę swoję? Gdyby ci na cię przyszli, co wino zbierają, izaliby nie zostawili którego grona?
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ถ้าขโมยเข้ามาหาเจ้า ถ้าพวกปล้นเข้ามาในเวลากลางคืน (เจ้าจะถูกทำลายสักเท่าใด) เขาจะไม่ขโมยเพียงพอแก่ตัวของเขาเท่านั้นหรือ ถ้าคนเก็บองุ่นมาหาเจ้า เขาจะไม่ทิ้งองุ่นตกค้างไว้บ้างหรือ</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Kung ang mga magnanakaw ay nagsiparoon sa iyo, kung mga mangloloob sa gabi (paano kang nahiwalay!) di baga sila sana'y nangagnakaw hanggang sa sila'y nangagkaroon ng sapat? kung mga mamimitas ng ubas ay nagsiparoon sa iyo, di baga sila sana'y nangagiwan ng laglag na ubas? 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 もし 盗 び と が あなた の 所 に 来 、 強盗 が 夜 き て も 、 彼 ら は 、 ほし い だけ 盗 む で は な い か 。 ああ 、 あなた は 全く 滅ぼ さ れ て しま う 。 もし ぶどう を 集め る 者 が あなた の 所 に 来 た なら 、 彼 ら は なお 余り の 実 を 残 さ な い で あ ろ う か 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						കള്ളന്മാര്‍ നിന്റെ അടുക്കല്‍ വന്നാലോ, രാത്രിയില്‍ പിടിച്ചുപറിക്കാര്‍ വന്നാലോ--നീ എങ്ങനെ നശിച്ചുപോയിരിക്കുന്നു--അവര്‍ തങ്ങള്‍ക്കു മതിയാകുവോളം മോഷ്ടിക്കയില്ലയോ? മുന്തിരിപ്പഴം പറിക്കുന്നവര്‍ നിന്റെ അടുക്കല്‍ വന്നാല്‍ അവര്‍ ഏതാനും കാലാപ്പഴം ശേഷിപ്പിക്കയില്ലയോ?
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Dacă ar fi intrat la tine nişte hoţi, sau nişte tîlhari de noapte, -cum eşti de pustiit! -ar fi luat ei oare mai mult decît ar fi putut? Dacă ar fi venit nişte culegători de vie la tine, n'ar fi lăsat ei niciun strugure pe urmă?
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Wenn Diebe oder Räuber zu Nacht über dich kommen werden, wie sollst du so zunichte werden! Ja, sie sollen genug stehlen; und wenn die Weinleser über dich kommen, so sollen sie dir kein Nachlesen übriglassen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						När tjuvar komma över dig, och rövare om natten, ja då är det förbi med dig. Sannerligen, de skola stjäla så mycket dem lyster. När vinbärgare komma över dig, sannerligen, en ringa efterskörd skola de lämna kvar.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ถ้า ขโมย เข้า มา หา เจ้า ถ้า พวก ปล้น เข้า มา ใน เวลา กลางคืน ( เจ้า จะ ถูก ทำลาย สัก เท่าใด ) เขา จะ ไม่ ขโมย เพียงพอ แก่ตัว ของ เขา เท่านั้น หรือ ถ้า คน เก็บ องุ่น มา หา เจ้า เขา จะ ไม่ ทิ้ง องุ่น ตกค้าง ไว้ บ้าง หรือ</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						5
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.6" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Taukiri e, te rapunga atu o nga mea a Ehau! te kimihanga o ana mea ngaro
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ê-sau đã bị lục soát là thể nào! Những đồ châu báu giấu kín của người đã bị khám xét là thể nào!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ah! comme Ésaü est fouillé! Comme ses trésors sont découverts!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Endrey ny fitady ny an'i Esao! Endrey ny fikatsaka ny hareny miafina!
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Mennyire kifosztogatták  Ézsaut; felkutatták rejtett kincseit!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Hayi, ukuphengululeka kwezinto zakwaEsawu! Hayi ukukhanukwa kwezinto zakhe eziqhushekiweyo!
					</lang><lang id="Korean">에서가 어찌 그리 수탐되었으며 그 감춘 보물이 어찌 그리 수탐 되었는고</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Kaip buvo apiplėštas Ezavas, iškasti jo paslėpti lobiai!
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Как обобрано все у Исава и обысканы тайники его!
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Hai keturunan Esau, engkau digeledah dan hartamu yang tersembunyi pun dijarah
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Giunsa ang pagsusi sa mga butang ni Esau! giunsa ang pagpangita sa iyang mga tinipigan nga bahandi!
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်သည် အလွန်ပျက်စီးပြီတကား။ ဧသော သည် အလွန်အစစ်ခံရပြီတကား။ သူဝှက်ထားသော ဥစ္စာ ကို အလွန်ရှာဖွေကြသည်တကား။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Chixjunil tâmakßekß chêru lâex li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú. Usta mukmûk raj êban li kßaxal lokß chêru, abanan teßxsicß toj retal teßxcßam chêru chixjunil.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Oj, aké sú prekutané veci Ezavove, prehľadané jeho poklady!
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तर हे एसाव! तिमीबाट तिम्रो सबै कुरो खोसिनेछ। मानिसहरूले लुकाएको सबै भण्डार खोजेर निकाल्नेछन्, अनि सबै भेट्उ नेछन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Kako se pretraži Isav, kako se nadjoše potaje njegove!</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men hvor blir ikke Esau ransaket, og hans skjulte skatter opsøkt! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Esav'ın her şeyi yağmalanacak, Gizli hazineleri ortaya çıkarılacak. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						كيف فتّش عيسو وفحصت مخابئه.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Como foram rebuscados os bens de Esaú! como foram esquadrinhados os seus tesouros ocultos!
					</lang><lang id="Latin">quomodo scrutati sunt Esau investigaverunt abscondita eius</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Πως εξηρευνηθη ο Ησαυ απεκαλυφθησαν οι κρυψωνες αυτου.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Hoe is Esau deursoek! Is sy verborge skatte deursnuffel!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Yo fouye toupatou nan peyi Ezaou a. Yo pran tout trezò nou te kache yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ê - sau đã bị lục_soát là thể_nào ! Những đồ châu_báu giấu kín của người đã bị khám_xét là thể_nào !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						איך נחפשו עשו נבעו מצפניו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">How Esau will be ransacked! How his hidden treasures are sought out!</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఏశావు సంతతి వారి సొమ్ము సోదా చూడబడును; వారు దాచి పెట్టిన ధనమంతయు పట్టబడును.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Но как е претърсен Исав! Как се откриха скривалищата му!
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kako je preiskano, kar je Ezavovega, kako so se našli skriti zakladi njegovi!
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						چیزهای عیسو چگونه تفتیش شده و چیزهای مخفی او چگونه تفحص گردیده است؟
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Hvor blev dog Esau ransaget, hans Skatte opsporet!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta kuinka onkaan Eesau läpikotaisin etsitty, hänen kätkönsä  pengotut!
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						以掃 的 隱密處 、 何 竟 被 搜尋 ． 他 隱藏 的 寶物 、 何竟 被 查出
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Guna ka di fintalyaŋ kaŋ cine i ga te Isuwa se! Guna ka di mate kaŋ cine i g'a arzaka tugantey ceeci nd'a! 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						以 掃 的 隱 密 處 、 何 竟 被 搜 尋 ． 他 隱 藏 的 寶 物 、 何 竟 被 查 出 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						परन्तु एसाव का धन कैसे खोजकर लूटा गया है, उसका गुप्त धन कैसे पता लगा लगाकर निकाला गया है!
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Jakť jsou vystiženy věci Ezau, vyhledáni pokladové jeho!
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kiel forte Esav estas prisercxita kaj liaj kasxejoj estas traesploritaj!
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Oh, sa do ta zhbirojnë Esaun, si do t'i rrëmojnë skutat e tij!
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Come è stato perquisito Esaù, come sono stati scovati i suoi nascondigli
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En hversu vandlega hefir verið leitað hjá Esaú og leitaðir uppi fólgnir dýrgripir hans. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						पण एसावचा लपविलेला खजिना शत्रू कसोशीने शोधेल. आणि त्यांना ते सर्व सापडेल.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						ああ、エサウはかすめられ、その隠しておいた宝は探り出される。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						¡Cómo fue saqueado Esaú; sus tesoros escondidos fueron saqueados
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Sidee baa loo dhacay alaabtii reer Ceesaw! Oo khasnadihiisii qarsoonaa sidee baa loo baadhay!
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Esau thilte zon khiak eita ve: A go baw, selgukte maikhiak eita ve:
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಏಸಾವನು ಎಷ್ಟೋ ಶೋಧಿ ಸಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿದ್ದಾನೆ, ಅವನ ರಹಸ್ಯ ಸ್ಥಳಗಳು ಹುಡುಕ ಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿವೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						How are the things of Esau searched out! how are his hidden things sought up!
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Alle verborgen schatten van Esau's nakomelingen zullen worden opgespoord en meegenomen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Kako li Edom bješe pretresen, skrivena mu skrovišta pretražena!</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Jakoż wyszpiegowane są skarby Ezaw, a wynalezione są skryte rzeczy jego.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ข้าวของของเอซาวได้ถูกรื้อค้นสักเท่าใดหนอ ทรัพย์สมบัติซึ่งซ่อนไว้ก็ถูกค้นไปหมด</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Paano nasiyasat ang mga bagay ng Esau! paano nasumpungan ang kaniyang mga kayamanang natago! 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 ああ 、 エサウ は かすめ られ 、 その 隠 し て お い た 宝 は 探り出 さ れ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഏശാവിന്നുള്ളവരെ കണ്ടുപിടിച്ചിരിക്കുന്നതും അവന്റെ നിക്ഷേപങ്ങളെ തിരഞ്ഞു കണ്ടിരിക്കുന്നതും എങ്ങനെ?
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Vai! Ce scormonit este Esau! Cum i s'au descoperit comorile!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Wie sollen sie dann Esau ausforschen und seine Schätze suchen!
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Huru genomsökt skall icke Esau bliva, huru skola ej hans dolda skatter letas fram!
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ข้าวของ ของ เอ ซาว ได้ ถูก รื้อ ค้น สัก เท่าใด หนอ ทรัพย์สมบัติ ซึ่ง ซ่อน ไว้ ก็ ถูก ค้น ไป หมด</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						6
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.7" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko nga tangata katoa o tau kawenata, kua riro koe i a ratou, tae rawa ki te rohe: ko nga tangata i mau nei ta ratou rongo ki a koe, kua tinihanga ki a koe, a taea ana koe e ratou; ko te hunga i kai i tau taro kua takoto i a ratou he mahanga ki ra ro i a koe: kahore he matauranga i a ia
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Mọi kẻ đồng minh cùng ngươi đã đuổi ngươi cho đến nơi bờ cõi. Những kẻ hòa thuận cùng ngươi, thì phỉnh ngươi, thắng hơn ngươi; còn những kẻ ăn bánh ngươi, thì đánh bẫy dưới ngươi; và người không có sự hiểu biết!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Tous tes alliés t`ont chassé jusqu`à la frontière, Tes amis t`ont joué, t`ont dominé, Ceux qui mangeaient ton pain t`ont dressé des pièges, Et tu n`as pas su t`en apercevoir!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ny olona rehetra izay vita fanekena taminao no nampandeha anao hatramin'ny sisin-tany; Izay tsara fihavanana aminao no namitaka ka naharesy anao; Izay mihinana ny haninao no namela-pandrika ao ambaninao Tsy misy fahalalana ao aminy!
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						A határig ûznek ki összes frigytársaid; megcsalnak, levernek szövetségeseid; kenyeredet tõrül vetik alád. Nincsen benne okosság!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Onke amadoda abenqophisene nawe akukhaphile, ada esa emdeni;  akulukuhlile, akweyisile amadoda abexolelene nawe. Isonka sakho asenze inxeba okulalwa ngalo, phantsi kwakho. Akukho kuqonda kuye.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">너와 약조한 자들이 다 너를 쫓아 변경에 이르게 하며 너와 화목하던 자들이 너를 속이고 이기며 네 식물을 먹는 자들이 네 아래 함정을 베푸니 네 마음에 지각이 없음이로다</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tavo sąjungininkai nustūmė tave iki sienos. Tie, kurie taikoje su tavimi, apgavo ir nugalėjo tave. Kurie valgė tavo duoną, spendė tau pinkles. Nėra jame supratimo.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						До границы выпроводят тебя все союзники твои, обманут тебя, одолеют тебя живущие с тобою в мире, ядущие хлеб твой нанесут тебе удар. Нет в нем смысла!
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Engkau ditipu oleh sekutu-sekutumu, dan diusir dari negerimu. Engkau dikalahkan oleh sahabat-sahabatmu, dijebak oleh orang yang makan bersamamu. Mereka bertanya-tanya tentang dirimu, 'Di mana kini segala kepandaiannya?
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ang tanang mga tawo nga sakup sa panagsangga nga imong gipangulohan maoy naghatud kanimo sa imong gipadulngan, bisan pa hangtud sa utlanan: ang mga tawo nga diha sa pakigdait uban kanimo nanaglimbong kanimo, ug nakadaug batok kanimo; sila nga nagaingon sa imong tinapay nanagbutang ug lit-ag sa ilalum nimo: walay salabutan diha kaniya.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်နှင့်မိဿဟာယဖွဲ့သော သူအပေါင်းတို့ သည် ပြည်စွန်းသို့ နှင်ကြပြီ။ အဆွေလုပ်သော သူတို့သည် သင့်ကို လှည့်စား၍ နိုင်ကြပြီ။ သင်နှင့်အတူ စားသောက် သောသူတို့သည် သင့်အောက်၌ ကျော့ကွင်းကို ထောင် ထားကြပြီ။ သင်၏ဥာဏ်ပညာ ကုန်ပြီ။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb li xnînkal ru tenamit li queßtenkßan êre junxil, xicß chic texril ut aßaneb ajcuiß teßisînk êre saß lê tenamit. Lê ramîg li nequeßcuaßac êriqßuin, xicß chic texril. Cßojcßo raj êchßôl riqßuineb, abanan aßaneb ajcuiß teßqßuehok li raßal re nak texchapekß chi incßaß têqßue retal.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Až k pomedziu ťa vyprevadia všetci tí mužovia, s ktorými máš smluvu; povedú ťa, zmocnia sa ťa mužovia, s ktorými máš pokoj! Tí, ktorí jedia tvoj chlieb, nastavia ti pascu! Nebude proti tomu rozumu.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिम्रा मित्र राष्ट्रहरूले तिमीलाई आक्रमण गर्छन् र सिमानाबाट तिमीलाई तान्छन्। तिनीहरू तिम्रा मित्रहरू हुन् भनी मानिएका छन्। तर तिनीहरूले तिमीलाई धोका दिन्छन् र तिमीलाई पराजय गर्छन्। ती जसले तिम्रो रोटी तिमीसित मिलेर खान्छन् तिनीहरूले तिम्रो विरूद्ध पड्‌यन्त्र गरिरहेका छन्। र तिमीलाई त्यो थाहासम्म पनि हुँदैन।”‘
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Do granice te odvedoše svi koji behu s tobom u veri, prevariše te i nadvladaše te koji behu u miru s tobom; koji jedu hleb tvoj podmetnuše ti zamku, da se ne opazi.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Like til grensen følger alle dine forbundsfeller dig; dine gode venner sviker dig og får overhånd over dig; de menn som eter ditt brød, legger en snare for dig. Det er ingen forstand hos ham! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Seninle antlaşma yapanların hepsi Seni toprağından sürecek. Güvendiğin insanlar Seni aldatıp yenilgiye uğratacak, Ekmeğini yiyenler sana tuzak kuracak Ve sen farkına varmayacaksın bile." 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						طردك الى التخم كل معاهديك. خدعك وغلب عليك مسالموك. اهل خبزك وضعوا شركا تحتك. لا فهم فيه.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Todos os teus confederados te levaram para fora dos teus limites; os que estavam de paz contigo te enganaram, e prevaleceram contra ti; os que comem o teu pão põem debaixo de ti uma armadilha; não há em Edom entendimento.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">usque ad terminum emiserunt te omnes viri foederis tui inluserunt tibi invaluerunt adversum te viri pacis tuae qui comedunt tecum ponent insidias subter te non est prudentia in eo</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Παντες οι ανδρες της συμμαχιας σου σε συνωδευσαν εως του οριου σου οι ανθρωποι, οιτινες ησαν εν ειρηνη μετα σου, σε ηπατησαν και υπερισχυσαν εναντιον σου οι τρωγοντες τον αρτον σου εβαλον ενεδραν υποκατω σου δεν υπαρχει συνεσις εν αυτω.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Al jou bondgenote het jou tot by die grens gestuur; die manne met wie jy vriendskap gehou het, het jou bedrieg, jou oorweldig; hulle lê 'n strik onder jou as jou brood. Daar is geen verstand in hom nie!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Tout moun ki te mete tèt ansanm avè nou yo woule nou byen woule. Yo mete nou deyò nan pwòp peyi nou an. Moun ki te pi bon zanmi nou yo twonpe nou byen twonpe. Moun ki te konn manje sou tab ansanm ak nou pare pèlen pou nou. Nou menm, nou pa menm wè sa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Mọi kẻ đồng_minh cùng ngươi đã đuổi ngươi cho đến_nơi bờ_cõi . Những kẻ hòa_thuận cùng ngươi , thì phỉnh ngươi , thắng hơn ngươi ; còn những kẻ ăn bánh ngươi , thì đánh bẫy dưới ngươi ; và người không có sự hiểu_biết !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						עד הגבול שלחוך כל אנשי בריתך השיאוך יכלו לך אנשי שלמך לחמך ישימו מזור תחתיך אין תבונה בו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">All the men of your alliance have brought you on your way, even to the border. The men who were at peace with you have deceived you, and prevailed against you. Friends who eat your bread lay a snare under you. There is no understanding in him."</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నీతో సంధిచేసిన వారు నిన్ను తమ సరిహద్దువరకు పంపివేయుదురు; నీతో సమాధాన ముగా ఉన్నవారు నిన్ను మోసపుచ్చి నీకు బలాత్కారము చేయుదురు; వారు నీ యన్నము తిని నీ కొరకు ఉరి యొడ్డుదురు; ఎదోమునకు వివేచన లేకపోయెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Всичките твои съюзни мъже Те изпратиха по пътя ти до границата; Човеците, които бяха в мир с тебе, те измамиха И преодоляха над тебе; Хлябът ти туриха за примка под тебе; А няма разум, за да се схване това.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Vsi zavezniki tvoji so te odpravili nazaj do meje; prekanili, premogli so te, ki so mir sklenili s teboj; kateri jedo kruh tvoj, so nastavili zadrgo pod tebe. Ni razuma pri njem.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						همه آنانی که با تو همعهد بودند تو را بسرحدفرستادند و صلح اندیشان تو، تو را فریب داده، برتو غالب آمدند و خورندگان نان تو دامی زیر توگستردند. در ایشان فطانتی نیست.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Alle dine Forbundsfæller jog dig lige til Grænsen, dine gode Venner sveg dig, tog Magten fra dig; for at skræmme dig lagde de Fælder under din Fod.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sinut on ajettu rajalle asti, kaikki liittolaisesi ovat sinut  pettäneet. Ystäväsi ovat vieneet sinusta voiton, ovat panneet  taritsemasi leivän paulaksi sinun eteesi. - Ei ole hänessä taitoa.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						與 你 結盟 的 、 都 送 你 上路 、 直到 交界 ． 與你 和 好的 、 欺騙 你 、 且勝過 你 ． 與你 一同 喫飯 的 設下 網羅 陷害 你 ． 在 你 心裡毫 無聰明
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ni amaana borey kulu ga ni gaaray ka koy hala hirro boŋ. Borey kaŋ yaŋ nin d'ey goono ga baani goray te, I ga ni fafagu, i ga te zaama ni boŋ mo. Ni ŋwaari ŋwaakoy, Ngey no goono ga hirrimiyaŋ daŋ ni cire, Ni mana bay a gaa mo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						與 你 結 盟 的 、 都 送 你 上 路 、 直 到 交 界 ． 與 你 和 好 的 、 欺 騙 你 、 且 勝 過 你 ． 與 你 一 同 喫 飯 的 設 下 網 羅 陷 害 你 ． 在 你 心 裡 毫 無 聰 明 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						जितनों ने तुझ से वाचा बान्धी थी, उन सभों ने तुझे सिवाने तक ढकेल दिया है; जो लोग तुझ से मेल रखते थे, वे तुझ को धोका देकर तुझ पर प्रबल हुए हैं; वे तेरी रोटी खाते हैं, वे तेरे लिये फन्दा लगाते हैं--  उस में कुछ समझ नहीं है।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Až ku pomezí vystrčí tě všickni, s kterýmiž smlouvu máš; podvedou tě, zmocní se tebe ti, s nimiž pokoj máš; náchlebníci tvoji udělajíť ránu zrádně, již nebude lze vyrozuměti.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Al la limo vin pusxis cxiuj viaj interliganoj, trompis kaj perfortis vin viaj amikoj; la mangxantoj de via pano metis sub vin kaptilon, kiun vi ecx ne rimarkis.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Tërë aleatët e tu do të të shtrëngojnë në kufi, ata që ishin në paqe me ty do të të mashtrojnë dhe do të kenë epërsi mbi ty; ata që hanë bukën tënde do të kurdisin gracka; por ai nuk e kupton këtë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ti hanno cacciato fino alla frontiera, tutti i tuoi alleati ti hanno ingannato, i tuoi amici ti hanno vinto, quelli che mangiavano il tuo pane ti hanno teso tranelli: in lui non c'è senno
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Allir sambandsmenn þínir reka þig út á landamærin. Þeir sem lifðu í friði við þig, draga þig á tálar, bera þig ofurliði. Þeir sem átu brauð þitt, leggja fyrir þig snörur, sem eigi er unnt að sjá. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तुझे मित्र असलेले लोकच तुला देशातून बळजबरीने बाहेर काढतील. तुझे मित्र तुला फसवतील व चुकीच्या गोष्टी करण्यासाठी तुझी खात्री करतील. युध्दात तुझ्याबरोबर असलेले सोबती तुझ्यासाठी सापळा रचायचा बेत करीत आहेत. ते म्हणतात, ‘ते तुझ्या लक्षात येणार नाही’.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたと契約を結んだ人々はみな、あなたを欺き、あなたを国境に追いやった。あなたと同盟を結んだ人々はあなたに勝った。あなたの信頼する友はあなたの下にわなを設けた、しかしその事を悟らない。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Hasta la frontera te arrojaron tus propios aliados. Te defraudaron y pudieron más que tus confidentes. Los que comían de tu pan te han puesto trampa. ¡No hay en él discernimiento
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kulli dadkii aad axdiga la lahaan jirteen oo dhammu waxay idinku celiyeen tan iyo soohdinta, oo dadkii nabadda idinla lahaan jiray ayaa idin khiyaanay, wayna idinka adkaadeen, oo kuwii kibistiina cuni jiray ayaa dabin idiin dhigay, oo innaba waxgarasho ma leh.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Namg lama pangte tengtengin gamgi hial nang a hontun ua: mi kituakte taka na om pihten nang a honkhem ua, honzouta uh ei ve; na tanghou neten na nuaiah thang a kam ua: amah ah theihsiamna himhim a om kei hi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನಿನ್ನ ಸಂಗಡ ಒಟ್ಟುಗೂಡಿದ ಮನುಷ್ಯರೆಲ್ಲರು ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಮೇರೆಯ ವರೆಗೂ ತಂದಿದ್ದಾರೆ: ನಿನ್ನ ಸಂಗಡ ಸಮಾಧಾನವಾಗಿದ್ದ ಮನುಷ್ಯರು ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಮೋಸ ಮಾಡಿ ನಿನಗೆ ವಿರೋಧವಾಗಿ ಜಯಹೊಂದಿದ್ದಾರೆ; ನಿನ್ನ ರೊಟ್ಟಿಯನ್ನು ತಿನ್ನುವರು ನಿನ್ನ ಕೆಳಗೆ ಬೋನು ಇಟ್ಟಿದ್ದಾರೆ; ಅವನಲ್ಲಿ ವಿವೇಕವೇನೂ ಇಲ್ಲ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						All the men of thy confederacy have brought thee even to the border: the men that were at peace with thee have deceived thee, and prevailed against thee; they that eat thy bread have laid a wound under thee: there is none understanding in him.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Al uw bondgenoten zullen zich tegen u keren en u uit uw land zetten. Zij zullen vrede beloven, maar zijn in werkelijkheid op uw ondergang uit. Uw beste vrienden zullen valstrikken voor u spannen en uw tegenmaatregelen zullen niets uithalen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Do granica te potjeraše, svi te saveznici tvoji prevariše, nadvladaše te tvoji prijatelji! Oni što kruh tvoj jedu zamku ti staviše: 'Sasvim je bez uma!'</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Aż do granicy wypchną cię wszyscy, z którymi masz przymierze; zdradzą cię, moc wezmą nad tobą ci, z którymi masz pokój; którzy chleb twój jedzą, ranęć zdradliwie zadadzą, tak, iż się nie obaczysz.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">พันธมิตรทั้งสิ้นของเจ้าได้ขับเจ้าไปถึงพรมแดน สหมิตรของเจ้าได้ล่อลวงเจ้า เขากลับสู้ชนะเจ้าเสียแล้ว มิตรที่กินข้าวหม้อเดียวกับเจ้าก็วางกับดักเจ้า เรื่องนี้ไม่มีใครเข้าใจอะไรเสียเลย</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Lahat na lalake na iyong kaalam ay dinala ka sa iyong lakad, hanggang sa hangganan: ang mga lalake na nangasa kapayapaan sa iyo ay dinaya ka, at nanaig laban sa iyo; silang nagsisikain ng iyong tinapay ay naglagay ng silo sa ilalim mo: walang paguunawa sa kaniya. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた と 契約 を 結 ん だ 人々 は みな 、 あなた を 欺 き 、 あなた を 国境 に 追いや っ た 。 あなた と 同盟 を 結 ん だ 人々 は あなた に 勝 っ た 。 あなた の 信頼 する 友 は あなた の 下 に わな を 設け た 、 しかし その 事 を 悟 ら な い 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിന്നോടു സഖ്യതയുള്ളവരൊക്കെയും നിന്നെ അതിരോളം അയച്ചുകളഞ്ഞു; നിന്നോടു സന്ധിയുള്ളവര്‍ നിന്നെ ചതിച്ചു തോല്പിച്ചിരിക്കുന്നു; നിന്റെ ആഹാരം ഭക്ഷിക്കുന്നവര്‍ നിനക്കു കണിവെക്കുന്നു; അവന്നു ബുദ്ധി ഒട്ടും ഇല്ല.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Toţi cei uniţi cu tine te-au izgonit înapoi pînă la hotar, prietenii tăi te-au înşelat şi te-au stăpînit. Cei ce mîncau din pînea ta ţi-au întins curse, pe cari nu le-ai băgat de seamă!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Alle deine eigenen Bundesgenossen werden dich zum Lande hinausstoßen; die Leute, auf die du deinen Trost setztest, werden dich betrügen und überwältigen; die dein Brot essen, werden dich verraten, ehe du es merken wirst.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ut till gränsen skola de driva dig, alla dina bundsförvanter; dina vänner skola svika dig och skola taga väldet över dig. I stället för att giva dig bröd skola de lägga en snara på din väg, där du icke kan märka den.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">พันธมิตร ทั้งสิ้น ของ เจ้า ได้ ขับ เจ้า ไป ถึง พรมแดน ส หมิตร ของ เจ้า ได้ ล่อลวง เจ้า เขา กลับ สู้ ชนะ เจ้า เสีย แล้ว มิตร ที่ กิน ข้าว หม้อ เดียว กับ เจ้า ก็ วาง กับ ดัก เจ้า เรื่อง นี้ ไม่ มี ใคร เข้าใจ อะไร เสีย เลย</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						7
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.8" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						He teka ianei, e ai ta Ihowa, ka kore i ahau i taua ra nga tangata whakaaro nui i roto i Eroma, me te matauranga o te maunga o Ehau
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ðức Giê-hô-va phán: Trong ngày đó, ta há chẳng diệt những kẻ khôn khỏi xứ Ê-đôm, và những người thông sáng khỏi núi Ê-sau sao?
					</lang><lang id="French">
						N`est-ce pas en ce jour, dit l`Éternel, Que je ferai disparaître d`Édom les sages, Et de la montagne d`Ésaü l`intelligence?
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Moa tsy amin'izany andro izany va, hoy Jehovah, no hamongorako ny olon-kendry ao Edoma, Sy ny manan-tsaina ao an-tendrombohitr'i Esao?
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Azon a napon, ezt mondja az Úr, nem vesztem-é ki a bölcseket  Edomból, és az értelmet az Ézsau hegyérõl?!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Andiyi kuthi na ngaloo mini, utsho uYehova,  ndizitshabalalise izilumko kwaEdom, neengqondi ezintabeni zakwaEsawu?
					</lang><lang id="Korean">나 여호와가 말하노라 그 날에 내가 에돔에서 지혜 있는 자를 멸하며 에서의 산에서 지각 있는 자를 멸하지 아니하겠느냐</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tą dieną,­sako Viešpats,­Aš išnaikinsiu Edomo išminčius ir protinguosius Ezavo kalne.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Не в тот ли день это будет, говорит Господь, когда Я истреблю мудрых в Едоме и благоразумных на горе Исава?
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Pada hari Aku menghukum Edom, orang-orangnya yang bijaksana Kubinasakan. Dan segala hikmat mereka akan hilang, tiada bekasnya
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Niadtong adlawa, miingon si Jehova: Dili ba laglagon ko ang mga tawo nga makinaadmanon sa Edom, ug ang mga tawo nga masinabuton dili ba laglagon ko sa bukid ni Esau?
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထာဝရဘုရား မိန့်တော်မူသည်ကား၊ ထိုကာလ ၌ ဧဒုံပြည်မှ ပညာရှိတို့ကို၎င်း၊ ဧသော၏တောင်မှ ဥာဏ် ကောင်းသော သူတို့ကို၎င်း ငါပယ်ရှားမည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Li Kâcuaß quixye: —Nak tebinqßue chixtojbal rix lix mâqueb laj Edom, tinsach ruheb li cuanqueb xnaßleb saß xyânkeb aßan. Lâin tinsach ruheb laj qßuehol naßleb li cuanqueb saß li tzûl saß lix naßajeb li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Či nebude toho dňa tak, hovorí Hospodin, že vyhubím múdrych z Edoma a rozumnosť s vrchu Ezavovho?
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						परमप्रभु भन्नुहुन्छ, “त्यस दिन एदोमको बुद्धिमानी मानिसहरूलाई नष्ट पार्नेछु अनि एसावको पहाडबाट समझदार मानिसहरूलाई नष्ट पार्नेछु।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">U onaj dan, govori Gospod, neću li pogubiti mudre u zemlji edemskoj i razumne u gori Isavovoj?</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Skal jeg ikke på den dag, sier Herren, gjøre ende på alle vismenn i Edom og all forstand på Esaus berg? 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    RAB diyor ki, "O gün Edom'un bilge adamlarını, Esav'ın dağlarındaki bilgiçleri yok edeceğim. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ألا أبيد في ذلك اليوم يقول الرب الحكماء من ادوم والفهم من جبل عيسو.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Acaso não acontecerá naquele dia, diz o Senhor, que farei perecer os sábios de Edom, e o entendimento do monte de Esaú?
					</lang><lang id="Latin">numquid non in die illa dicit Dominus perdam sapientes de Idumea et prudentiam de monte Esau</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Εν τη ημερα εκεινη, λεγει Κυριος, δεν θελω απολεσει και τους σοφους απο του Εδωμ και την συνεσιν απο του ορους του Ησαυ;
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Sal Ek nie in dié dag, spreek die HERE, die wyse manne uit Edom verdelg nie en die verstand uit die gebergte van Esau?
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Seyè a di konsa: -Jou m'ap pini moun Edon yo, m'ap disparèt tout moun ki gen bon konprann nan peyi a, tout moun lespri ki rete sou mòn Ezaou a
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ðức_Giê - hô-va phán : Trong ngày đó , ta há chẳng diệt những kẻ khôn khỏi xứ Ê - đôm , và những người thông sáng khỏi núi Ê - sau sao ?
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						הלוא ביום ההוא נאם יהוה והאבדתי חכמים מאדום ותבונה מהר עשו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">"Won't I in that day," says Yahweh, "destroy the wise men out of Edom, and understanding out of the mountain of Esau?</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఆ దినమందు ఏశావు పర్వతములలో వివేచన లేకపోవునట్లు ఎదోములోనుండి జ్ఞానులను నాశముచేతును; ఇదే యెహోవా వాక్కు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						В оня ден, казва Господ, Няма ли да погубя мъдрите от Едом, И благоразумието от Исавовия хълм?
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ne pogubim li tisti dan, govori GOSPOD, modrih iz Edoma in razumnosti z gore Ezavove?
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						خداوند می‌گوید: آیا در آن روز حکیمان ادوم را و فطانت را از کوه عیسو نابود نخواهم گردانید؟
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Visselig vil jeg på hin Dag, lyder det fra HERREN, udrydde de vise af Edom og Klogskab af Esaus Bjerge.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Totisesti, sinä päivänä, sanoo Herra, minä lopetan viisaat Edomista  ja taidon Eesaun vuorelta.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						耶和華 說 、 到 那日 、 我豈不從以東 除滅 智慧 人 、 從以掃山 除 滅聰 明人
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Manti zaari woodin ra no ay ga laakalkooney halaci Edom ra, Da fahamantey mo Isuwa tondi kuuko ra?» Yaadin no Rabbi ci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						耶 和 華 說 、 到 那 日 、 我 豈 不 從 以 東 除 滅 智 慧 人 、 從 以 掃 山 除 滅 聰 明 人 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						यहोवा की यह वाणी है, क्या मैं उस समय एदोम में से बुद्धिमानों को, और एसाव के पहाड़ में से चतुराई को नाश न करूंगा?
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Zdaliž v ten den, praví Hospodin, nevyhladím moudrých z země Idumejské, a rozumných s hory Ezau?
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						En tiu tempo, diras la Eternulo, Mi pereigos ja la sagxulojn cxe Edom kaj la prudenton sur la monto de Esav.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Atë ditë", thotë Zoti, "unë do të zhduk nga Edomi njerëzit e ditur dhe nga mali i Esaut mënçurinë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Forse in quel giorno, dice il Signore, non disperderò i saggi da Edom e l'intelligenza dal monte di Esaù
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Já, á þeim degi - segir Drottinn - mun ég afmá vitra menn í Edóm og hyggindin á Esaúfjöllum. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						परमेश्वर म्हणतो, “त्याच दिवशी, मी अदोममधील सुज्ञांचा नाश करीन. एसावच्या पर्वतातून समजूत नष्ट करीन.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						主は言われる、その日には、わたしはエドムから知者を滅ぼし、エサウの山から悟りを断ち除かないだろうか。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						"¿No haré que perezcan en aquel día los sabios de Edom y el discernimiento de la región montañosa de Esaú?, dice Jehovah
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Rabbigu wuxuu leeyahay, Wakhtigaas ragga xigmadda leh sow kama aan baabbi'in doono reer Edom oo waxgarashadana sow kama baabbi'in doono buurta Ceesaw?
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huai ni chiangin Edom akipan mi pilte ka hihmangin, Esau tang akipan theihsiamna ka hihmang kei dia hia? TOUPAN a chi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಕರ್ತನು ಅನ್ನುವದೇನಂದರೆ--ನಾನು ಆ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಎದೋಮಿ ನೊಳಗಿಂದ ಜ್ಞಾನಿಗಳನ್ನೂ ಏಸಾವನ ಬೆಟ್ಟದೊಳಗಿಂದ ವಿವೇಕವನ್ನೂ ನಾಶಮಾಡದಿರುವೆನೋ?
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Shall I not in that day, saith the LORD, even destroy the wise men out of Edom, and understanding out of the mount of Esau?
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Op die dag", zegt de HERE, "zal in Edom geen enkele wijze man (B) meer worden gevonden. Want Ik zal de wijze mannen van Edom vullen met onverstand.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Neću li u dan onaj - riječ je Jahvina - uništit' mudraca u Edomu i razum iz gore Ezavljeve?</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Izali dnia onego, mówi Pan, nie wytracę mędrców z Edom, a roztropnych z góry Ezawa?
					</lang><lang id="Thai">พระเยโฮวาห์ตรัสว่า ในวันนั้นเราจะไม่ทำลายคนฉลาดให้สิ้นไปจากเอโดม และทำลายความเข้าใจเสียจากภูเขาเอซาวหรือ</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Di ko baga lilipulin sa araw na yaon, sabi ng Panginoon, ang mga pantas na tao sa Edom, at papawiin ang unawa sa bundok ng Esau? 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 主 は 言 わ れ る 、 その 日 に は 、 わたし は エドム から 知者 を 滅ぼ し 、 エサウ の 山 から 悟り を 断 ち 除 か な い だ ろ う か 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അന്നാളില്‍ ഞാന്‍ എദോമില്‍നിന്നു ജ്ഞാനികളെയും ഏശാവിന്റെ പര്‍വ്വതത്തില്‍ നിന്നു വിവേകത്തെയും നശിപ്പിക്കും എന്നു യഹോവയുടെ അരുളപ്പാടു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						,,Oare, zice Domnul, nu voi pierde Eu în ziua aceea pe cei înţelepţi din Edom, şi princeperea din muntele lui Esau?
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Was gilt's? spricht der HERR, ich will zur selben Zeit die Weisen zu Edom zunichte machen und die Klugheit auf dem Gebirge Esau.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Sannerligen, på den dagen, säger HERREN skall jag förgöra de vise i Edom och allt förstånd på Esaus berg.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">พระ เยโฮ วาห์ตรัส ว่า ใน วัน นั้น เรา จะ ไม่ ทำลาย คน ฉลาด ให้ สิ้น ไป จาก เอ โดม และ ทำลาย ความ เข้าใจ เสีย จาก ภูเขา เอ ซาว หรือ</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						8
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.9" langNo="59"><lang id="Maori">
						A ka wehi ou marohirohi, e Temana, he mea e hatepea atu ai nga tangata katoa o te maunga o Ehau, tukituki rawa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Hỡi Thê-man, những lính-chiến của ngươi sẽ thất kinh, hầu cho ai nấy bị trừ khỏi núi Ê-sau trong lúc giết lát.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Tes guerriers, ô Théman, seront dans l`épouvante, Car tous ceux de la montagne d`Ésaü périront dans le carnage.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary ho raiki-tahotra ny lehilahy maherinao, ry Temana, Mba haringana amin'ny vonoana ho foana ny any an-tendrombohitr'i Esao.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						És megrémülnek a te vitézeid, oh Témán! hogy kiirtassék mindenki az Ézsau hegyérõl az öldöklés  által.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Aya kuqhiphuka umbilini amagorha akho, Teman, ukuze banqanyulwe bonke ezintabeni zakwaEsawu ngokubulawa.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">드만아 네 용사들이 놀랄 것이라 이로 인하여 에서의 산의 거민이 살륙을 당하여 다 멸절되리라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Temane, išsigąs tavo karžygiai, kad visi Ezavo kalne galėtų būti išžudyti.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Поражены будут страхом храбрецы твои,Феман, дабы все на горе Исава истреблены были убийством.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Para pejuang dari Teman akan ketakutan, dan semua prajurit Edom akan tewas.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug ang imong mga gamhanang tawo, Oh Teman, mangaluya sa kahadlok, sa tuyo nga ang tagsatagsa pagaputlon gikan sa bukid ni Esau pinaagi sa pagpamatay.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အိုတေမန်မြို့၊ ဧသော၏တောင်မှ ခပ်သိမ်းသော သူတို့ကို ပယ်ဖြတ်မည်အကြောင်း၊ သင်၏ သူရဲတို့သည် ကြောက်ကြလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Sicsotkeb xbaneb xxiu li cauheb rib chi pletic saß li tenamit Temán. Ut telajeßsachekß ruheb chixjunileb li cuanqueb saß li tzûl saß lix naßajeb li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A tvoji udatní sa budú desiť, Témane, aby bol vyťatý človek s vrchu Ezavovho pre vraždu.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali"></lang><lang id="Serbian">I tvoji će se junaci uplašiti, Temane, da se istrebe pokoljem svi iz gore Isavove.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Dine kjemper, Teman, skal bli motløse, så hver mann blir drept og utryddet på Esaus berg. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Ey Teman, yiğitlerin öyle bir korkuya kapılacak ki, Esav'ın dağlarında bulunanların hepsi Kıyıma uğrayıp yok olacak. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						فيرتاع ابطالك يا تيمان لكي ينقرض كل واحد من جبل عيسو بالقتال
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						E os teus valentes, ó Temã, estarão atemorizados, para que do monte de Esaú seja cada um exterminado pela matança.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et timebunt fortes tui a meridie ut intereat vir de monte Esau</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Και οι μαχηται σου, Θαιμαν, θελουσι πτοηθη, δια να εκκοπη εν σφαγη πας ανθρωπος εκ του ορους του Ησαυ.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En jou helde sal verskrik wees, o Teman, sodat elkeen deur moord uit die gebergte van Esau uitgeroei sal word.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Sòlda lavil Teman yo pral tranble nan kanson yo. Yo pral masakre tout gason peyi Edon ki konn goumen
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Hỡi_Thê - man , những lính - chiến của ngươi sẽ thất_kinh , hầu cho ai_nấy bị trừ khỏi núi Ê - sau trong lúc giết lát .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						וחתו גבוריך תימן למען יכרת איש מהר עשו מקטל׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Your mighty men, Teman, will be dismayed, to the end that everyone may be cut off from the mountain of Esau by slaughter.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						తేమానూ, నీ బలాఢ్యులు విస్మయ మొందుదురు, అందువలన ఏశావుయొక్క పర్వత నివాసు లందరు హతులై నిర్మూలమగుదురు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						И твоите военни мъже, Темане, ще се уплашат, За да се изтреби с клане всеки човек от Исавовите хълми.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In tvoji junaki, o Teman, izgube pogum, zato da bo vsakdo iztrebljen z gore Ezavove v moritvi.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و جباران تو‌ای تیمان هراسان خواهندشد تا هر کس از کوه عیسو به قتل منقطع شود.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Da skal dine Helte lammes at Rædsel, o Teman, og hver en Mand ryddes ud at Esaus Bjerge.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Ja sinun sankarisi, Teeman, kauhistuvat, niin että viimeinenkin mies  häviää Eesaun vuorelta murhatöitten tähden.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						提幔 哪 、 你 的 勇士 必 驚惶 、 甚 致以 掃山 的 人 、 都 被 殺戮 剪除
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 «Ya Teman, ni yaarukomey ga gartu, Hal i ma afo kulu tuusu ka kaa Isuwa tondi kuuko ra da wiyaŋ. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						提 幔 哪 、 你 的 勇 士 必 驚 惶 、 甚 致 以 掃 山 的 人 、 都 被 殺 戮 剪 除 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						और हे तेमान, तेरे शूरवीरों का मन कच्चा न हो जाएगा, और यों एसाव के पहाड़ पर का हर एक पुरूष घात होकर नाश हो जाएगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						I budou se děsiti udatní tvoji, ó Temane, proto, že poraženi jsouce, vypléněni budou všickni s hory Ezau.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Ektimos viaj kuragxuloj, ho Teman, por ke cxiuj sur la monto de Esav estu ekstermitaj per mortigo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Atëherë trimat e tu do t'i zërë tmerri, o Teman, derisa çdo njeri të shfaroset nga mali i Esaut në masakër.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Saranno fiaccati i tuoi prodi, o Teman, e sarà sterminato ogni uomo dal monte di Esaù. Per la carneficin
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Kappar þínir, Teman, skulu skelfast, til þess að hver maður verði upprættur af Esaúfjöllum í manndrápunum. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi"></lang><lang id="Japanese">
						テマンよ、あなたの勇士は驚き恐れる。人はみな殺されてエサウの山から断ち除かれる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Tus valientes, oh Temán, serán destrozados, para que todo hombre sea destruido por la masacre en los montes de Esaú
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Reer Teemaanow, raggiinna xoogga badanu way wada nixi doonaan, oo sidaas daraaddeed mid kasta oo buurta Ceesaw ka yimid ayaa laynta ku go'i doona.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Aw Teman, Esau tang akipan mi chih thahgama a om vekna ding un, na mi hatte nakpi takin a lunglel ding uh.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಸರ್ವರು ಸಂಹಾರದಿಂದ ಏಸಾವನ ಬೆಟ್ಟದೊಳಗಿಂದ ನಾಶ ವಾಗುವ ಹಾಗೆ ಓ ತೇಮಾನೇ, ನಿನ್ನ ಪರಾಕ್ರಮ ಶಾಲಿಗಳು ಗಾಬರಿಪಡುವರು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And thy mighty men, O Teman, shall be dismayed, to the end that every one of the mount of Esau may be cut off by slaughter.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Ook de dappere soldaten uit Teman zullen verbijsterd zijn en niets kunnen doen om de slachtpartij op de bergen van Edom te voorkomen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Ratnike tvoje, Temane, užas će spopasti, i posljednji će biti istrijebljen na gori Ezavljevoj." "Za pokolj</lang><lang id="Polish">
						I ulękną się mocarze twoi, o Temanie! dlatego, że porażeni będąc wygubieni będą wszyscy z góry Ezawa.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">โอ เทมานเอ๋ย ชายผู้มีกำลังทั้งหลายของเจ้าจะขยาด จนในที่สุดทุกคนที่มาจากภูเขาเอซาวจะถูกตัดขาดเสียด้วยการสังหาร</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang iyong mga makapangyarihang tao, Oh Teman, ay manglulupaypay, palibhasa'y bawa't isa'y mahihiwalay sa bundok ng Esau sa pamamagitan ng patayan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 テマン よ 、 あなた の 勇士 は 驚き 恐れ る 。 人 は みな 殺 さ れ て エサウ の 山 から 断 ち 除 か れ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഏശാവിന്റെ പര്‍വ്വതത്തില്‍ ഏവനും കുലയാല്‍ ഛേദിക്കപ്പെടുവാന്‍ തക്കവണ്ണം തേമാനേ, നിന്റെ വീരന്മാര്‍ ഭ്രമിച്ചുപോകും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Vitejii tăi, Temane, se vor spăimînta, pentruca toţi cei din muntele lui Esau să piară în măcel.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und deine Starken zu Theman sollen zagen, auf daß alle auf dem Gebirge Esau ausgerottet werden durch Morden.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Dina hjältar, o Teman, skola då bliva slagna av förfäran; och så skall var man på Esaus berg bliva utrotad och dräpt.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">โอ เท มาน เอ๋ย ชาย ผู้ มี กำลัง ทั้งหลาย ของ เจ้า จะ ขยาด จน ใน ที่สุด ทุก คน ที่มา จาก ภูเขา เอ ซาว จะ ถูก ตัดขาด เสีย ด้วย การ สังหาร</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						9
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.10" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ka taupokina koe e te whakama hei utu mo te mahi tutu ki tou teina, ki a Hakopa, ka hatepea atu ano koe a ake ake
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ấy là vì cớ sự hung bạo ngươi đối với anh em ngươi là Gia-cốp, mà ngươi sẽ mang hổ, và bị diệt đời đời!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						A cause de ta violence contre ton frère Jacob, Tu seras couvert de honte, Et tu seras exterminé pour toujours.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Noho ny fampahoriana an'i Jakoba rahalahinao dia ho voasaron-kenatra ianao Ka ho fongotra mandrakizay.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Jákób öcséd ellen [elkövetett] erõszakért  szégyen borul reád, és kivágatol mindörökre!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ngenxa yokumgonyamela kwakho umninawa wakho uYakobi, kuya kukugubungela ukudana, unqanyulwe ngonaphakade.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">네가 네 형제 야곱에게 행한 포학을 인하여 수욕을 입고 영원히 멸절되리라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Už tavo broliui Jokūbui padarytą smurtą būsi sunaikintas amžiams.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						За притеснение брата твоего, Иакова, покроет тебя стыд и ты истреблен будешь навсегда.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						"Engkau telah berlaku kejam terhadap saudara-saudaramu keturunan Yakub. Sebab itu engkau akan dibinasakan, dan dicela orang sepanjang zaman
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Tungod sa pagpanlupig nga imong gihimo sa imong igsoon nga si Jacob, ang kaulaw magatabon kanimo, ug ikaw pagaputlon sa walay katapusan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်သည် ညီယာကုပ်ကို အသေသတ်ခြင်း၊ အနိုင်အထက်ပြုခြင်းအပြစ်ကြောင့် ကိုယ်တိုင်အရှက်ကွဲ ၍၊ အကုန်အစင်ပယ်ဖြတ်ခြင်းကို ခံရလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Lâex aj Edom, ralal xcßajolex laj Esaú, tâcßutekß êxutân ut texsachekß chi junaj cua xban li mâusilal li quebânu reheb li ralal xcßajol laj Jacob, li rîtzßin lê xeßtônil yucuaß.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Pre ukrutnosť, ktorú si páchal na svojom bratovi Jakobovi, pokryje ťa hanba, a budeš vyťatý na večnosť.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमी लाजले पूरिने छौ अनि तिमी सधैंको निम्ति नष्ट हुनेछौ। किनकि आफ्नो भाइ याकूब प्रति तिमी अत्यन्तै निर्दयी भयौ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Za nasilje učinjeno bratu tvom Jakovu pokriće te stid i istrebićeš se zasvagda.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						For den vold du har gjort mot din bror Jakob, skal skam dekke dig, og du skal bli utryddet til evig tid. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    "Yakup soyundan gelen kardeşlerine Yaptığın zorbalıktan ötürü utanca boğulacak Ve sonsuza dek yok olacaksın. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						من اجل ظلمك لاخيك يعقوب يغشاك الخزي وتنقرض الى الابد.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Por causa da violência feita a teu irmão Jacó, cobrir-te-á a confusão, e serás exterminado para sempre.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">propter interfectionem et propter iniquitatem in fratrem tuum Iacob operiet te confusio et peribis in aeternum</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Δια την αδικιαν την προς τον αδελφον σου Ιακωβ θελει σε καλυψει αισχυνη και θελεις εκκοπη διαπαντος.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Weens die geweld teen jou broer Jakob gepleeg, sal skande jou bedek, en jy sal uitgeroei word vir ewig.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Paske nou te masakre pitit pitit Jakòb yo, kouzen nou yo, paske nou te fè yo anpil mechanste, yo pral fè nou wont, yo pral disparèt nou nèt
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ấy_là vì cớ sự hung_bạo ngươi đối_với anh_em ngươi là Gia-cốp , mà ngươi sẽ mang hổ , và bị diệt đời_đời !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						מחמס אחיך יעקב תכסך בושה ונכרת לעולם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">For the violence done to your brother Jacob, shame will cover you, and you will be cut off forever.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నీ సహోదరులైన యాకోబు సంతతికి నీవు చేసిన బలాత్కారమును బట్టి నీవు అవమానము నొందుదువు, ఇక నెన్నటికిని లేకుండ నీవు నిర్మూలమగుదువు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Поради насилието, което ти извърши на брата си Якова, Срам ще те покрие, И ще бъдеш изтребен за всегда.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Zavoljo silovitosti, storjene bratu tvojemu Jakobu, te pokrije sramota in iztrebljen boš na vekomaj.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						به‌سبب ظلمی که بر برادرت یعقوب نمودی، خجالت تو را خواهد پوشانید و تا به ابد منقطع خواهی شد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						For Drab og Vold mod din Broder Jakob skal du skjules af Skam; udryddes skal du for evigt,
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Väkivallan tähden veljeäsi Jaakobia kohtaan peittää sinut häpeä, ja  sinut hävitetään ikiajoiksi.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						因 你 向 兄弟 雅各 行 強暴 、 羞愧 必 遮 蓋 你 、 你 也 必 永遠斷絕
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ni nya-izo Yakuba toonya kaŋ ni te a se din sabbay se, Haawi ga ni daabu, i ga ni halaci mo hal abada. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						因 你 向 兄 弟 雅 各 行 強 暴 、 羞 愧 必 遮 蓋 你 、 你 也 必 永 遠 斷 絕 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						हे एसाव, एक उपद्रव के कारण जो तू ने अपने भाई याकूब पर किया, तू लज्जा से ढंपेगा; और सदा के लिये नाश हो जाएगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Pro nátisk bratru tvému Jákobovi činěný přikryje tě hanba, a vypléněn budeš na věčnost.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Pro tio, ke vi premis vian fraton Jakob, kovros vin honto, kaj vi estos ekstermita por cxiam.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Për shkak të dhunës kundër vëllait tënd Jakob, turpi do të të mbulojë dhe do të shfarosesh përjetë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						e la violenza contro Giacobbe tuo fratello la vergogna ti coprirà e sarai sterminato per sempre
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Sökum ofríkis þess, er þú hefir sýnt bróður þínum Jakob, skal smán hylja þig, og þú skalt að eilífu upprættur verða. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तू अप्रतिष्ठेने माखशील. आणि तुझा कायमचा नाश होईल. का? कारण तू, तुझा भाऊ याकोब याच्याशी क्रूरपणे वागलास.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたはその兄弟ヤコブに暴虐を行ったので、恥はあなたをおおい、あなたは永遠に断たれる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						"Por la violencia hecha a tu hermano Jacob, te cubrirá la vergüenza, y serás destruido para siempre
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Xumaantii aad walaalihiin reer Yacquub ku samayseen aawadeed ayaa ceebu idiinku degi doonta, oo weligiin baad go'naan doontaan.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Na Unaupa Jakob tunga na hiamgamna jiakin zumnain nang a honkhuh ding, khantawna hihmanthat in na om ding.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನಿನ್ನ ತಮ್ಮನಾದ ಯಾಕೋಬನಿಗೆ ವಿರೋಧವಾದ ನಿನ್ನ ಬಲಾತ್ಕಾರದ ನಿಮಿತ್ತ ನಾಚಿಕೆಯು ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಮುಚ್ಚು ವದು; ನೀನು ಎಂದೆಂದಿಗೂ ಕಡಿದುಹಾಕಲ್ಪಡುವಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						For thy violence against thy brother Jacob shame shall cover thee, and thou shalt be cut off for ever.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">U hebt uw broer Israël vreselijke dingen aangedaan. Beschaamd en weerloos zult u daarom voorgoed worden uitgeroeid.</lang><lang id="Croatian">i nasilje nad bratom svojim Jakovom sram će te pokriti i nestat ćeš zasvagda.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Dla bezprawia bratu twemu Jakóbowi uczynionego haóba cię okryje, a wykorzeniony będziesz na wieki.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ความบาปของเอโดมต่ออิสราเอลเหตุเพราะความรุนแรงที่กระทำต่อยาโคบน้องชายของเจ้า ความอับอายจะปกคลุมเจ้าไว้ เจ้าจะต้องถูกตัดขาดออกไปเป็นนิตย์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Dahil sa karahasan na ginawa sa iyong kapatid na Jacob ay kahihiyan ang tatakip sa iyo, at ikaw ay mahihiwalay magpakailan man. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた は その 兄弟 ヤコブ に 暴虐 を 行 っ た の で 、 恥 は あなた を おおい 、 あなた は 永遠 に 断 た れ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിന്റെ സഹോദരനായ യാക്കോബിനോടു നീ ചെയ്ത സാഹസംനിമിത്തം ലജ്ജ നിന്നെ മൂടും; നീ സദാകാലത്തേക്കും ഛേദിക്കപ്പെടും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Din pricina silniciei făcute împotriva fratelui tău Iacov, vei fi acoperit de ruşine, şi vei fi nimicit cu desăvîrşire pentru totdeauna.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Um des Frevels willen, an deinem Bruder Jakob begangen, sollst du zu Schanden werden und ewiglich ausgerottet sein.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ja, för det våld du övade mot din broder Jakob skall du höljas med skam och bliva utrotad till evig tid.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ความ บาป ของ เอ โดม ต่อ อิส รา เอลเหตุเพราะ ความ รุนแรง ที่ กระทำ ต่อ ยา โค บ น้อง ชาย ของ เจ้า ความ อับอาย จะ ปกคลุม เจ้า ไว้ เจ้า จะ ต้อง ถูก ตัดขาด ออก ไป เป็นนิตย์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						10
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.11" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						I te ra i tu hangai mai ai koe, i te ra i whakaraua ai ona rawa e nga tautangata, i tapoko ai nga tangata iwi ke ki ona kuwaha, i kokiri nui ai mo Hiruharama, i rite rawa ano koe ki tetahi o ratou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Trong ngày người lạ cướp của cải nó, dân ngoại quốc vào các cửa thành nó, và bắt thăm trên thành Giê-ru-sa-lem, thì trong ngày ấy ngươi đứng bên kia, ngươi cũng chỉ như một người trong chúng nó.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Le jour où tu te tenais en face de lui, Le jour où des étrangers emmenaient captive son armée, Où des étrangers entraient dans ses portes, Et jetaient le sort sur Jérusalem, Toi aussi tu étais comme l`un d`eux.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Tamin'ilay andro namitsahanao teny am-pita, Tamin'ny andro namaboan'ny vahiny ny fananany, Sy nidiran'ny hafa firenena teo amin'ny vavahadiny, Ary nanaovany loka an'i Jerosalema, Dia mba toy ny anankiray tamin'ireny koa ianao.[Heb. nijanonanao]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						A mikor vele szembeálltál; a mikor serege idegenek rabjává lett, és idegenek törtek be kapuján és Jeruzsálemre sorsot vetettek: olyan voltál te is, mint bármelyik közülök.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ngemini owabumi malunga naye, mini abasemzini bathimba ubutyebi bakhe, abolunye uhlanga beza emasangweni akhe,  bayenzela amaqashiso iYerusalem: nawe wawunjengomnye wabo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">네가 멀리 섰던 날 곧 이방인이 그의 재물을 늑탈하며 외국인이 그의 성문에 들어가서 예루살렘을 얻기 위하여 제비뽑던 날에 너도 그들 중 한 사람 같았었느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tada, kai svetimieji plėšė Jokūbo turtus, veržėsi pro miesto vartus, metė burtą dėl Jeruzalės, tu stovėjai su jais ir buvai kaip vienas iš jų!
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						В тот день, когда ты стоял напротив, в тот день, когда чужие уводили войско его в плен и иноплеменники вошли в ворота его и бросали жребий о Иерусалиме, ты был как один из них.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Engkau berdiri di kejauhan, pada hari musuh mendobrak pintu Yerusalem dan mengalahkan kota itu. Engkau diam saja waktu mereka mengangkut semua kekayaan Yerusalem dan membagi-baginya di antara mereka. Engkau sama jahatnya dengan musuh itu
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Sa adlaw nga ikaw mitindog sa pikas nga daplin, sa adlaw nga ang iyang katigayonan gidala sa mga dumuloong, ug ang mga lumalangyaw mingsulod sa iyang mga ganghaan, ug nanagpapalad mahitungod sa Jerusalem, bisan pa ikaw sama sa usa usab kanila.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်သည် တဘက်၌နေသောနေ့၊ တကျွန်းတ နိုင်ငံသားတို့သည် သူ၏အမှုထမ်းများကို သိမ်းသွားသော နေ့၊ တပါးအမျိုးသားတို့သည် သူ၏မြို့တံခါးထဲသို့ ဝင်၍ ယေရုရှလင်မြို့ကို စာရေးတံချသောနေ့၌ သင်သည် လက်ခံသောသူဖြစ်၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Li queßchal saß jalan tenamit, li xicß nequeßiloc reheb, queßxtßan li oquebâl re li tenamit Jerusalén ut queßnumta saß xbêneb. Lâex cuanquex aran ut mâcßaß quebânu re xtenkßanquileb laj Judá. Chanchan ajcuiß lâex jun saß xyânkeb li xicß nequeßiloc reheb xban nak incßaß quetenkßaheb nak queßmakßeß chiruheb li cßaßru cuan reheb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Toho dňa, ktorého si stál naproti, toho dňa, ktorého cudzinci zajímali jeho vojsko, a keď cudzozemci vošli do jeho brán a o Jeruzalem hádzali los, aj ty si bol ako jeden z nich.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						त्यस समय तिमी सहायता बिना अर्को पट्टि हुनेछौ। अपरिचितले याकूबको भण्डार लिएर गयो। विदेशीहरू इस्राएल शहरको दैलोबाट पस्यो, ती विदेशीले चिट्ठा राखेर निश्चय गरे कि तिनीहरूले यरूशलेमको कुन चाँहि भाग लिने। त्यससमय तिमी चाँहि अर्को तिर उभिरहेको थियौ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Onaj dan, kad ti stajaše nasuprot; onaj dan, kad inostranci odvodjahu u ropstvo vojsku njegovu, i tudjinci ulažahu na vrata njegova i bacahu žreb za Jerusalim, beše i ti kao koji od njih.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Den dag da du holdt dig unda, den dag da fremmede bortførte hans gods, og utlendinger gikk inn i hans porter og kastet lodd om Jerusalem, da var også du som en av dem. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Çünkü yabancılar onların malını mülkünü yağmaladıkları gün Uzakta durup seyrettin. Öteki uluslar kapılarından içeri girip Yeruşalim için kura çektiklerinde Sen de onlardan biri gibi davrandın. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						يوم وقفت مقابله يوم سبت الاعاجم قدرته ودخلت الغرباء ابوابه والقوا قرعة على اورشليم كنت انت ايضا كواحد منهم.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						No dia em que estiveste do lado oposto, no dia em que estranhos lhe levaram os bens, e os estrangeiros lhe entraram pelas portas e lançaram sortes sobre Jerusalém, tu mesmo eras como um deles.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">in die cum stares adversus quando capiebant alieni exercitum eius et extranei ingrediebantur portas eius et super Hierusalem mittebant sortem tu quoque eras quasi unus ex eis</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Εν τη ημερα καθ' ην ιστασο απεναντι, τη ημερα καθ' ην οι αλλογενεις εφεραν εις αιχμαλωσιαν το στρατευμα αυτου και οι αλλοτριοι εισηλθον εις τας πυλας αυτου και εβαλον κληρους επι την Ιερουσαλημ, εσο και συ ως εις αυτων.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Die dag toe jy daarby gestaan het, die dag toe vreemdes sy rykdom weggevoer en uitlanders deur sy poorte gedring en die lot oor Jerusalem gewerp het--toe was jy ook soos een van hulle!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nou te rete kanpe la ap gade, lè moun lòt nasyon yo t'ap piye tout richès yo. Nou pa t' pi bon pase etranje yo ki te defonse pòtay yo lè sa a, ki te separe bay chak moun tout richès lavil Jerizalèm yo. Nou menm tou, nou te fè menm bagay la
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Trong ngày người lạ cướp của_cải nó , dân ngoại_quốc vào các cửa thành nó , và bắt_thăm trên thành Giê-ru-sa-lem , thì trong ngày ấy ngươi đứng bên kia , ngươi cũng chỉ như một người trong chúng_nó .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ביום עמדך מנגד ביום שבות זרים חילו ונכרים באו שערו ועל ירושלם ידו גורל גם אתה כאחד מהם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">In the day that you stood on the other side, in the day that strangers carried away his substance, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots for Jerusalem, even you were like one of them.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నీవు పగవాడవై నిలిచిన దిన మందు, పరదేశులు వారి ఆస్తిని పట్టుకొనిపోయిన దిన మందు, అన్యులు వారి గుమ్మములలోనికి చొరబడి యెరూష లేముమీద చీట్లువేసిన దినమందు నీవును వారితో కలిసి  కొంటివి గదా.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						В деня, когато ти стоеше настрана, В деня, когато иностранци заведоха в плен войската му, И чужденци като влязоха в портите му, Хвърлиха жребие за Ерусалим, Тогава и ти беше като един от тях.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Oni dan, ko si stal nasproti, v dan, ko so tujci peljali stran imetje njegovo in so inostranci vstopili skozi vrata in so za Jeruzalem metali kocko, tedaj si tudi tí bil kakor eden od njih.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						در روزی که به مقابل وی ایستاده بودی، هنگامی که غریبان اموال او را غارت نمودند وبیگانگان به دروازه هایش داخل شدند و براورشلیم قرعه انداختند، تو نیز مثل یکی از آنهابودی.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						fordi du så til, da fremmede raned hans Gods og Udlændinge kom i bans Porte; da de lodded Jerusalem bort, var og du som en af dem.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sinä päivänä, jona sinäkin olit läsnä, päivänä, jona vieraat veivät  pois hänen rikkautensa, jona muukalaiset tunkeutuivat sisään hänen  porteistaan ja heittivät Jerusalemista arpaa, olit myöskin sinä niinkuin  yksi heistä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						當 外人 擄掠 雅各 的 財物 、 外邦人 進入 他 的 城門 、 為 耶路撒冷 拈鬮 的 日子 、 你 竟 站在 一旁 、 像與 他 們同夥
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Zaaro din kaŋ ni kay fayante kuray fo waani, Zaaro din kaŋ yawey n'a arzaka ku, Yawey furo a birni meyey ra mo, I na kurne catu Urusalima boŋ, Ni mo ciya sanda i boro fo cine. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						當 外 人 擄 掠 雅 各 的 財 物 、 外 邦 人 進 入 他 的 城 門 、 為 耶 路 撒 冷 拈 鬮 的 日 子 、 你 竟 站 在 一 旁 、 像 與 他 們 同 夥 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						जिस दिन परदेशी लोग उसकी धन सम्पत्ति छीनकर ले गए, और बिराने लोगों ने उसके फाटकों से घुसकर यरूशलेम पर चिट्ठी डाली, उस दिन तू भी उन में से एक था।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Stál jsi v ten den naproti, a když zajímali cizí vojsko jeho, a když cizozemci vcházeli do bran jeho, a o Jeruzalém metali losy, ty jsi také byl jako jeden z nich.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						En la tempo, kiam vi staris apude, kiam fremduloj kondukis lian militistaron en kaptitecon kaj aligentuloj eniris en liajn pordegojn kaj lotis pri Jerusalem, vi ankaux estis kiel unu el ili.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Sepse ti ishe i pranishëm ditën që ti rrije mënjanë, ditën që të huajt e çonin në robëri ushtrinë e tij dhe të huajt hynin nga portat e tij dhe hidhnin në short fatet e Jeruzalemit, edhe ti ishe si një prej tyre.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Poiché tu eri presente quando gli stranieri ne deportavano le ricchezze, quando i forestieri entravano per le sue porte e gettavano le sorti su Gerusalemme, anzi ti sei comportato come uno di loro
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þann dag, er þú stóðst andspænis honum, þann dag, er aðkomnir menn fluttu burt fjárafla hans hertekinn og útlendingar brutust inn um borgarhlið hans og urpu hlutkesti um Jerúsalem, varst þú sem einn af þeim. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तू इस्राएलच्या शत्रूंना जाऊन मिळालास; परक्यांनी इस्राएलचे धन लुटून नेले परदेशी इस्राएलच्या गावाच्या वेशीतून आत शिरले; त्यांनी यरुशलेमचा कोणता भाग घ्यायचा ह्यासाठी चिठ्या टाकल्या; आणि तू अगदी तेथेच तुझ्या वाटणीची वाट बघत उभा होतास.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたが離れて立っていた日、すなわち異邦人がその財宝を持ち去り、外国人がその門におし入り、エルサレムをくじ引きにした日、あなたも彼らのひとりのようであった。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						En el día cuando te pusiste firme del lado contrario, en el día cuando su poderío fue llevado cautivo por los extraños, y los extranjeros llegaron hasta sus puertas y echaron suertes por Jerusalén, tú también te comportaste como uno de ellos
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Waayo, wakhtigii aad ag taagnaydeen oo iska fiirinayseen, markay shisheeyayaashu maalkooda qaadanayeen, oo dadka qalaad irdihooda soo gelayeen, oo ay Yeruusaalem saamiga u ridanayeen, xataa idinku iyagoo kalaad ahaydeen.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						lang khata na din nia, mikhualten a sum a lak mang ni ua, nam dang mite a kulh kongkhaka a honglut ua, Jerusalem tunga ai a san lai un, nang leng amau laka tel bangin na om hi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನೀನು ಆ ಕಡೆಯಲ್ಲಿ ನಿಂತ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಪರರು ಅವನ ಸೆರೆಯಾಗಿ ತಕ್ಕೊಂಡುಹೋದ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅನ್ಯರು ಅವನ ಬಾಗಲುಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಪ್ರವೇಶಿಸಿ ಯೆರೂಸಲೇಮಿನ ಮೇಲೆ ಚೀಟುಗಳನ್ನು ಹಾಕಿದಾಗ ನೀನು ಸಹ ಅವರಲ್ಲಿ ಒಬ್ಬನ ಹಾಗಿದ್ದಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						In the day that thou stoodest on the other side, in the day that the strangers carried away captive his forces, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots upon Jerusalem, even thou wast as one of them.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Want in tijden van nood liet u Israël in de steek. U ging aan de kant staan en stak geen hand uit om te helpen toen binnenvallende troepen haar soldaten als krijgsgevangenen meenamen en Jeruzalem door loting onder elkaar verdeelden. U was geen haar beter dan al die vijanden.</lang><lang id="Croatian">U dan onaj kad stajaše postrance, dok mu tuđinci blago odvodiše, dok stranci ulažahu na vrata njegova i ždrijeb bacahu za Jeruzalem, ti bijaše kao jedan od njih.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Stałeś dnia onego naprzeciwko, dnia onego, gdy cudzy imali wojsko jego, i gdy cudzoziemcy wchodzili w bramy jego, a o Jeruzalem los miotali, tyś też był jako jeden z nich.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ในวันที่เจ้ายืนเป็นปฏิปักษ์ ในวันที่คนต่างด้าวนำกำลังของเขาไปเป็นเชลย และคนต่างชาติเข้ามาทางประตูเมือง เขาจับฉลากเอากรุงเยรูซาเล็มกัน เจ้าก็เหมือนคนเหล่านั้นคนหนึ่ง</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Nang araw na ikaw ay tumayo sa kabilang dako, nang araw na dalhin ng mga taga ibang bayan ang kaniyang kayamanan, at magsipasok ang mga mangingibang bayan sa kaniyang mga pintuang-bayan at pagsapalaran ang Jerusalem, ikaw man ay naging gaya ng isa sa kanila. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた が 離れ て 立 っ て い た 日 、 すなわち 異邦 人 が その 財宝 を 持ち去 り 、 外国 人 が その 門 に おし 入 り 、 エルサレム を くじ引き に し た 日 、 あなた も 彼 ら の ひとり の よう で あ っ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നീ എതിരെ നിന്ന നാളില്‍ അന്യജാതിക്കാര്‍ അവന്റെ സമ്പത്തു അപഹരിച്ചു കൊണ്ടുപോകയും അന്യദേശക്കാര്‍ അവന്റെ ഗോപുരങ്ങളില്‍ കടന്നു യെരൂശലേമിന്നു ചീട്ടിടുകയും ചെയ്ത നാളില്‍ തന്നേ, നീയും അവരില്‍ ഒരുത്തനെപ്പോലെ ആയിരുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Căci în ziua cînd stăteai în faţa lui, în ziua cînd străinii îi luau averea, cînd străinii intrau pe porţile lui, şi aruncau sorţul asupra Ierusalimului, şi tu erai atunci ca unul din ei!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Zu der Zeit, da du wider ihn standest, da die Fremden sein Heer gefangen wegführten und Ausländer zu seinen Toren einzogen und über Jerusalem das Los warfen, da warst du gleich wie deren einer.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						På den dag då du lämnade honom i sticket, på den dag då främlingar förde bort hans gods och utlänningar drogo in genom hans port och kastade lott om Jerusalem, då var ju ock du såsom en av dem.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ใน วัน ที่ เจ้า ยืน เป็น ปฏิปักษ์ ใน วัน ที่ คน ต่างด้าว นำ กำลัง ของ เขา ไป เป็น เชลย และ คน ต่าง ชาติ เข้า มา ทาง ประตู เมือง เขา จับ ฉลาก เอา กรุง เยรูซา เล็ม กัน เจ้า ก็ เหมือน คน เหล่า นั้น คน หนึ่ง</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						11
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.12" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Otiia kaua koe e titiro ki te ra o tou teina, i te ra o tona aitua, kaua hoki koe e koa ki nga tama a Hura i te ra o to ratou whakangaromanga; kaua hoki e whakanuia tou mangai i te ra o te raru
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ôi! chớ nhìn xem ngày của anh em ngươi, là ngày tai nạn của nó; chớ vui mừng trong ngày hủy diệt của con cái Giu-đa; cũng đừng nói cách khoe khoang trong ngày nó bị khốn khổ.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ne repais pas ta vue du jour de ton frère, du jour de son malheur, Ne te réjouis pas sur les enfants de Juda au jour de leur ruine, Et n`ouvre pas une grande bouche au jour de la détresse!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Aza finaritra mijery ny andron'ny rahalahinao amin'ny andro ahitany loza izay tsy misy toa izany; Ary aza mifaly ny amin'ny taranak'i Joda amin'ny andro andringanana azy; Ary aza manao teny miavonavona amin'ny andro fahoriana
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						De ne gyönyörködjél  öcsédnek napján, az õ szerencsétlenségének napján; és ne örvendj a Júda fiain az õ veszedelmök napján, és ne kérkedjél a szorongattatás napján.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Musa ukukhangela kwimini yomninawa wakho ngemini yeshwangusha lakhe, ungabavuyeleli oonyana bakaYuda ngemini yenkxwaleko yabo; ungasineki ngemini yembandezelo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">네가 형제의 날 곧 그 재앙의 날에 방관할 것이 아니며 그 고난의 날에 네가 입을 크게 벌릴 것이 아니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tau nederėjo gėrėtis tavo brolio nelaime, džiaugtis Judo vaikų sunaikinimu ir išdidžiai kalbėti jų sielvarto dieną.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Не следовало бы тебе злорадно смотреть на день брата твоего, на день отчуждения его; не следовало бырадоваться о сынах Иуды в день гибели их и расширять рот в день бедствия.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tak sepatutnya engkau senang atas nasib sial orang Yehuda dan bergembira pada hari saudaramu itu binasa. Tak sepantasnya engkau membual pada waktu ia susah
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Apan ayaw pagtan-aw lamang sa adlaw sa imong igsoon diha sa adlaw sa iyang kadaut, ug ayaw pagmalipayon mahitungod sa mga anak sa Juda sa adlaw sa ilang pagkalaglag: ni magsulti ka nga mapahitas-on sa adlaw sa kalaut.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်၏ညီသည် တပါးအမျိုးသားဖြစ်သောနေ့၌ သူ၏အမှုကို သင်မကြည့်သင့်။ ယုဒအမျိုးသားတို့သည် ပျက်စီးသောနေ့၌ မဝါကြွားသင့်။ ဒုက္ခခံရသောနေ့၌ စော်ကားသောစကားကို မပြောသင့်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Incßaß raj xsahoß êchßôl saß li cutan nak li ralal xcßajol li rîtzßin lê xeßtônil yucuaß yôqueb chixcßulbal li raylal. Incßaß raj xsahoß saß êchßôl chirilbaleb laj Judá nak queßrahobtesîc. Ut incßaß raj xehobeb nak xeßnumta li xicß nequeßiloc reheb saß xbêneb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A preto sa nedívaj na deň svojho brata, na deň jeho nešťastia ani sa neraduj nad synmi Júdovými v deň ich zahynutia ani neroztváraj naširoko svojich úst v deň úzkosti.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमी आफ्नो भाइको विपत्तिमा, त्यो प्रति हाँस्यौ। तिमीले यसो गर्नुहुँदैन थियो। तिमी त्यससमय खुशी थियौ। जब मानिसहरूले यहूदालाई नष्ट पारे। तिमीले त्यसो गर्नु हुँदैन थियो। उनिहरूको विपत्तिको समयमा, तिमीले तिनीहरूको खिल्ली उडायौ। तिमीले त्यसो गर्नु हुँदैन थियो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ali ti ne trebaše gledati dana brata svog, dana, kad se odvodjaše u tudju zemlju, niti se radovati sinovima Judinim u dan kad propadahu, niti razvaljivati usta u dan nevolje njihove.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Se ikke med skadefryd på din brors dag, på hans ulykkes dag, og gled dig ikke over Judas barn på deres undergangs dag, og lukk ikke din munn så vidt op på trengselens dag! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Yahudalı kardeşlerinin o kötü gününden Zevk almamalıydın. Başlarına gelen yıkıma sevinmemeli, Sıkıntılı günlerinde onlarla alay etmemeliydin. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ويجب ان لا تنظر الى يوم اخيك يوم مصيبته ولا تشمت ببني يهوذا يوم هلاكهم ولا تفغر فمك يوم الضيق.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Mas tu não devias olhar com prazer para o dia de teu irmão no dia do seu desterro, nem alegrar-te sobre os filhos de Judá no dia da sua ruína, nem falar arrogantemente no dia da tribulação;
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et non despicies in die fratris tui in die peregrinationis eius et non laetaberis super filios Iuda in die perditionis eorum et non magnificabis os tuum in die angustiae</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Δεν επρεπεν ομως να επιβλεπης εις την ημεραν του αδελφου σου, εις την ημεραν της αποξενωσεως αυτου, ουδε να επιχαιρης κατα των υιων του Ιουδα εν τη ημερα του αφανισμου αυτων, ουδε να μεγαλορρημονης εν τη ημερα της θλιψεως αυτων.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En tog moes jy nie met genot die dag van jou broer aanskou het nie, die dag van sy onheil, en jou nie verheug het oor die kinders van Juda op die dag van hulle ondergang nie en nie gespog het op die dag van benoudheid nie!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nou pa t' dwe kontan wè kouzen nou yo nan malè. Nou pa t' dwe kontan wè y'ap fini ak moun fanmi Jida yo. Nou pa t' dwe pase yo nan rizib, lè yo te nan tray
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ôi ! chớ nhìn xem_ngày của anh_em ngươi , là ngày tai_nạn của nó ; chớ vui_mừng trong ngày hủy_diệt của con_cái Giu-đa ; cũng đừng nói cách khoe_khoang trong ngày nó bị khốn_khổ .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואל תרא ביום אחיך ביום נכרו ואל תשמח לבני יהודה ביום אבדם ואל תגדל פיך ביום צרה׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But don't look down on your brother in the day of his disaster, and don't rejoice over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction. Don't speak proudly in the day of distress.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నీ సహోదరుని శ్రమానుభవదినము చూచి నీవు ఆనందమొంద తగదు; యూదావారి నాశన దినమున వారి స్థితినిచూచి నీవు సంతోషింపతగదు;
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Обаче, недей гледа страстно В деня на брата си, В деня на бедствието му; Нито да се радваш на Юдейците В деня на загинването им, И да не говориш надменно в деня на угнетението им.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						A ti ne bi bil smel všečno gledati dneva brata svojega v dan njegove nesreče in se ne veseliti nad sinovi Judovimi v dan njih pogube, ne se širokoustiti v dan stiske;
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						بر روز برادر خود هنگام مصیبتش نگاه مکن و بر بنی یهودا در روز هلاکت ایشان شادی منما و در روز تنگی ایشان لاف مزن.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						At nyde din Broders Dag, hans Vanhelds Dag, og glæde dig over Judæerne på Undergangens Dag! At opspærre Munden på Trængselens Dag,
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta älä katso iloiten veljesi päivää, hänen onnettomuutensa  päivää; älä ilku juutalaisia heidän turmionsa päivänä äläkä suullasi  suurentele ahdistuksen päivänä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						你 兄弟 遭難 的 日子 、 你 不 當 瞪眼 看著 、 猶大人 被 滅 的 日子 、 你 不 當 因此 歡樂 ． 他 們遭難 的 日子 、 你 不 當說 狂傲 的 話
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ni si hima ka bina kaani te ni nya-izo boŋ a jirbey ra, Danga a masiibey zaarey ra nooya. Wala ni ma farhã Yahuda izey boŋ i halaciyaŋo zaaro ra, Wala mo ni ma fooma sanni te i kankami zaaro ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						你 兄 弟 遭 難 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 瞪 眼 看 著 、 猶 大 人 被 滅 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 因 此 歡 樂 ． 他 們 遭 難 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 說 狂 傲 的 話 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						परन्तु तुझे उचित न था कि तू अपने भाई के दिन में, अर्थात् उसकी विपत्ति के दिन में उसकी ओर देखता रहता, और यहूदियों के नाश होने के दिन उनके ऊपर आनन्द करता, और उनके संकट के दिन बड़ा बोल बोलता।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nedívejž se tedy na den bratra svého, na den zajetí jeho, aniž se vesel nad syny Judskými v den zahynutí jejich, aniž pyšně mluv ústy svými v den uzkosti.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Vi devus ne rigardi la malfelicxan tagon de via frato, la tagon de lia forpusxiteco, kaj vi devus ne gxoji pri la idoj de Jehuda en la tago de ilia pereo, nek fanfaroni en la tago de ilia mizero.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Por ti nuk duhet të shikoje me gëzim ditën e vëllait tënd, ditën e fatkeqësisë së tij, as duhet të gëzoheshe për bijtë e Judës ditën e shkatërrimit të tyre dhe as të flisje me arrogancë ditën e fatkeqësisë së tyre.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Non guardare con gioia al giorno di tuo fratello, al giorno della sua sventura. Non gioire dei figli di Giuda nel giorno della loro rovina. Non spalancare la bocca nel giorno della loro angoscia
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Horf eigi með ánægju á dag bróður þíns, á ógæfudag hans, og gleð þig eigi yfir Júda sonum á eyðingardegi þeirra og lát þér eigi stóryrði um munn fara á neyðardegi þeirra. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तुझ्या भावाच्या संकटांना तू हसलास. तू असे करायला नको होतेस. लोकांनी जेव्हा यहूदाचा नाश केला तेव्हा तू आनंद मानलास, तू तसे करायला नको होतेस. त्याच्या संकटसमयी तू प्रौढी मिरविलीस; असेही तू करायला नको होतेस.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						しかしあなたは自分の兄弟の日、すなわちその災の日をながめていてはならなかった。あなたはユダの人々の滅びの日に、これを喜んではならず、その悩みの日に誇ってはならなかった。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						No debiste haberte quedado mirando a tu hermano en su día trágico, en el día de su desgracia. No debiste alegrarte de los hijos de Judá en el día de su ruina. No debiste extralimitarte con tu boca en el día de la angustia
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiinse ha fiirina wakhtiga walaalihiin cidhiidhiga ku jiraan, oo ha ku farxina wakhtiga reer Yahuudah baabba'ooda, oo hana u faanina wakhtiga cidhiidhiga.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Ahihhangin na unaupa a siat laiin a siatna ni en ken la, Juda tate tungah a manthat ni un kipak kenla; a haksat niin kisathei takin pau sam ken.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಆದರೆ ನಿನ್ನ ಸಹೋದರನ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅವನು ಅನ್ಯನಾದ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ನೀನು ನೋಡಬಾರ ದಾಗಿತ್ತು; ಯೆಹೂದನ ಮಕ್ಕಳ ಮೇಲೆ ಅವರ ನಾಶನದ ದಿವಸದಲ್ಲಿ ಸಂತೋಷಿಸಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು; ಕಷ್ಟದ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅಹಂಕಾರವಾಗಿ ಮಾತನಾಡಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು;
					</lang><lang id="English">
						But thou shouldest not have looked on the day of thy brother in the day that he became a stranger; neither shouldest thou have rejoiced over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction; neither shouldest thou have spoken proudly in the day of distress.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Dat had u niet moeten doen. U had geen leedvermaak mogen hebben, toen zij uw broer naar vreemde landen wegvoerden. U had zich niet mogen verheugen over zijn ongeluksdag. U had niet de spot met hem mogen drijven toen hij in nood verkeerde.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Ne naslađuj se bratu u dan nesreće njegove! Ne likuj nad sinovima judejskim u dan propasti njine! Ne razvaljuj usta u dan tjeskobni!</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Nie patrzże tedy na dzieó brata swego, na dzieó pojmania jego; ani się wesel nad synami Judzkimi w dzieó zginienia ich, ani hardzie mów usty swemi w dzieó ucisku.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เจ้าไม่ควรยืนยิ้มอยู่ด้วยความพอใจในวันที่น้องชายของเจ้ารับเคราะห์ในวันนั้น เจ้าไม่ควรเปรมปรีดิ์เย้ยประชาชนยูดาห์ในวันที่เขาทั้งหลายถูกทำลาย เจ้าไม่ควรจะโอ้อวดในวันที่เขาตกทุกข์ได้ยาก</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Huwag ka ngang magmasid sa araw ng iyong kapatid sa kaarawan ng kaniyang kasakunaan, at huwag mong ikagalak ang mga anak ni Juda sa kaarawan ng kanilang pagkabuwal; ni magsalita mang may kapalaluan sa kaarawan ng pagkahapis. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 しかし あなた は 自分 の 兄弟 の 日 、 すなわち その 災 の 日 を ながめ て い て は な ら な かっ た 。 あなた は ユダ の 人々 の 滅び の 日 に 、 これ を 喜 ん で は な ら ず 、 その 悩み の 日 に 誇 っ て は な ら な かっ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിന്റെ സഹോദരന്റെ ദിവസം, അവന്റെ അനര്‍ത്ഥദിവസം തന്നെ, നീ കണ്ടു രസിക്കേണ്ടതല്ല; നീ യെഹൂദ്യരെക്കുറിച്ചു അവരുടെ അപായദിവസത്തില്‍ സന്തോഷിക്കേണ്ടതല്ല; അവരുടെ കഷ്ടദിവസത്തില്‍ നീ വമ്പു പറയേണ്ടതല്ല.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Nu trebuiai să te uiţi mulţămit la ziua fratelui tău, în ziua nenorocirii lui, nu trebuiai să te bucuri de copiii lui Iuda în ziua pieirii lor, şi nu trebuiai să vorbeşti cu semeţie în ziua strîmtorării!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Du sollst nicht mehr so deine Lust sehen an deinem Bruder zur Zeit seines Elends und sollst dich nicht freuen über die Kinder Juda zur Zeit ihres Jammers und sollst mit deinem Maul nicht so stolz reden zur Zeit Ihrer Angst;
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men se icke så med lust på din broders dag, på hans motgångs dag; gläd dig icke så över Juda barn på deras undergångs dag; spärra icke upp munnen så stort på nödens dag.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เจ้า ไม่ ควร ยืน ยิ้ม อยู่ ด้วย ความ พอใจ ใน วัน ที่ น้อง ชาย ของ เจ้า รับ เคราะห์ ใน วัน นั้น เจ้า ไม่ ควร เปรม ปรีดิ์ เย้ย ประชาชน ยู ดาห์ใน วัน ที่ เขา ทั้งหลาย ถูก ทำลาย เจ้า ไม่ ควร จะ โอ้อวด ใน วัน ที่ เขา ตก ทุกข์ ได้ ยาก</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						12
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.13" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Kaua e tomo ki roto ki te kuwaha o taku iwi i te ra o to ratou aitua; ae ra, kaua koe e matakitaki ki to ratou matenga i te ra o to ratou aitua, kaua ano hoki koutou e pa ringaringa ki o ratou rawa i te ra o to ratou raru
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Chớ vào cửa thành dân ta, đang này nó bị họa; chớ nhìn xem tai nạn nó, đang ngày nó bị khốn khó! Chớ vồ lấy của cải nó, đang ngày nó bị họa hoạn.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						N`entre pas dans les portes de mon peuple au jour de sa ruine, Ne repais pas ta vue de son malheur au jour de sa ruine, Et ne porte pas la main sur ses richesses au jour de sa ruine!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Aza miditra amin'ny vavahadin'ny oloko amin'ny andro ahitany loza; Aza finaritra mijery ny fahantrany amin'ny andro ahitany loza ianao, Ary aza maninji-tàna haka ny fananany amin'ny andro ahitany loza
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ne törj be népem kapuján nyomorúságuk napján; ne gyönyörködjél te is a baján nyomorúsága napján; és ne nyúlj az õ jószágához nyomorúsága napján;
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Musa ukungena esangweni labantu bam ngemini yeshwangusha labo, ungakhangeli nawe ebubini babo ngemini yeshwangusha labo,  ungasi sandla ebutyebini babo ngemini yeshwangusha labo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">내 백성이 환난을 당하는 날에 네가 그 성문에 들어가지 않을 것이며 환난을 당하는 날에 네가 그 고난을 방관하지 않을 것이며 환난을 당하는 날에 네가 그 재물에 손을 대지 않을 것이며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tau nederėjo įeiti pro mano tautos vartus ir gėrėtis jų kentėjimu bei tiesti rankas į jų turtą jų žuvimo dieną.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Не следовало бы тебе входить в ворота народа Моего в день несчастья его и даже смотреть на злополучие его в день погибели его, ни касаться имущества его в день бедствия его,
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tidak selayaknya engkau memasuki kota umat-Ku, dan menyoraki orang-orang yang sedang menderita, apalagi merampok hartanya pada hari kemalangannya
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ayaw pagsulod sa ganghaan sa akong katawohan sa adlaw sa ilang kagul-anan; oo, ayaw pagtan-awa ang ilang kasakitan sa adlaw sa ilang kagul-anan, ni magkawkaw ka sa ilang mga katigayanan sa adlaw sa ilang kagul-anan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ငါ၏လူတို့သည် ဘေးဥပဒ်ကို ခံရသောနေ့၌ သူတို့နေရာတံခါးအတွင်းသို့ မဝင်သင့်။ ဘေးဥပဒ်ကို ခံရ သောနေ့၌ သူတို့၏ဆင်းရဲဒုက္ခကို မကြည့်မရှုသင့်။ ဘေး ဥပဒ်ကို ခံရသောနေ့၌ သူတို့ဥစ္စာကို မလုမယူသင့်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Incßaß raj xex-oc Jerusalén saß xtenamiteb li cualal incßajol saß eb li cutan nak yôqueb chixcßulbal li raylal. Incßaß raj xsahoß saß êchßôl nak queßsacheß. Ut incßaß raj xerelkßa li cßaßruheb re nak xeßxcßul li raylal.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Nevojdi do brány môjho ľudu v deň ich zkazy; nedívaj sa i ty na jeho zlé v deň jeho zkazy; ani nevystri svojej ruky na jeho imanie v deň jeho zkazy.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमी मेरो शहरको दैलोबाट भित्र पसेर अनि उनीहरूको समस्यामा हाँस्यौ। तिमीले त्यसो गर्नु हुँदैन थियो। उसको त्यस्तो विपत्ति उनीहरूको धनको भण्डार लियौ तिमीले त्यस्तो गर्नु हुँदैन थियो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ne trebaše ti ući na vrata naroda mog u dan pogibli njihove, ne trebaše da i ti gledaš zlo njihovo u dan pogibli njihove, ni da se dohvataš dobra njihova u dan pogibli njihove.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Dra ikke inn gjennem mitt folks port den dag de er i nød, se ikke også du med skadefryd på deres ulykke den dag de er i nød, og legg ikke hånd på deres gods den dag de er i nød, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Halkım felakete uğradığı gün Kente girmemeliydin, O gün halkımın uğradığı kötülükten zevk almamalı, Malını mülkünü ele geçirmeye kalkmamalıydın. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ولا تدخل باب شعبي يوم بليتهم. ولا تنظر انت ايضا الى مصيبته يوم بليّته ولا تمد يدا الى قدرته يوم بليّته.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						nem entrar pela porta do meu povo no dia da sua calamidade; sim, tu não devias olhar, satisfeito, para o seu mal, no dia da sua calamidade; nem lançar mão dos seus bens no dia da sua calamidade;
					</lang><lang id="Latin">neque ingredieris portam populi mei in die ruinae eorum neque despicies et tu in malis eius in die vastitatis illius et non emitteris adversum exercitum eius in die vastitatis illius</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Δεν επρεπε να εισελθης εις την πυλην του λαου μου εν τη ημερα της συμφορας αυτων, ουδε να θεωρης και συ την θλιψιν αυτων εν τη ημερα της συμφορας αυτων, ουδε να επιβαλης χειρα επι την περιουσιαν αυτων εν τη ημερα της συμφορας αυτων,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Tog moes jy nie in die poort van my volk gekom het op die dag van hulle nood nie, moes jy ook nie met genot aanskou het sy onheil op die dag van sy nood nie en nie die hand uitgesteek het na sy rykdom op die dag van sy nood nie!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nou pa t' dwe janbe pòtay lavil pèp mwen an pou nou te antre ladan l', jou malè te tonbe sou yo a. Nou pa t' dwe kontan wè jan y'ap soufri, jou malè te tonbe sou yo a. Nou pa t' dwe mete men nou sou byen yo, jou malè te tonbe sou yo a
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Chớ vào cửa thành dân ta , đang này nó bị họa ; chớ nhìn xem tai_nạn nó , đang ngày nó bị khốn_khó ! Chớ vồ lấy của_cải nó , đang ngày nó bị họa hoạn .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אל תבוא בשער עמי ביום אידם אל תרא גם אתה ברעתו ביום אידו ואל תשלחנה בחילו ביום אידו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Don't enter into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity. Don't look down on their affliction in the day of their calamity, neither seize their wealth on the day of their calamity.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నా జనుల ఆపద్దినమున నీవు వారి గుమ్మములలోనికి చొరబడ దగదు; వారి ఆపద్దినమున నీవు సంతోషపడుచు వారి బాధను చూడతగదు; వారి ఆపద్దినమున నీవు వారి ఆస్తిని పట్టుకొనతగదు;
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Недей влиза в портата на людете ми В деня на бедствието им; Да! не гледай страстно злощастието им В деня на бедствието им, Нито да туриш ръка на имота им В деня на бедствието им;
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						ti ne bi bil smel stopiti v vrata ljudstva mojega v dan nadloge njegove, prav ti ne bi bil smel všečno gledati nesreče njegove v dan nadloge njegove, ne roke iztegniti po blagu njegovem v dan nadloge njegove;
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و به دروازه های قوم من در روز بلای ایشان داخل مشو و تو نیز بر بدی ایشان در روز بلای ایشان منگر و دست خود را بر اموال ایشان در روز بلای ایشان دراز مکن.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						komme i mit Folks Port på Ulykkens Dag, være med til at nyde dets Kval på Ulykkens Dag, gribe efter dets Gods på Ulykkens Dag!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Älä tunkeudu sisään minun kansani portista heidän hätäpäivänänsä.  Älä katso iloiten, myös sinä, hänen onnettomuuttansa hänen  hätäpäivänänsä. Älä ojenna kättäsi hänen rikkauteensa hänen  hätäpäivänänsä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						我 民 遭災 的 日子 、 你 不 當進 他 們的 城門 ． 他 們遭災 的 日子 、 你 不 當 瞪眼 看著 他 們受苦 ． 他 們遭災 的 日子 、 你 不 當 伸手 搶 他 們的財物
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ma si furo ay borey birni meyey ra i balaaw zaaro hane. Oho, ma si i masiiba gomdo i balaaw zaaro ra, Ma si ni kambe dake mo i arzakey gaa i balaaw zaaro ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						我 民 遭 災 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 進 他 們 的 城 門 ． 他 們 遭 災 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 瞪 眼 看 著 他 們 受 苦 ． 他 們 遭 災 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 伸 手 搶 他 們 的 財 物 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						तुझे उचित न था कि मेरी प्रजा की विपत्ति के दिन तू उसके फाटक से घुसता, और उसकी विपत्ति के दिन उसकी धन सम्पत्ति पर हाथ लगाता।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nevcházej do brány lidu mého v den bídy jejich, aniž se dívej trápení jeho v den bídy jeho, a nechtěj sahati na statek jeho v den bídy jeho.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Vi devus ne eniri en la pordegon de Mia popolo en la tago de ilia malfelicxo, vi devus ne rigardi ilian suferadon en la tago de ilia malfelicxo, nek tusxi ilian havajxon en la tago de ilia malfelicxo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Nuk duhet të hyje nga porta e popullit tim, ditën e fatkeqësisë së tij, as të sodisje edhe ti me kënaqësi mjerimin e tij, ditën e fatkeqësisë së tij dhe as të shtrije duart mbi pasuritë e tij ditën e fatkeqësisë së tij.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Non varcare la soglia del mio popolo nel giorno della sua sventura, non guardare con compiacenza la sua calamità; non stendere la mano sui suoi beni nel giorno della sua sventura
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Ryðst ekki inn um hlið þjóðar minnar á glötunardegi þeirra, horf þú ekki líka með ánægju á óhamingju hennar á glötunardegi hennar og rétt þú ekki út höndina eftir fjárafla hennar á glötunardegi hennar. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						माझ्या लोकांच्या वेशीतून तू आत आलास; आणि त्यांच्या समस्यांकडे पाहून हसलास; तू असे करायला नको होतेस त्यांच्या संकटसमयी तू त्यांची संपत्ती घेतलीस, तू असे करायला नको होतेस.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたはわが民の災の日に、その門にはいってはならず、その災の日にその苦しみをながめてはならなかった。またその災の日に、その財宝に手をかけてはならなかった。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						No debiste entrar por la puerta de mi pueblo en el día de su ruina. Tampoco debiste mirar su miseria en el día de su ruina. No debiste echar mano de sus bienes en el día de su ruina
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Iridda dadkayga ha soo gelina wakhtiga ay belaayaysan yihiin, oo weliba dhibkooda ha fiirsanina wakhtiga ay belaayaysan yihiin, oo maalkoodana far ha saarina wakhtiga ay belaayaysan yihiin.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Ka mite a vangtah ni un a kulh kongpi uah lut ken; ahi, a vangtah ni un a thuakna te uh en ken la, a vangtah ni un a sum uleh a paite uh tungah na khutte uh nga sam kei un.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನನ್ನ ಜನರ ಬಾಗಲೊಳಗೆ ಅವರ ಆಪತ್ತಿನ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಪ್ರವೇಶಿಸಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು; ಹೌದು, ನೀನು ಅವರ ಆಪತ್ತಿನ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅವರ ಕೇಡನ್ನು ನೋಡಬಾರ ದಾಗಿತ್ತು; ಅವರ ಆಪತ್ತಿನ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅವರ ಆಸ್ತಿಯ ಮೇಲೆ ಕೈಹಾಕಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು;
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Thou shouldest not have entered into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity; yea, thou shouldest not have looked on their affliction in the day of their calamity, nor have laid hands on their substance in the day of their calamity;
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Kom niet naar Israël op die rampzalige dag. Maak u niet meester van de buit en heb geen leedvermaak over haar ondergang.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Ne provaljuj na vrata naroda moga u dan nesreće njegove! Ne naslađuj se njegovom propašću u dan nesreće njegove! Ne pružaj ruke na imanje njegovo u dan nesreće njegove!</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Nie wchodź w bramę ludu mego w dzieó utrapienia ich, ani patrz na złe jego w dzieó doległości jego, ani ściągaj ręki swej na majętność jego, w dzieó skruszenia jego;
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เจ้าไม่ควรเข้าประตูเมืองแห่งประชาชนของเราในวันแห่งหายนะของเขา เออ เจ้าไม่ควรยืนยิ้มอยู่ในเรื่องภัยพิบัติของเขาในวันแห่งหายนะของเขา เจ้าไม่ควรจะเข้าริบทรัพย์สินของเขาไปในวันแห่งหายนะของเขา</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Huwag kang pumasok sa pintuan ng aking bayan sa kaarawan ng kanilang kasakunaan; oo, huwag mong masdan ang kanilang pagdadalamhati sa kaarawan ng kanilang kasakunaan, o pakialaman man ninyo ang kanilang kayamanan sa kaarawan ng kanilang kasakunaan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた は わが 民 の 災 の 日 に 、 その 門 に はい っ て は な ら ず 、 その 災 の 日 に その 苦しみ を ながめ て は な ら な かっ た 。 また その 災 の 日 に 、 その 財宝 に 手 を かけ て は な ら な かっ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						എന്റെ ജനത്തിന്റെ അപായദിവസത്തില്‍ നീ അവരുടെ വാതിലിന്നകത്തു കടക്കേണ്ടതല്ല; അവരുടെ അപായദിവസത്തില്‍ നീ അവരുടെ അനര്‍ത്ഥം കണ്ടു രസിക്കേണ്ടതല്ല; അവരുടെ അപായദിവസത്തില്‍ അവരുടെ സമ്പത്തിന്മേല്‍ നീ കൈ വെക്കേണ്ടതല്ല.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Nici nu trebuiai să intri pe porţile poporului Meu în ziua nenorocirii lui, nici nu trebuiai să te bucuri de nenorocirea lui în ziua prăpădului lui, şi nu trebuiai să pui mîna pe bogăţiile lui în ziua prăpădului lui!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						du sollst nicht zum Tor meines Volkes einziehen zur Zeit ihres Jammers; du sollst nicht deine Lust sehen an ihrem Unglück zur Zeit ihres Jammers; du sollst nicht nach seinem Gut greifen zur Zeit seines Jammers; 
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Drag icke in genom mitt folks port på deras ofärds dag; se ej så hans olycka med lust, också du, på hans ofärds dag; och räck icke ut din hand efter hans gods på hans ofärds dag.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เจ้า ไม่ ควร เข้า ประตู เมือง แห่ง ประชาชน ของ เรา ใน วัน แห่ง หายนะ ของ เขา เออ เจ้า ไม่ ควร ยืน ยิ้ม อยู่ ใน เรื่อง ภัย พิบัติ ของ เขา ใน วัน แห่ง หายนะ ของ เขา เจ้า ไม่ ควร จะ เข้า ริบทรัพย์สิน ของ เขา ไป ใน วัน แห่ง หายนะ ของ เขา</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						13
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.14" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						A kaua koe e tu ki te pekanga o te ara ki te hatepe i ona morehu e mawhiti; kaua hoki e tukua ona morehu i te ra o te raru
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Chớ đứng nơi ngã ba đường đặng diệt những kẻ trốn tránh của nó, và chớ nộp những kẻ sống sót sau cùng của nó trong ngày nguy nan.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ne te tiens pas au carrefour pour exterminer ses fuyards, Et ne livre pas ses réchappés au jour de la détresse!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Aza mamitsaka eo amin'ny sampanan-dalana hamono izay afa-nandositra ianao; Ary aza manolotra izay sisa aminy amin'ny andro fahoriana.[Heb. mijanona]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						A résre se állj fel menekülõit elveszíteni; és ne áruld el az õ megmaradottait a szorongattatás napján!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Musa ukuma ekwahlukaneni kweendlela, ukuze unqumle abasabayo bakubo; ungabanikeli abaseleyo bakubo ngemini yembandezelo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">사거리에 서서 그 도망하는 자를 막지 않을 것이며 고난의 날에 그 남은 자를 대적에게 붙이지 않을 것이니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tau nederėjo stovėti kryžkelėse ir naikinti pabėgėlius bei išduoti tuos, kurie ištrūko priespaudos metu!
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						ни стоять на перекрестках для убивания бежавших его, ни выдаватьуцелевших из него в день бедствия.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tidak seharusnya engkau berdiri di persimpangan, untuk menghadang orang-orang yang sedang melarikan diri dari musuh, atau menyerahkan mereka kepada lawan pada hari mereka ditimpa kesusahan.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug ayaw pagtindog sa kinasang-an sa dalan, aron sa pagputol niadtong mga iya nga nanagpangalagiw; ug ayaw pag-itugyan kadtong mga iya nga managpabilin sa adlaw sa kasub-anan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						လွတ်သောသူတို့ကို ဆီးတားခြင်းငှါ ဖြတ်လမ်း၌ မရပ်မနေသင့်။ အမှုရောက်သောနေ့၌ ကျန်ကြွင်းသော သူတို့ကို မအပ်သင့်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Incßaß raj xexakab êrib saß xâla be chixrambaleb li yôqueb chi êlelic. Ut incßaß raj xecamsiheb. Incßaß raj xechapeb li queßcana ut incßaß raj xekßaxtesiheb cuißchic saß rukßeb li xicß nequeßiloc reheb saß li cutan nak yôqueb chixcßulbal li raylal.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Ani nestoj na rozcestí, aby si vyťal tých, ktorí by z neho unikli, ani nevydaj nepriateľovi jeho pozostatkov v deň úzkosti.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमी दोबाटोहरूमा उसको जीवन बचाउँने चेष्टा गर्दै भगुवालाई रोक्न उभिनु हुँदैन थियो, तिमीले उसको बाँचेकाहरूलाई दुःखको दिनमा उसको हातमा सुम्पिनु हुँदैन थियो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Niti trebaše da staneš na rasputicu da ubijaš bežan njihovu, niti da izdaješ onih koji ostaše u dan nevolje.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						og stå ikke på veiskjellet for å utrydde dem av mitt folk som har sloppet unda, og overgi ikke dets flyktninger til fienden på trengselens dag! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Kaçmaya çalışanları öldürmek için Yol ağzında durmamalı, O sıkıntılı günde kurtulanları Düşmana teslim etmemeliydin." 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ولا تقف على المفرق لتقطع منفلتيه ولا تسلّم بقاياه يوم الضيق.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						nem te postar nas encruzilhadas, para exterminares os que escapassem; nem entregar os que lhe restassem, no dia da tribulação.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">neque stabis in exitibus ut interficias eos qui fugerint et non concludes reliquos eius in die tribulationis</lang><lang id="Greek">
						ουδε επρεπε να σταθης επι τας διεξοδους, δια να αποκλειης τους διασωζομενους αυτου ουδε να παραδωσης τους υπολοιπους αυτου εν τη ημερα της θλιψεως αυτων
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En jy moes nie gestaan het op die kruispad om sy vlugtelinge uit te roei nie en nie sy vrygeraaktes uitgelewer het op die dag van benoudheid nie.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nou pa t' dwe kanpe nan kalfou yo pou nou touye sa ki t'ap chache chape kò yo. Nou pa t' dwe lage sa ki pa t' mouri yo nan men lènmi yo, jou malè te tonbe sou yo a
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Chớ đứng nơi ngã ba đường đặng diệt những kẻ trốn_tránh của nó , và chớ nộp những kẻ sống_sót sau_cùng của nó trong ngày nguy_nan .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואל תעמד על הפרק להכרית את פליטיו ואל תסגר שרידיו ביום צרה׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Don't stand in the crossroads to cut off those of his who escape. Don't deliver up those of his who remain in the day of distress.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						వారిలో తప్పించుకొనినవారిని సంహ రించుటకు అడ్డత్రోవలలో నీవు నిలువతగదు, శ్రమదిన మందు అతనికి శేషించినవారిని శత్రువులచేతికి అప్పగింప తగదు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Недей застава на кръстопътя, За да изтребваш бежанците му, Нито да предадеш останалите от него В деня на угнетението им.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						ti ne bi bil smel stati ob razpotju, da bi posekal njegove ubežnike, in ne bi bil smel izročiti sovražniku tistih, ki so mu preostali v dan stiske.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و بر سر دو راه مایست تافراریان ایشان را منقطع سازی و باقی ماندگان ایشان را در روز تنگی تسلیم منما.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						At stå ved Dalenes Munding og dræbe de undslupne, prisgive dem, som slap bort, på Trængselens Dag!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Älä seiso tienhaarassa hävittämässä hänen pelastuneitansa.  Älä  luovuta hänen pakoonpäässeitänsä ahdistuksen päivänä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						你 不 當站 在 岔路口 、 剪除 他 們中間逃脫 的 ． 他 們遭難 的 日子 、 你 不 當將 他 們 剩下 的 人 交付 仇敵
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ma si kay mo fondo fayyaŋ boŋ hala ni m'a wane fooyaŋ kaŋ goono ga yana kosaray. Borey kaŋ yaŋ cindi mo, Ni ma si i nooyandi gurzugay zaari ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						你 不 當 站 在 岔 路 口 、 剪 除 他 們 中 間 逃 脫 的 ． 他 們 遭 難 的 日 子 、 你 不 當 將 他 們 剩 下 的 人 交 付 仇 敵 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						तुझे उचित न था कि तिरमुहाने पर उसके भागनेवालों को मार डालने के लिये खड़ा होता, और संकट के दिन उसके बचे हुओं को पकड़ाता।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Aniž stůj při mezeře, abys hubil ty, kteříž z nich ucházejí, aniž vydávej nepříteli v moc těch, kteříž z nich pozůstali v den úzkosti.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Vi devus ne stari cxe la vojdisigxo, por ekstermi iliajn forsavigxintojn,  nek transdoni iliajn restintojn en la tago de malfelicxo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Nuk duhet të viheshe në udhëkryqet për të masakruar ikanakët e tij dhe as t'i jepje në dorë të armikut ata që kishin mbijetuar ditën e fatkeqësisë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Non appostarti ai crocicchi delle strade, per massacrare i suoi fuggiaschi; non far mercato dei suoi superstiti, nel giorno dell'angoscia
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Nem eigi staðar á vegamótum til þess að drepa niður flóttamenn hennar, og framsel eigi menn hennar, þá er undan komast, á degi neyðarinnar. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						जिथे रस्ते एकमेकांना छेदतात तिथे तू उभा राहिलास आणि पळून जाण्याचा प्रयत्न करणाऱ्यांचा नाश केलास. तू असे करायला नको होते. जिवंत सुटलेल्यांना तू पकडलेस तू असे करायला नको होते.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたは分れ道に立って、そののがれる者を切ってはならなかった。あなたは悩みの日にその残った者を敵にわたしてはならなかった。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Tampoco debiste ponerte en las encrucijadas de los caminos para aniquilar a sus fugitivos. No debiste haber entregado a sus sobrevivientes en el día de la desgracia
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo meesha jidadka isku gooyaana ha u istaagina si aad u laysaan kuwooda soo fakaday, oo kuwooda wakhtigii cidhiidhiga ka hadhayna cadowgooda ha u gacangelina.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						A mi khenkhat tai khete that dingin lam thuamah dingin haksat niin a mi omsunte mansak ken.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಅವನಲ್ಲಿ ಓಡಿ ಹೋದವರನ್ನು ಕಡಿದುಬಿಡುವದಕ್ಕೆ ನೀನು ಕೂಡುವ ದಾರಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ನಿಲ್ಲಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು; ಕಷ್ಟದ ದಿನದಲ್ಲಿ ಅವನಲ್ಲಿ ಉಳಿದುಕೊಂಡವರನ್ನು ಒಪ್ಪಿಸಬಾರದಾಗಿತ್ತು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Neither shouldest thou have stood in the crossway, to cut off those of his that did escape; neither shouldest thou have delivered up those of his that did remain in the day of distress.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Ga niet op kruispunten staan om degene die proberen te vluchten, te vermoorden. Neem de overlevenden niet gevangen om hen uit te leveren aan hun vijanden in die tijd van barre ellende.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Ne stoj na raskršćima da pobiješ njegove bjegunce! Ne izdaji preživjelih njegovih u dan tjeskobni!"</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Ani stój na rozstaniu dróg, abyś zatracał tych, którzy z nich uchodzą; ani podawaj nieprzyjacielowi w moc tych, którzy z nich zostali w dzieó ucisku.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เจ้าไม่ควรจะยืนสกัดทางแยก เพื่อจะกำจัดพวกที่หลบหนีของเขา เจ้าไม่ควรจะมอบพวกที่เหลืออยู่ให้แก่ศัตรูของเขาในวันที่เขาตกทุกข์ได้ยาก</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At huwag kang tumayo sa mga salubungang daan na ihiwalay ang kaniya na tumatanan; at huwag mong ibigay ang kaniya na nalabi sa kaarawan ng kapanglawan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた は 分れ道 に 立 っ て 、 その のがれ る 者 を 切 っ て は な ら な かっ た 。 あなた は 悩み の 日 に その 残 っ た 者 を 敵 に わた し て は な ら な かっ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അവന്റെ പലായിതന്മാരെ ഛേദിച്ചുകളവാന്‍ നീ വഴിത്തലെക്കല്‍ നില്‍ക്കേണ്ടതല്ല; കഷ്ടദിവസത്തില്‍ അവന്നു ശേഷിച്ചവരെ നീ ഏല്പിച്ചുകൊടുക്കേണ്ടതുമല്ല.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Nu trebuiai să stai la răspîntii, ca să nimiceşti pe fugarii lui, şi nici nu trebuiai să dai în mîna vrăjmaşului pe cei ce scăpaseră din el în ziua necazului lui!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						du sollst nicht stehen an den Wegscheiden, seine Entronnenen zu morden; du sollst seine übrigen nicht verraten zur Zeit der Angst.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ställ dig icke vid vägskälet för att nedgöra hans flyktingar, och giv icke hans undsluppna till pris på nödens dag.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เจ้า ไม่ ควร จะ ยืน สกัด ทาง แยก เพื่อ จะ กำจัด พวก ที่ หลบ หนี ของ เขา เจ้า ไม่ ควร จะ มอบ พวก ที่ เหลือ อยู่ ให้ แก่ ศัตรู ของ เขา ใน วัน ที่ เขา ตก ทุกข์ ได้ ยาก</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						14
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.15" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Kua tata hoki te ra o Ihowa ki nga tauiwi katoa; ka rite ki tau i mea ai ka meatia ki a koe; ka hoki tau utu ki runga ki tou mahunga
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Vì ngày của Ðức Giê-hô-va đã gần trên hết thảy các nước: bấy giờ người ta sẽ làm cho ngươi như chính mình ngươi đã làm; những việc làm của ngươi sẽ đổ lại trên đầu ngươi.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Car le jour de l`Éternel est proche, pour toutes les nations; Il te sera fait comme tu as fait, Tes oeuvres retomberont sur ta tête.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa efa antomotra amin'ny jentilisa rehetra ny andron'i Jehovah; Toy ny nataonao no mba hatao aminao kosa; Eny, hitsingerina ho eo an-dohanao ny nataonao.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Mert közel van az Úrnak napja minden népek ellen. A mint cselekedtél,  úgy cselekesznek veled; a mit te fizettél, visszaszáll fejedre.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ngokuba isondele imini kaYehova kuzo zonke iintlanga.  Njengoko wenze ngako, kuya kwenjiwa njalo kuwe; okwenzileyo kuya kubuyela entlokweni yakho.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">여호와의 만국을 벌할 날이 가까왔나니 너의 행한대로 너도 받을것인즉 너의 행한 것이 네 머리로 돌아갈 것이라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Juk Viešpaties diena arti visoms tautoms. Kaip tu darei, taip tau darys­tavo atlygis grįš tau pačiam.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Ибо близок день Господень на все народы: как ты поступал, так поступлено будет и с тобою; воздаяние твое обратится на голову твою.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						"Sungguh, sudah dekat harinya, Aku, TUHAN, mengadili bangsa-bangsa. Apa yang dilakukan Edom akan dibalaskan kepadanya. Ia akan merasakan juga apa yang telah ia perbuat
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kay ang adlaw ni Jehova haduol man sa sa ibabaw sa tanang mga nasud: ingon sa imong gibuhat, kanimo pagabuhaton kini; ang imong gibuhat magabalik sa imong kaugalingong ulo.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အကြောင်းမူကား၊ ထာဝရဘုရား၏နေ့ရက် သည် ခပ်သိမ်းသောလူမျိုးတို့နှင့် နီးပြီ။ သင်ပြုသည်အ တိုင်း သင်၌ သူတပါးပြုလိမ့်မည်။ သင်ပြုသောအမှုသည် သင့်ခေါင်းပေါ်သို့ ရောက်ရလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Joß xebânu reheb laj Judá, joßcan ajcuiß têcßul lâex. Lâex têcßul lê kßajcâmunquil. Cuulac re xkßehil nak lâin li Kâcuaß tinrakok âtin saß xbêneb chixjunileb li jalanil tenamit. Ut tinrakok ajcuiß âtin saß êbên lâex.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Lebo je blízko deň Hospodinov, ktorý prijde na všetky tie národy. Jako si robil, tak sa urobí aj tebe; tvoja odplata sa navráti na tvoju hlavu.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						सबै देशहरूमा चाँडै नै परमप्रभु आउँनु हुने दिन आउँदैछ। तिमीले अन्य मानिसहरूसंग नराम्रो काम गरेकाछौ। त्यही नराम्रो काम तिमीले भोग्नु पर्ने छ। सबै नराम्रो कर्महरूको फल थाप्लोमा पर्नेछ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Jer je dan Gospodnji blizu svim narodima: kako si činio, tako će ti biti, plata će ti se vratiti na glavu tvoju.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						For nær er Herrens dag over alle folkene; som du har gjort, skal det gjøres med dig, dine gjerninger skal falle tilbake på ditt eget hode. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    "RAB'bin bütün ulusları yargılayacağı gün yaklaştı. Ey Edom, ne yaptıysan sana da aynısı yapılacak. Yaptıkların kendi başına gelecek. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						فانه قريب يوم الرب على كل الامم. كما فعلت يفعل بك. عملك يرتد على راسك.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Porquanto o dia do Senhor está perto, sobre todas as nações, como tu fizeste, assim se fará contigo; o teu feito tornará sobre a tua cabeça.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">quoniam iuxta est dies Domini super omnes gentes sicut fecisti fiet tibi retributionem tuam convertet in caput tuum</lang><lang id="Greek">
						διοτι εγγυς ειναι η ημερα του Κυριου επι παντα τα εθνη καθως εκαμες θελει γεινει εις σε η ανταποδοσις σου θελει στρεψει επι την κεφαλην σου.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Want die dag van die HERE is naby oor al die nasies; soos jy gedoen het, sal aan jou gedoen word, jou daad sal op jou hoof neerkom.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Jou a pa lwen rive, kote mwen menm, Seyè a, mwen pral jije tout nasyon yo. Nou menm moun peyi Edon, sa nou te fè a, se sa yo pral fè nou tou. Yo pral fè nou sibi tou sa nou te fè lòt yo sibi
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Vì ngày của Ðức_Giê - hô-va đã gần trên hết_thảy các nước : bấy_giờ người_ta sẽ làm cho ngươi như chính mình ngươi đã làm ; những việc_làm của ngươi sẽ đổ lại trên đầu ngươi .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						כי קרוב יום יהוה על כל הגוים כאשר עשית יעשה לך גמלך ישוב בראשך׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">For the day of Yahweh is near all the nations! As you have done, it will be done to you. Your deeds will return upon your own head.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						యెహోవాదినము  అన్యజనులందరిమీదికి  వచ్చు చున్నది. అప్పుడు నీవు చేసినట్టే నీకును చేయబడును, నీవు చేసినదే నీ నెత్తిమీదికి వచ్చును.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Защото денят Господен е близо против всичките народи; Както си направил, така ще се направи и на тебе; Постъпките ти ще се върнат на главата ти.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kajti dan GOSPODOV je blizu nad vsemi poganskimi narodi: kakor si storil ti, se bo storilo tebi; dejanje tvoje se ti povrne na glavo.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						زیرا که روزخداوند بر جمیع امت‌ها نزدیک است و چنانکه عمل نمودی همچنان به تو عمل کرده خواهدشد و اعمالت بر سرت خواهد برگشت.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Thi nær er HERRENs Dag over alle Folkene; som du har gjort, skal der gøres med dig, Gengæld kommer over dit Hoved.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sillä lähellä on Herran päivä kaikkia pakanakansoja: Niinkuin sinä  olet tehnyt, niin sinulle tehdään; kosto sinun teostasi kohtaa sinun  omaa päätäsi.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						耶和華 降 罰 的 日子 臨近 萬國 ． 你 怎樣行 、 他 也 必 照樣 向 你 行 ． 你 的 報應 必歸 到 你 頭上
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Zama Rabbi zaaro maan, kaŋ ga kaa dumey cindey gaa. Sanda mate kaŋ cine ni te, Yaadin cine no i ga te ni mo se. Ni te-goyey ga ye ka kaŋ ni boŋ. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						耶 和 華 降 罰 的 日 子 臨 近 萬 國 ． 你 怎 樣 行 、 他 也 必 照 樣 向 你 行 ． 你 的 報 應 必 歸 到 你 頭 上 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						क्योंकि सारी अन्यजातियों पर यहोवा के दिन का आना निकट है। जैसा तु ने किया है, वैसा ही तुझ से भी किया जाएगा, तेरा व्यवहार लौटकर तेरे ही सिर पर पड़ेगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nebo blízko jest den Hospodinův proti všechněm těm národům. Jakž jsi činil, tak se stane tobě, odplata tvá navrátí se na hlavu tvou.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						CXar proksima estas la tago de la Eternulo kontraux cxiuj nacioj. Kiel vi agis, tiel oni agos kun vi; kion vi meritas, tio venos sur vian kapon.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Sepse dita e Zotit është e afërt për tërë kombet; atë që u bëre të tjerëve do të ta bëjnë ty, shpërblimi i veprimeve të tua do të bjerë mbi kokën tënde.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Perché è vicino il giorno del Signore contro tutte le genti. Come hai fatto tu, così a te sarà fatto, ciò che hai fatto agli altri ricadrà sul tuo capo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Því að dagur Drottins er nálægur fyrir allar þjóðir. Eins og þú hefir öðrum gjört, eins skal þér gjört verða; gjörðir þínar skulu þér í koll koma. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						परमेश्वराचा दिवस लवकरच सर्व राष्ट्रांकडे येत आहे; तू दुसऱ्या लोकांशी वाईट कृत्ये केलीस त्या वाईट गोष्टी तुझ्या बाबतीत घडतील. तू केलेली दुष्कर्मे तुझ्या डोक्यावर येऊन आदळतील.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						主の日が万国の民に臨むのは近い。あなたがしたようにあなたもされる。あなたの報いはあなたのこうべに帰する。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						"Cercano está el día de Jehovah sobre todas las naciones. Como tú hiciste, se hará contigo; tu retribución volverá sobre tu cabeza
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Waayo, maalintii Rabbigu way soo dhow dahay oo way ku dhici doontaa quruumaha oo dhan, oo sidaad samayseen ayaa idinkana laydiinku samayn doonaa, oo abaalgudkiinnii ayaa madaxiinna ku soo noqon doonaa.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Nam tengteng tungah TOUPA ni lah a nai ngala: na nahihsia mahbangin na tungah hih ahi ding; na hihdan tak nangmah lu jangah honkik nawn ding.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಕರ್ತನ ದಿನವು ಎಲ್ಲಾ ಜನಾಂಗಗಳ ಮೇಲೆ ಸವಿಾಪವಾಗಿದೆ; ನೀನು ಮಾಡಿದ ಹಾಗೆಯೇ ನಿನಗೆ ಮಾಡಲ್ಪಡುವದು; ನಿನ್ನ ಪ್ರತಿಫಲವು ನಿನ್ನ ತಲೆಯ ಮೇಲೆ ತಿರುಗುವದು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						For the day of the LORD is near upon all the heathen: as thou hast done, it shall be done unto thee: thy reward shall return upon thine own head.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Binnenkort zal de HERE wraaknemen op alle heidense volken. Wat u Israël hebt aangedaan, zal u nu zelf overkomen. U krijgt uw verdiende loon.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Jer blizu je Jahvin dan svima narodima! Dat će ti se milo za drago, tvoja će djela na tvoju glavu pasti.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Bo bliski jest dzieó Paóski przeciwko tym wszystkim narodom; jakoś uczynił, tak ci się stanie, nagroda twoja obróci się na głowę twoję.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">การรื้อทำลายเอโดม เปรียบได้กับวันแห่งพระเยโฮวาห์ในอนาคตเพราะวันแห่งพระเยโฮวาห์ใกล้ประชาชาติทั้งสิ้นเข้ามาแล้ว เจ้ากระทำแก่เขาอย่างไร ก็จะมีผู้มากระทำแก่เจ้าอย่างนั้น การตอบแทนของเจ้าจะกลับมาตกบนศีรษะของเจ้าเอง</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Sapagka't ang kaarawan ng Panginoon ay malapit na, laban sa lahat ng bansa: kung ano ang iyong gawin, ay siyang gagawin sa iyo; ang iyong gawa ay babalik sa iyong sariling ulo. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
					 	 主 の 日 が 万国 の 民 に 臨 む の は 近 い 。 あなた が し た よう に あなた も さ れ る 。 あなた の 報い は あなた の こうべ に 帰 する 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						സകലജാതികള്‍ക്കും യഹോവയുടെ നാള്‍ അടുത്തിരിക്കുന്നു; നീ ചെയ്തിരിക്കുന്നതുപോലെ നിന്നോടും ചെയ്യും; നിന്റെ പ്രവൃത്തി നിന്റെ തലമേല്‍ തന്നേ മടങ്ങിവരും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Căci ziua Domnului este aproape pentru toate neamurile. Cum ai făcut, aşa ţi se va face; faptele tale se vor întoarce asupra capului tău.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Denn der Tag des HERRN ist nahe über alle Heiden. Wie du getan hast, soll dir wieder geschehen; und wie du verdient hast, so soll dir's wieder auf deinen Kopf kommen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ty HERRENS dag är nära för alla hednafolk. Såsom du har gjort, så skall man ock göra mot dig; dina gärningar skola komma tillbaka över ditt eget huvud.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">การ รื้อ ทำลาย เอ โดม เปรียบ ได้ กับ วัน แห่ง พระ เยโฮ วาห์ใน อนาคต เพราะ วัน แห่ง พระ เยโฮ วาห์ใกล้ ประชาชาติ ทั้งสิ้น เข้า มา แล้ว เจ้า กระทำ แก่ เขา อย่างไร ก็ จะ มี ผู้ มาก ระ ทำ แก่ เจ้า อย่าง นั้น การ ตอบแทน ของ เจ้า จะ กลับ มา ตก บน ศีรษะ ของ เจ้า เอง</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						15
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.16" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ka rite hoki ki ta koutou inumanga i runga i toku maunga tapu; ka pena ano te inu a nga tauiwi katoa a ake nei, ake nei; ina, ka inu ratou, ka horomia ano e ratou, a me te mea i kore ratou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Phải, như các ngươi đã uống trên núi thánh ta thể nào, thì hết thảy các nước cũng sẽ cứ uống thể ấy; phải, chúng nó sẽ uống và nuốt đi, rồi chúng nó sẽ như vốn không hề có!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Car, comme vous avez bu sur ma montagne sainte, Ainsi toutes les nations boiront sans cesse; Elles boiront, elles avaleront, Et elles seront comme si elles n`avaient jamais été.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa toy ny nisotroanareo teo an-tendrombohitra masina, Dia toy izany koa no hisotroan'ny firenena rehetra mandrakariva, Eny, hisotro izy ka hitelina, Ary ho toy ny tsy ary izy.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Mert a mint ti ittatok szent hegyemen, úgy isznak szüntelen  az összes népek; bizony isznak és hörpengetnek, és olyanok lesznek, mintha nem lettek volna.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ngokuba njengoko nisele ngako entabeni yam engcwele, ziya kuhlala zisela ngokunjalo zonke iintlanga, zisele zibizele,  zibe njengabangabangakho.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">너희가 내 성산에서 마신 것 같이 만국인이 항상 마시리니 곧 마시고 삼켜서 본래 없던 것 같이 되리라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Kaip jūs gėrėte mano šventame kalne, taip visos tautos gers nuolatos ir jos pražus lyg nebuvusios.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Ибо, как вы пили на святой горе Моей, так все народы всегда будут пить, будут пить, проглотят и будут, как бы их не было.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Di atas gunung-Ku yang suci umat-Ku telah minum-minuman yang melambangkan hukumannya. Tetapi minuman bagi bangsa-bangsa di bumi ini lebih pahit lagi. Hukuman itu tak dapat mereka hindari. Mereka harus meminumnya sampai habis, kemudian mereka akan lenyap tanpa bekas.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kay ingon nga kamo nanginum ibabaw sa akong balaan nga bukid, sa mao nga pagkaagi ang tanang mga nasud manginum sa walay paghunong; oo, sila manginum, ug motulon, ug mahimo nga daw wala sila mangatawo.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ယုဒအမျိုးသားတို့သည် သန့်ရှင်းသော ငါ့တောင် ပေါ်မှာ စားသောက်သကဲ့သို့၊ ပတ်လည်၌နေသော လူမျိုး အပေါင်းတို့သည် စားသောက်ရကြလိမ့်မည်။ စားသောက် ၍ မျိုသဖြင့် မရှိဘူးသောသူကဲ့သို့ ဖြစ်ရကြလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Joß nak xerecßa xcßahil li rahobtesîc lâex saß lin tzûl Sión, joßcan ajcuiß nak teßrecßa xcßahil li rahobtesîc chixjunileb li tenamit toj retal teßosokß.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Lebo jako ste pili na vrchu mojej svätosti, tak budú piť všetky tie národy ustavične, a tedy budú piť a budú hltať a budú, jako keby ich nebolo bývalo.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						किनकि जसरी तिमीले पवित्र पहाडमा दाखरस पिएर खुशी मनायौ, त्यसरी नै सबै अन्य जातिहरूले निरन्तर मेरो दण्ड पिउँनेछन् अनि उनीहरू सबै लोप भएर जानेछन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Jer kao što ste vi pili na svetoj gori mojoj, tako će piti svi narodi vazda, piće, i ždreće, i biće kao da ih nije bilo.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						For likesom I har drukket på mitt hellige berg, skal alle folkene drikke uten å holde op; de skal drikke i fulle drag og bli som om de aldri hadde vært til. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Ey Yahudalılar, kutsal dağımda nasıl içtiyseniz, Bütün uluslar da öyle içecekler. İçip içip yok olacaklar, Hiç var olmamış gibi." 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						لانه كما شربتم على جبل قدسي يشرب جميع الامم دائما يشربون ويجرعون ويكونون كانهم لم يكونوا
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Pois como vós bebestes no meu santo monte, assim beberão de contínuo todas as nações; sim, beberão e sorverão, e serão como se nunca tivessem sido.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">quomodo enim bibisti super montem sanctum meum bibent omnes gentes iugiter et bibent et absorbent et erunt quasi non sint</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Διοτι καθως σεις επιετε επι το ορος το αγιον μου, ουτω θελουσι πινει διαπαντος παντα τα εθνη ναι, θελουσι πινει και θελουσιν εκροφει και θελουσιν εισθαι ως οι μη υπαρχοντες
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Want net soos julle gedrink het op my heilige berg, sal al die nasies gedurigdeur drink, ja, hulle sal drink en swelg en word asof hulle nooit bestaan het nie.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Pèp mwen an pase pa l' anba men mwen sou mòn ki apa pou mwen an. Konsa tou, tout nasyon yo pral pran pa yo san rete. Yo pral pran jouk yo p'ap kapab ankò. Yo pral disparèt tankou si yo pa t' janm la
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Phải , như các ngươi đã uống trên núi thánh ta thể_nào , thì hết_thảy các nước cũng sẽ cứ uống thể ấy ; phải , chúng_nó sẽ uống và nuốt đi , rồi chúng_nó sẽ như vốn không hề có !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						כי כאשר שתיתם על הר קדשי ישתו כל הגוים תמיד ושתו ולעו והיו כלוא היו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">For as you have drunk on my holy mountain, so will all the nations drink continually. Yes, they will drink, swallow down, and will be as though they had not been.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మీరు నా పరిశుద్ధ  మైన కొండమీద త్రాగినట్లు అన్యజనులందరును నిత్యము త్రాగుదురు; తాము ఇక నెన్నడు నుండనివారైనట్లు వారేమియు మిగులకుండ త్రాగుదురు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Защото както вие,находящи се на светия ми хълм, пиехте от гнева ми, Така непрестанно ще пият всичките народи; Да! ще пият и ще поглъщат, И ще бъдат като че не са били.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kakor ste namreč pili na gori svetosti moje, tako bodo neprestano pili vsi narodi; da, pili bodo in srkali in bodo kakor taki, ki jih nikdar ni bilo.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						زیراچنانکه بر کوه مقدس من نوشیدید، همچنان جمیع امت‌ها خواهند نوشید و آشامیده، خواهندبلعید و چنان خواهند شد که گویا نبوده‌اند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 Thi som I drak på mit hellige Bjerg, skal alle Folkene drikke uden Ophør; de skal drikke og rave og blive, som om de aldrig havde været til.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sillä niinkuin te olette juoneet minun pyhällä vuorellani, niin  tulevat kaikki pakanakansat juomaan ainiaan: he juovat ja särpivät ja  ovat, niinkuin ei heitä olisi ollutkaan.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						你 們猶 大人 在 我 聖山 怎 樣 喝 了 苦杯 、 萬國 也 必 照 樣 常常 地 喝 ． 且 喝 且 咽 、 他 們就歸於 無有
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Zama sanda mate kaŋ cine araŋ haŋ ay tondi hananta boŋ, Yaadin cine no dumi cindey kulu ga haŋ, duumi. Oho, i ga haŋ, i ma gon, Edom ma ciya danga day a mana te ce fo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						你 們 猶 大 人 在 我 聖 山 怎 樣 喝 了 苦 杯 、 萬 國 也 必 照 樣 常 常 地 喝 ． 且 喝 且 咽 、 他 們 就 歸 於 無 有 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						जिस प्रकार तू ने मेरे पवित्रा पर्वत पर पिया, उसी प्रकार से सारी अन्यजातियां लगातार पीती रहेंगी, वरन वे सुड़क- सुड़ककर पीएंगी, और एसी हो जाएंगी जैसी कभी हुई ही नहीं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nebo poněvadž vy na mé hoře svaté píti bedete, nadtoť píti budou všickni národové ustavičně. Píti, pravím, a požírati budou, až budou, jako by jich nebylo.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						CXar kiel vi trinkis sur Mia sankta monto, tiel trinkos cxiam cxiuj nacioj; ili trinkos, trinkos gxisfunde, gxis ili farigxos kiel tute ne ekzistintaj.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Sepse ashtu si keni pirë mbi malin tim të shenjtë, kështu do të pinë tërë kombet vazhdimisht; po, do të pinë, do të rrëkëllejnë dhe do të jenë si të mos kenë qenë kurrë".
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Poiché come avete bevuto sul mio monte santo così berranno tutte le genti senza fine, berranno e tracanneranno: e saranno come se non fossero mai stati
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Því að eins og þér hafið drukkið á mínu heilaga fjalli, svo skulu allar þjóðirnar drekka stöðuglega. Þær skulu drekka og sötra og verða eins og þær aldrei hefðu til verið. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						का? कारण तू माझ्या पवित्र पर्वतावर रक्त सांडलेस म्हणून दुसरी राष्ट्रेही तुझे रक्त सांडतील. तू संपशील. तू कधी अस्तित्वात नव्हतास, अशीच तुझी दशा होईल. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたがたがわが聖なる山で飲んだように、周囲のもろもろの民も飲む。すなわち彼らは飲んでよろめき、かつてなかったようになる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Porque como bebisteis en mi santo monte, beberán todas las naciones de alrededor. Beberán ruidosamente, y quedarán como si nunca hubiesen existido
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo sidaad buurtayda quduuska ah korkeeda wax ugu cabteen ayaa quruumaha oo dhammuna had iyo goorba wax u cabbi doonaan, haah, iyagu way cabbi doonaan oo way liqi doonaan, oo waxay ahaan doonaan sidii iyagoo aan weligood ahaanin.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Ka tang siangthou-a na dawn bang un, nam tengtengten lah a dawn gige sin ngal ua, ahi, a dawn ding ua, a valh ding ua, piang lou bang maiin a om ding uh.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನೀವು ನನ್ನ ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧ ಪರ್ವತದ ಮೇಲೆ ಕುಡಿದ ಹಾಗೆಯೇ ಜನಾಂಗಗಳೆಲ್ಲಾ ನಿತ್ಯವಾಗಿ ಕುಡಿಯುವವು; ಹೌದು, ಕುಡಿದು ನುಂಗಿಬಿಡುವವು; ಇಲ್ಲದೆ ಇದ್ದವರ ಹಾಗೆಯೇ ಇರುವವು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						For as ye have drunk upon my holy mountain, so shall all the heathen drink continually, yea, they shall drink, and they shall swallow down, and they shall be as though they had not been.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Zoals u op mijn heilige berg hebt gedronken, zo zullen alle omringende volken drinken uit de beker met mijn straf en worden als nooit bestaan.</lang><lang id="Croatian">"Jest, kako vi piste na svetoj mi gori, pit će svi narodi bez oduška, pit će i iskapiti - i bit će k'o da ih nigda bilo nije.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Bo ponieważ wy pić będziecie na górze mojej świętej, tak pić będą wszystkie narody; ustawicznie, mówię, pić i pożerać będą, aż się staną, jakoby ich nie było.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เจ้าดื่มอยู่บนภูเขาบริสุทธิ์ของเราฉันใด ประชาชาติทั้งสิ้นก็จะดื่มไม่หยุดฉันนั้น เออ เขาจะดื่มแล้วก็โอนเอนไป เขาจะเป็นเหมือนอย่างที่ไม่เคยเกิดมา</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Sapagka't kung paanong kayo'y nagsiinom sa aking banal na bundok, gayon magsisiinom na palagi ang lahat na bansa, oo, sila'y magsisiinom, at magsisitungga, at magiging wari baga sila'y hindi nangabuhay. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた がた が わが 聖 な る 山 で 飲 ん だ よう に 、 周囲 の もろもろ の 民 も 飲 む 。 すなわち 彼 ら は 飲 ん で よろめき 、 かつて な かっ た よう に な る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിങ്ങള്‍ എന്റെ വിശുദ്ധപര്‍വ്വതത്തില്‍വെച്ചു കുടിച്ചതുപോലെ സകലജാതികളും ഇടവിടാതെ കുടിക്കും; അവര്‍ മോന്തിക്കുടിക്കയും ജനിക്കാത്തവരെപ്പോലെ ആകയും ചെയ്യും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Căci, după cum aţi băut paharul mîniei, voi cei de pe muntele Meu cel sfînt, tot aşa, toate neamurile îl vor bea necurmat; vor bea, vor sorbi din el, şi vor fi ca şi cînd n'ar fi fost niciodată.``
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Denn wie ihr auf meinem heiligen Berge getrunken habt, so sollen alle Heiden täglich trinken; ja, sie sollen's aussaufen und verschlingen und sollen sein, als wären sie nie gewesen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ja, såsom I haven druckit på mitt heliga berg, så skola ock alla hednafolk få dricka beständigt, de skola få dricka kalken i botten och bliva såsom hade de ej varit till.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เจ้า ดื่ม อยู่ บน ภูเขา บริสุทธิ์ ของ เรา ฉันใด ประชาชาติ ทั้งสิ้น ก็ จะ ดื่ม ไม่ หยุด ฉันนั้น เออ เขา จะ ดื่ม แล้ว ก็ โอนเอน ไป เขา จะ เป็น เหมือน อย่าง ที่ ไม่ เคย เกิด มา</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						16
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.17" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Otiia tera ano nga mea ka mawhiti i Maunga Hiona, a ka tapu tera; a ka riro o ratou wahi i te whare o Hakopa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nhưng sẽ còn lại những người trốn khỏi trên núi Si-ôn, núi ấy sẽ là thánh, và nhà Gia-cốp sẽ được sản nghiệp mình.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Mais le salut sera sur la montagne de Sion, elle sera sainte, Et la maison de Jacob reprendra ses possessions.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa ao an-tendrombohitra Ziona dia hisy izay sisa afaka, Ary ho masina izy; Ary ny taranak'i Jakoba hahalasa ny fananany.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						De a Sion hegyén szabadulás lészen, és szentté lészen az, és a Jákób háza  birtokba veszi az õ örökségét.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ke, entabeni yeZiyon kuya kubakho okusindileyo, kube yingcwele; indlu kaYakobi izihluthe iindawo eyazihluthwayo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">오직 시온산에서 피할 자가 있으리니 그 산이 거룩할 것이요 야곱 족속은 자기 기업을 누릴 것이며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Bet Siono kalne bus išgelbėjimas ir šventumas. Tada Jokūbo namai užvaldys savo nuosavybę.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						А на горе Сионе будет спасение, и будет она святынею; и дом Иакова получит во владение наследие свое.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						"Tetapi di Gunung Sion, akan ada yang selamat, dan gunung itu menjadi tempat yang khusus untuk Aku. Maka keturunan Yakub akan memiliki kembali tanah pusaka mereka
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Apan didto sa bukid sa Sion magapuyo kadtong mga nangalagiw, ug kana mahimong balaan; ug ang balay ni Jacob makabaton sa ilang mga napanag-iya.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ဇိအုန်တောင်ပေါ်မှာ ဘေးလွတ်သောသူအချို့ ရှိကြလိမ့်မည်။ သန့်ရှင်းသောအရပ်ဖြစ်လိမ့်မည်။ ယာ ကုပ်အမျိုးသည် မိမိပိုင်ထိုက်သောမြေကို ပိုင်ရလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Abanan eb li cuanqueb saß li tzûl Sión teßcolekß. Ut teßsantobresîk. Ut eb li ralal xcßajol laj Jacob teßrêchani cuißchic lix naßajeb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Ale na vrchu Sione bude uniklé, a vrch Sion bude svätým, a dom Jakobov bude dedične vládnuť svojimi vlastníctvami.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तर सियोन पहाडमा केही जीवितहरू हुनेछन्। र सियोन पवित्र हुनेछ। याकूबको देशले सबै चीजहरू फेरि पाउँनेछ जुन त्यसको थियो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A na gori će Sionu biti spasenje, i biće sveta, i dom će Jakovljev naslediti nasledstvo svoje.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men på Sions berg skal det være en flokk av undslopne, og det skal være hellig; og Jakobs hus skal ta sine eiendommer i eie. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    "Ama kurtulanlar Siyon Dağı'nda toplanacak Ve orası kutsal olacak. Yakup soyu da mirasına kavuşacak. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						واما جبل صهيون فتكون عليه نجاة ويكون مقدّسا ويرث بيت يعقوب مواريثهم.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Mas no monte de Sião haverá livramento, e ele será santo; e os da casa de Jacó possuirão as suas herdades.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et in monte Sion erit salvatio et erit sanctus et possidebit domus Iacob eos qui se possederant</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Επι δε του ορους Σιων θελει εισθαι σωτηρια και θελει εισθαι αγιον και ο οικος Ιακωβ θελει κατακληρονομησει τας κληρονομιας αυτων
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar op die berg Sion sal daar ontkoming wees, en dit sal 'n heiligdom wees; en die huis van Jakob sal sy besittings in besit neem.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Men, sou mòn Siyon an, kèk moun pral sove. Se yon kote ki pral apa nèt pou mwen. Moun fanmi Jakòb yo pral reprann tout peyi lènmi te wete nan men yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nhưng sẽ còn lại những người trốn khỏi trên núi Si-ôn , núi ấy sẽ là thánh , và nhà Gia-cốp sẽ được sản_nghiệp mình .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ובהר ציון תהיה פליטה והיה קדש וירשו בית יעקב את מורשיהם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But in Mount Zion, there will be those who escape, and it will be holy. The house of Jacob will possess their possessions.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అయితే సీయోను కొండ ప్రతిష్ఠితమగును, తప్పించుకొనినవారు దానిమీద నివసింతురు, యాకోబు సంతతివారు తమ స్వాస్థ్యములను స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						А на Сионския хълм ще се намерят оцелелите, И той ще бъде свет; И Якововият дом ще владее изново своето наследство.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ali na gori Sionu bode rešitev, in bode sveta; in v last prejme hiša Jakobova posesti onih.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اما بر کوه صهیون نجات خواهد بود ومقدس خواهد شد و خاندان یعقوب میراث خودرا به تصرف خواهند‌آورد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Men på Zions Bjerg skal der være Frelse, og det skal være en Helligdom, og Jakobs Hus skal tage sine Ejendomme i Eje.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta Siionin vuorella saavat olla pelastuneet, ja se on oleva pyhä,  ja Jaakobin heimo on perivä perintönsä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						在 錫安山 必有 逃脫 的 人 、 那 山 也 必 成聖 ． 雅各 家 必得 原有 的 產業
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Amma Sihiyona tondo ra i ga boro fooyaŋ gar kaŋ ga yana. A ga ciya hanante, Yakuba kunda mo ga nga mayray haro ŋwa. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						在 錫 安 山 必 有 逃 脫 的 人 、 那 山 也 必 成 聖 ． 雅 各 家 必 得 原 有 的 產 業 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						परन्तु उस समय सिरयोन पर्वत पर बचे हुए लोग रहेंगे, ओर वह पवित्रास्थान ठहरेगा; और याकूब का घराना अपने निज भागों का अधिकारी होगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Na hoře pak Sion bude vysvobození, a bude svatá, a tak dědičně držeti bude dům Jákobův dědictví svá.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed sur la monto Cion estos savigxo, kaj gxi estos sankta; kaj la domo de Jakob ekposedos tiujn, kiuj ilin posedis.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						"Por mbi malin e Sionit do të jenë ata që mbijetuan dhe do të jetë një vend i shenjtë; dhe shtëpia e Jakobit do të shtjerë në dorë pronat e veta.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ma sul monte Sion vi saranno superstiti e saranno santi e la casa di Giacobbe avrà in mano i suoi possessori
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En á Síonfjalli skal frelsun verða, og það skal heilagt vera, og Jakobs niðjar skulu fá aftur eignir sínar. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						पण सियोन पर्वतावर काही वाचलेले असतील. ते माझे खास लोक असतील. याकोबाचे राष्ट्र त्याच्या मालकीच्या गोष्टी परत स्वत:कडे घेईल. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						しかしシオンの山には、のがれる者がいて、聖なる所となる。またヤコブの家はその領地を獲る。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						"Pero en el monte Sion estarán los libertados, y será santo. La casa de Jacob poseerá las posesiones de ellos
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiinse Buur Siyoon waxaa joogi doona kuwa baxsaday, oo iyana quduus bay ahaan doontaa, oo reer Yacquubna waxay lahaan doonaan waxyaalihii dhaxalkoodii ahaa.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Zion tangah bel tai khete a om ding ua, a siangthou ding; huan, Jakob inkoten a goutante uh a tang ding uh.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಆದರೆ ಚೀಯೋನ್‌ ಪರ್ವತದಲ್ಲಿ ಬಿಡುಗಡೆ ಇರುವದು, ಅದು ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧ ವಾಗಿರುವದು; ಯಾಕೋಬಿನ ಮನೆತನದವರು ತಮ್ಮ ಸ್ವಾಸ್ತ್ಯಗಳನ್ನು ಸ್ವತಂತ್ರಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವರು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						But upon mount Zion shall be deliverance, and there shall be holiness; and the house of Jacob shall possess their possessions.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Maar de berg Sion zal een toevluchtsoord zijn, een afgezonderde schuilplaats. Het volk Israël zal het land weer in bezit nemen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Al' na gori Sionu bit će spasenici - postat će sveta - i dom će Jakovljev baštiniti svoju baštinu.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A na górze Syon będzie wybawienie, a ta góra będzie święta, i posiędzie dom Jakóbowy osiadłości swe.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ในยุด 1000 ปี อิสราเอลจะได้แผ่นดินของเอซาวเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์แต่จะมีคนรอดพ้นในภูเขาศิโยน และที่นั้นจะบริสุทธิ์ และวงศ์วานของยาโคบจะได้ถือกรรมสิทธิ์ที่ดินอันเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์ของเขา</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Nguni't sa bundok ng Sion ay doroon yaong nangakatatanan, at magiging banal; at aariin ng sangbahayan ni Jacob ang kaniyang mga pag-aari. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 しかし シオン の 山 に は 、 のがれ る 者 が い て 、 聖 な る 所 と な る 。 また ヤコブ の 家 は その 領地 を 獲 る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						എന്നാല്‍ സീയോന്‍ പര്‍വ്വതത്തില്‍ ഒരു രക്ഷിത ഗണം ഉണ്ടാകും; അതു വിശുദ്ധമായിരിക്കും; യാക്കോബ്ഗൃഹം തങ്ങളുടെ അവകാശങ്ങളെ കൈവശമാക്കും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						,,Dar mîntuirea va fi pe muntele Sionului, el va fi sfînt, şi casa lui Iacov îşi va lua înapoi moşiile.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Aber auf dem Berge Zion wird eine Errettung sein, und er soll heilig sein, und das Haus Jakob soll seine Besitzer besitzen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men på Sions berg skall finnas en räddad skara, och det skall vara en helig plats; och Jakobs hus skall åter få råda över sina besittningar.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ใน ยุด 1000 ปี อิส รา เอลจะได้ แผ่นดิน ของ เอ ซาว เป็น กรรมสิทธิ์ แต่ จะ มีค น รอด พ้น ใน ภูเขา ศิโยน และ ที่ นั้น จะ บริสุทธิ์ และ วงศ์วาน ของ ยา โค บ จะ ได้ ถือ กรรมสิทธิ์ ที่ดิน อันเป็น กรรมสิทธิ์ ของ เขา</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						17
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.18" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						A hei ahi te whare o Hakopa, hei mura ano te whare o Hohepa, hei kakau witi hoki te whare o Ehau: ka ngiha ratou i roto i a ratou, a pau ake, kahore hoki he morehu o te whare o Ehau: na Ihowa nei hoki te kupu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nhà Gia-cốp sẽ là lửa, và nhà Giô-sép sẽ là ngọn lửa; nhà Ê-sau sẽ là đống rơm, mà chúng nó sẽ đốt và thiêu đi. Nhà Ê-sau sẽ không còn sót chi hết; vì Ðức Giê-hô-va đã phán vậy.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						La maison de Jacob sera un feu, et la maison de Joseph une flamme; Mais la maison d`Ésaü sera du chaume, Qu`elles allumeront et consumeront; Et il ne restera rien de la maison d`Ésaü, Car l`Éternel a parlé.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ny taranak'i Jakoba ho afo, Ary ny taranak'i Josefa ho lelafo, Fa ny taranak'i Esao kosa ho vodivary, Ary harehitr'ireny izy ka holevoniny; Ary tsy hisy sisa afaka ny taranak'i Esao, Fa Jehovah no efa niteny.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						És a Jákób háza tûz lészen, és a József háza láng; az Ézsau  háza pedig pozdorja; és meggyújtják és megemésztik õket, és nem marad meg senki Ézsau házából, mert az Úr szólott.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Indlu kaYakobi iya kuba ngumlilo, nendlu kaYosefu ibe lilangatye; indlu kaEsawu ibe ziindiza, batshise phakathi kwabo, babadle, kungabikho usalayo wasendlwini kaEsawu; ngokuba uYehova uthethile.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">야곱 족속은 불이 될 것이요 요셉 족속은 불꽃이 될 것이며 에서 족속은 초개가 될 것이라 그들이 그의 위에 붙어서 그를 사를 것인즉 에서 족속에 남은 자가 없으리니 이는 여호와께서 말씀하셨음이니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jokūbo namai bus ugnis, Juozapo namai­liepsna, o Ezavo namai­ražienos. Jie padegs ir sudegins juos, ir niekas iš Ezavo namų nepabėgs,­sako Viešpats.­
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						И дом Иакова будет огнем, и дом Иосифа – пламенем, а дом Исавов– соломою: зажгут его, и истребят его, и никого не останется из дома Исава: ибо Господь сказал это.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Umat-Ku Israel akan seperti api yang membakar habis keturunan Esau, seperti api membakar habis jerami di ladang. Tak seorang pun dari keturunan Esau akan luput. Aku, TUHAN telah berbicara
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug ang balay ni Jacob mahimong kalayo, ug ang balay ni Jose mahimong siga, ug ang balay ni Esau mahimong pulaig, ug kini manga sunog sa taliwala nila, ug magaut-ut kanila; ug walay bisan unsa nga mahabilin sa balay ni Esau; kay si Jehova namulong niana.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ယာကုပ်အမျိုးသည် မီး၊ ယောသပ်အမျိုးသည် မီးလျှံ၊ ဧသောအမျိုးသည် အမှိုက်ဖြစ်လျက် မီးညှိ၍ လောင်သဖြင့်၊ ဧသောအမျိုးသား မကျန်ကြွင်းရ။ ထာဝရ ဘုရားမိန့်တော်မူပြီ။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb li ralal xcßajol laj Jacob chanchanakeb li xam. Eb li ralal xcßajol laj José chanchanakeb li rakß xam. Ut eb li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú chanchan nak nacßat li qßuim nak teßosokß. Teßsachekß ruheb chi junaj cua li ralal xcßajol laj Esaú. Mâ jun saß xyânkeb teßcolekß. Lâin li Kâcuaß xinyehoc re aßin.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A dom Jakobov bude ohňom a dom Jozefov plameňom, a dom Ezavov bude slamou, a rozpália sa na neho a strávia ho, ani nebude toho, kto by pozostal domu Ezavovmu, lebo Hospodin hovoril.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						याकूबको कुल बल्दै गरेको आगो जस्तै हुनेछ। यूसुफको घर आगोको ज्वाला जस्तै हुनेछ। तर एसावको देश चाँहि अँगार जस्तै हुनेछ। यहूदाका मानिसहरूले एदोमको मानिसहरूलाई नष्ट पार्नेछन्। एसावको राष्ट्रमा कोही पनि बाँच्नेछैन।” किनभने परमप्रभु परमेश्वरले यसो भन्नु भएकोछ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I dom će Jakovljev biti oganj i dom Josifov plamen, a dom Isavov strnjika; i razgoreće se na njih, i spaliće ih; i neće biti ostataka domu Isavovom, jer Gospod reče.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Og Jakobs hus skal bli en ild, og Josefs hus en lue, og Esaus hus skal bli til halm, og de skal sette ild på det og fortære det, og det skal ikke bli nogen tilbake av Esaus hus, for Herren har talt. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Yakup soyu ateş, Yusuf soyu alev, Esav soyu anız olacak. Onları yakıp yok edecekler. Esav soyundan kurtulan olmayacak." RAB böyle diyor. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ويكون بيت يعقوب نارا وبيت يوسف لهيبا وبيت عيسو قشا فيشعلونهم وياكلونهم ولا يكون باق من بيت عيسو لان الرب تكلم.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						E a casa de Jacó será um fogo, e a casa de José uma chama, e a casa de Esaú restolho; aqueles se acenderão contra estes, e os consumirão; e ninguém mais restará da casa de Esaú; porque o Senhor o disse.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et erit domus Iacob ignis et domus Ioseph flamma et domus Esau stipula et succendentur in eis et devorabunt eos et non erunt reliquiae domus Esau quia Dominus locutus est</lang><lang id="Greek">
						και ο οικος Ιακωβ θελει εισθαι πυρ και ο οικος Ιωσηφ φλοξ, ο δε οικος Ησαυ ως καλαμη και θελουσιν εξαφθη κατ' αυτων και καταφαγει αυτους και δεν θελει εισθαι υπολοιπον του οικου Ησαυ διοτι Κυριος ελαλησε.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Dan sal die huis van Jakob 'n vuur wees en die huis van Josef 'n vlam, maar die huis van Esau 'n stoppel; en dié sal hulle aan die brand steek en hulle verteer, sodat daar geen oorblyfsel vir die huis van Esau sal wees nie, want die HERE het dit gespreek.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Moun fanmi Jakòb yo pral tankou dife. Pitit pitit Jozèf yo pral tankou yon flanm dife. Yo pral detwi pitit Ezaou yo nèt tankou dife nan zèb chèch. Pesonn nan fanmi Ezaou a p'ap chape. Se mwen menm, Seyè a, ki di sa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nhà_Gia - cốp sẽ là lửa , và nhà Giô-sép sẽ là ngọn lửa ; nhà Ê - sau sẽ là đống rơm , mà chúng_nó sẽ đốt và thiêu đi . Nhà Ê - sau sẽ không còn sót chi hết ; vì Ðức_Giê - hô-va đã phán vậy .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						והיה בית יעקב אש ובית יוסף להבה ובית עשו לקש ודלקו בהם ואכלום ולא יהיה שריד לבית עשו כי יהוה דבר׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">The house of Jacob will be a fire, the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble. They will burn among them, and devour them. There will not be any remaining to the house of Esau." Indeed, Yahweh has spoken.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మరియు యాకోబు సంతతి వారు అగ్నియు, యోసేపు సంతతివారు మంటయు అగుదురు; ఏశావు సంతతివారు వారికి కొయ్యకాలుగా ఉందురు; ఏశావు సంతతివారిలో ఎవడును తప్పించుకొన కుండ యోసేపు సంతతివారు వారిలో మండి వారిని కాల్చుదురు. యెహోవా మాట యిచ్చియున్నాడు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Якововият дом ще бъде огън, И Йосифовият дом като пламък; А Исавовият дом като слама; И те ще я запалят и ще я изгорят, Тъй щото никой няма да остане от Исавовия дом; Защото Господ изговори това.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In hiša Jakobova bode ogenj in hiša Jožefova plamen, hiša Ezavova pa strnišče; in bosta goreli med njimi in jih požrli, da ne preostane hiši Ezavovi noben ostanek; kajti GOSPOD je govoril.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و خاندان یعقوب آتش و خاندان یوسف شعله و خاندان عیسو کاه عوبدیا خواهند بود و در میان ایشان مشتعل شده، ایشان را خواهد سوزانید و برای خاندان عیسو بقیتی نخواهد ماند زیرا خداوند تکلم نموده است.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Jakobs Hus skal blive en Ild og Josefs Hus en Lue, men Esaus Hus skal blive Strå, og de skal sætte Ild derpå og fortære det, og ingen af Esaus Hus skal undslippe, så sandt HERREN har talet.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Jaakobin heimo on oleva tuli ja Joosefin heimo liekki, mutta Eesaun  heimo kuin olki, ja ne polttavat sen ja kuluttavat sen; eikä jää  pakoonpäässyttä Eesaun heimosta. Sillä Herra on puhunut.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						雅各 家 必 成為 大火 ． 約瑟 家 必為火燄 ． 以 掃家 必 如 碎秸 、 火 必將 他 燒著 吞滅 ． 以 掃家必無餘剩 的 ． 這是 耶和華 說的
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Saaya din ra Yakuba kunda ga ciya danji, Yusufu kunda mo ga ciya danji beele. Isuwa kunda mo ga hima sanda buunu cine, Kaŋ danji ga ŋwa i game ra, A m'i ŋwa ka ban. Boro kulu si cindi Isuwa kunda ra, Zama Rabbi no ka woodin ci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						雅 各 家 必 成 為 大 火 ． 約 瑟 家 必 為 火 燄 ． 以 掃 家 必 如 碎 秸 、 火 必 將 他 燒 著 吞 滅 ． 以 掃 家 必 無 餘 剩 的 ． 這 是 耶 和 華 說 的 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						तब याकूब का घराना आग, और यूसुफ का घराना लौ, और एसाव का घराना खूंटी बनेगा; और वे उन में आग लगाकर उनको भस्म करेंगे, और एसाव के घराने का कोई न बचेगा; क्योंकि यहोवा ही ने ऐसा कहा है।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						I bude dům Jákobův oheň, a dům Jozefův plamen, dům pak Ezau plevy, i rozpálí se na ně a sehltí je, aniž kdo pozůstane z domu Ezau; nebo Hospodin mluvil.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						La domo de Jakob estos fajro, la domo de Jozef estos flamo; sed la domo de Esav estos pajlo, oni ekbruligos gxin kaj ekstermos gxin, kaj neniu restos el la domo de Esav; cxar la Eternulo tion diris.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Shtëpia e Jakobit do të jetë një zjarr, shtëpia e Jozefit një flakë, por shtëpia e Esaut do të jetë si kallamishte: ata do ta djegin dhe do ta gllabërojnë, dhe shtëpisë së Esaut nuk do t'i mbetet asnjë trashëgimtar", sepse ka folur Zoti.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						La casa di Giacobbe sarà un fuoco e la casa di Giuseppe una fiamma, la casa di Esaù sarà come paglia: la bruceranno e la consumeranno, non scamperà nessuno della casa di Esaù, poiché il Signore ha parlato
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Og Jakobs hús mun verða að eldi og Jósefs hús að loga og Esaú hús að hálmi, og þeir munu kveikja í og eyða honum, svo að ekkert skal eftir verða af Esaúniðjum, því að Drottinn hefir talað það. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						याकोबाचे घराणे आगीप्रमाणे होईल योसेफाचे घराणे जाळासारखे असेल पण एसावाचे राष्ट्र राखेप्रमाणे होईल यहुदाचे लोक अदोम जाळतील, ते अदोमचा नाश करतील. एसाव राष्ट्रात मग कोणी शिल्लक राहणार नाही.” का? कारण परमेश्वर देव असे म्हणाला आहे. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						ヤコブの家は火となり、ヨセフの家は炎となり、エサウの家はわらとなる。彼らはその中に燃えて、これを焼く。エサウの家には残る者がないようになると主は言われた。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						La casa de Jacob será fuego, y la casa de José será llama. La casa de Edom será estopa, y ellos los quemarán y los consumirán. Ni un solo sobreviviente quedará de la casa de Esaú", porque Jehovah lo ha dicho
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Reer Yacquub dab buu ahaan doonaa, oo reer Yuusufna olol buu ahaan doonaa, reer Ceesawna bal jajab ah buu ahaan doonaa. Dhexdooday ku gubi doonaan oo iyagana way laasan doonaan, oo reer Ceesawna innaba waxba kama hadhi doonaan, waayo, Rabbigu sidaasuu ku hadlay.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Jakobinkote mei ahi ding ua, Joseph inkote meikuang ahi ding uh, Esau inkote buhpawl ding ahi ding ua, amau lakah a kuang ding uh, a kang mang vek ding uh: Esau inkote a val himhim a om kei ding uh: TOUPAN lah a chita ngala.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇದಲ್ಲದೆ ಯಾಕೋಬಿನ ಮನೆತನದವರು ಬೆಂಕಿಯಾಗಿಯೂ ಯೋಸೇಫನ ಮನೆತನದವರು ಜ್ವಾಲೆಯಾಗಿಯೂ ಇರುವರು; ಏಸಾವನ ಮನೆತನದವರು ಕೂಳೆಯಾಗು ವರು. ಅವರು ಹೊತ್ತಿಸಿ ಇವರನ್ನು ತಿಂದುಬಿಡುವರು; ಏಸಾವನ ಮನೆತನದವರಿಗೆ ಯಾರೂ ಉಳಿಯರು; ಕರ್ತನೇ ಅದನ್ನು ನುಡಿದಿದ್ದಾನೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And the house of Jacob shall be a fire, and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble, and they shall kindle in them, and devour them; and there shall not be any remaining of the house of Esau; for the LORD hath spoken it.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Israël zal zijn als een vuur dat de stoppelvelden van Edom in brand steekt. Er zullen geen overlevenden in Edom zijn, omdat de HERE het zo heeft bevolen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Dom će Jakovljev biti oganj, dom Josipov plamen, dom Ezavljev strnjika. Potpalit će ga i proždrijeti, i od doma Ezavljeva nitko neće ostati" - riječ je Jahvina.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						I stanie się dom Jakóbowy ogniem, a dom Józefowy płomieniem, dom zaś Ezawowy ścierniskiem; i rozpali się na nich, i strawi ich, a nikt nie zostanie z domu Ezawowego; bo Pan to mówił.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">วงศ์วานของยาโคบจะเป็นไฟ วงศ์วานของโยเซฟจะเป็นเปลวไฟ และวงศ์วานของเอซาวจะเป็นตอข้าว ไฟและเปลวไฟจะไหม้และเผาผลาญเสีย วงศ์วานของเอซาวจะไม่มีใครรอดได้เลย เพราะว่าพระเยโฮวาห์ได้ลั่นพระวาจาแล้ว</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang sangbahayan ni Jacob ay magiging isang apoy, at ang sangbahayan ni Jose ay isang liyab, at ang sangbahayan ni Esau ay dayami, at sila'y kanilang susunugin, at sila'y susupukin; at walang malalabi sa sangbahayan ni Esau; sapagka't sinalita ng Panginoon. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 ヤコブ の 家 は 火 と な り 、 ヨセフ の 家 は 炎 と な り 、 エサウ の 家 は わら と な る 。 彼 ら は その 中 に 燃え て 、 これ を 焼 く 。 エサウ の 家 に は 残 る 者 が な い よう に な る と 主 は 言 わ れ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അന്നു യാക്കോബ് ഗൃഹം തീയും യോസേഫ്ഗൃഹം ജ്വാലയും ഏശാവുഗൃഹം താളടിയും ആയിരിക്കും; അവര്‍ അവരെ കത്തിച്ചു ദഹിപ്പിച്ചുകളയും; ഏശാവുഗൃഹത്തിന്നു ശേഷിപ്പു ഉണ്ടാകയില്ല; യഹോവയല്ലോ അരുളിച്ചെയ്തിരിക്കുന്നതു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Casa lui Iacov va fi un foc, şi casa lui Iosif, o flacără; dar casa lui Esau va fi miriştea, pe care o vor aprinde şi o vor mistui; şi nu va mai rămînea niciunul din casa lui Esau, căci Domnul a vorbit!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und das Haus Jakob soll ein Feuer werden und das Haus Joseph eine Flamme, aber das Haus Esau Stroh; das werden sie anzünden und verzehren, daß dem Hause Esau nichts übrigbleibe; denn der HERR hat's geredet.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Då skall Jakobs hus bliva en eld och Josefs hus en låga, och Esaus hus skall varda såsom strå, och de skola antända det och förtära det, och ingen skall slippa undan av Esaus hus; ty så har HERREN talat.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">วงศ์วาน ของ ยา โค บ จะ เป็นไฟ วงศ์วาน ของ โย เซ ฟจะเป็น เปลว ไฟ และ วงศ์วาน ของ เอ ซาว จะ เป็น ตอ ข้าว ไฟ และ เปลว ไฟ จะ ไหม้ และ เผา ผลาญ เสีย วงศ์วาน ของ เอ ซาว จะ ไม่ มี ใคร รอด ได้ เลย เพราะว่า พระ เยโฮ วาห์ได้ ลั่น พระ วาจา แล้ว</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						18
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.19" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na ka riro te maunga o Ehau i te hunga o te tonga; me nga Pirihitini i te hunga o te mania; ka riro ano i a ratou nga mara a Eparaima me nga mara o Hamaria; mo Pineamine hoki a Kireara
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Những người ở phương nam sẽ được núi của Ê-sau, những kẻ ở đồng bằng sẽ được người Phi-li-tin làm kỷ vật, chúng nó sẽ được ruộng của Ép-ra-im và ruộng của Sa-ma-ri; những người Bên-gia-min sẽ được Ga-la-át.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ceux du midi posséderont la montagne d`Ésaü, Et ceux de la plaine le pays des Philistins; Ils posséderont le territoire d`Éphraïm et celui de Samarie; Et Benjamin possédera Galaad.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ny any amin'ny tany atsimo no hahalasa ny tendrombohitr'i Esao;Ary ny any amin'ny tany lemaka amoron-tsiraka no hahalasa ny Filistina; Hahalasa ny tanin'ny Efraima sy ny tany Samaria izy; Ary Benjamina hahalasa an'i Gileada. [Heb. sefela]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						A déliek örökség szerint bírják az Ézsau hegyét, a síkon lakók pedig a Filiszteusokat. És örökség szerint bírják az Efraim mezõit és Samaria mezõit; Benjámin pedig a Gileádot.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Abakwelasezantsi bozithimba iintaba zakwaEsawu;  nabasezithabazini bahluthe amaFilisti; bahluthe isisimi sakwaEfrayim, nesisimi sakwaSamari; uBhenjamin ahluthe elaseGiliyadi.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">남방 사람은 에서의 산을 얻을 것이며 평지 사람은 블레셋을 얻을 것이요 또 그들이 에브라임의 들과 사마리아의 들을 얻을 것 이며 베냐민은 길르앗을 얻을 것이며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tada pietiečiai užvaldys Ezavo kalnyną, o lygumų gyventojai­filistinus. Jie užvaldys Efraimo kalnus ir Samarijos laukus, o Benjaminas­Gileadą.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						И завладеют те, которые к югу, горою Исава, а которые в долине, – Филистимлянами; изавладеют полем Ефрема и полем Самарии, а Вениамин завладеет Галаадом.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Orang-orang Yehuda Selatan akan menduduki Edom. Orang-orang dari pegunungan sebelah barat akan mengalahkan wilayah Filistin. Suku Benyamin akan menduduki Gilead, dan Israel umat-Ku akan menguasai seluruh Efraim dan Samaria
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug sila nga atua sa Habagatan magapanag-iya sa bukid ni Esau, ug kadtong atua sa kapatagan magapanag-iya sa mga Filistehanon; ug sila magapanag-iya sa kaumahan sa Ephraim, ug sa kaumahan sa Samaria; ug si Benjamin magapanag-iya sa Galaad.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						တောင်မျက်နှာသားတို့သည် ဧသော၏တောင် ကို၎င်း၊ မြေညီသောအရပ်သားတို့သည် ဖိလိတ္တိပြည်ကို ၎င်း၊ ဧဖရိမ်လယ်ပြင်နှင့် ရှမာရိလယ်ပြင်ကို၎င်း၊ ဗင်္ယာ မိန်အမျိုးသည် ဂိလဒ်ပြည်ကို၎င်း သိမ်းယူကြလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb laj Israel li cuanqueb aran Neguev, aßaneb li teßêchanînk re li tzûl saß lix naßajeb laj Esaú. Ut eb laj Israel li cuanqueb saß li ru takßa Sefela, aßaneb li teßêchanînk re lix chßochßeb laj filisteo. Ut aßaneb ajcuiß li teßêchanînk re lix chßochßeb laj Efraín ut lix chßochßeb laj Samaria. Ut eb li ralal xcßajol laj Benjamín, aßaneb li teßêchanînk re li naßajej Galaad.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Tí na juhu budú dedične vládnuť vrchom Ezavovým a tí na rovine Filištínmi a budú dedične vládnuť poľom Efraimovým a poľom Samárie a Benjamin Gileádom.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तब नगेवका मानिसहरूले एसावको पहाडहरू अधिकार गर्नेछन् र बेंसीकाहरूले पलिश्तीको भूमिहरूमा अधिकार गर्नेछन्। यहूदाका मानिसहरूले एप्रैम र सामरियाको भूमिहरूमा अधिकार गर्नेछन् र बिन्यामीनले गिलादलाई अधिकार गर्नेछ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I naslediće jug, goru Isavovu, i ravnicu, Filisteje; i naslediće polje Jefremovo i polje samarijsko i Venijaminovo i Galad;</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Og de som bor i sydlandet, skal ta Esaus berg i eie, og de som bor i lavlandet, skal ta filistrenes land, og de skal ta Efra'ims land og Samarias land i eie, og Benjamin skal ta Gilead, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Yahudalılar'dan Negev halkı Esav'ın dağlarını; Şefela halkı Filist bölgesini; Yahudalılar'ın tümü Efrayim ve Samiriye topraklarını; Benyaminliler Gilat'ı mülk edinecekler. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ويرث اهل الجنوب جبل عيسو واهل السهل الفلسطينيين ويرثون بلاد افرايم وبلاد السامرة ويرث بنيامين جلعاد.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Ora, os do Negebe possuirão o monte de Esaú, e os da planície, os filisteus; possuirão também os campos de Efraim, e os campos de Samária; e Benjamim possuirá a Gileade.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et hereditabunt hii qui ad austrum montem Esau et qui in campestribus Philisthim et possidebunt regionem Ephraim et regionem Samariae et Beniamin possidebit Galaad</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Και οι της μεσημβριας θελουσι κατακληρονομησει το ορος του Ησαυ και οι της πεδινης τους Φιλισταιους και θελουσι κατακληρονομησει τους αγρους του Εφραιμ και τους αγρους της Σαμαρειας, ο δε Βενιαμιν την Γαλααδ,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Dan sal dié van die Suidland die gebergte van Esau, en dié van die Laeveld die land van die Filistyne in besit neem; en hulle sal die veld van Efraim en die veld van Samaría, en Benjamin Gílead in besit neem.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Moun pèp Izrayèl ki rete nan zòn Negèv la pral pran mòn Ezaou a pou yo. Moun pèp Izrayèl ki rete nan plenn ki nan pye mòn Jida yo pral pran peyi moun Filisti yo nan men yo. Moun pèp Izrayèl yo pral pran peyi Efrayim ak peyi Samari pou yo. Moun Benjamen yo pral pran peyi Galarad la pou yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Những người_ở phương nam sẽ được núi của Ê - sau , những kẻ ở đồng_bằng sẽ được người Phi-li-tin làm kỷ_vật , chúng_nó sẽ được ruộng của Ép - ra-im và ruộng của Sa-ma-ri ; những người Bên-gia-min sẽ được Ga-la-át .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						וירשו הנגב את הר עשו והשפלה את פלשתים וירשו את שדה אפרים ואת שדה שמרון ובנימן את הגלעד׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Those of the South will possess the mountain of Esau, and those of the lowland, the Philistines. They will possess the field of Ephraim, and the field of Samaria. Benjamin will possess Gilead.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						దక్షిణ దిక్కున నివసించువారు  ఏశావుయొక్క  పర్వత మును స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు;  మైదానమందుండువారు ఫిలిష్తీయులదేశమును  స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు; మరియు ఎఫ్రాయిమీయుల భూములను షోమ్రోనునకు చేరిన పొలమును వారు స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు. బెన్యామీ నీయులు గిలాదుదేశమును స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Жителите на юг ще владеят Исавовия хълм, И ония на поляните Филистимците, Ще владеят и Ефремовите ниви и Самарийските ниви; А Вениамин ще владее Галаад;
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In tisti, ki so proti Jugu, posedejo gorovje Ezavovo, in kateri so na ravnini, Filistejo, tudi posedejo poljane Efraimove in poljane samarijske, Benjamin pa posede Gilead.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						واهل جنوب کوه عیسو را و اهل هامون فلسطینیان را به تصرف خواهند‌آورد و صحرای افرایم وصحرای سامره را به تصرف خواهند‌آورد وبنیامین جلعاد را (متصرف خواهد شد).و اسیران این لشکر بنی‌اسرائیل ملک کنعانیان راتا صرفه به تصرف خواهند‌آورد و اسیران اورشلیم که در صفارد هستند شهرهای جنوب را به تصرف خواهند‌آورد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						De skal tage Sydlandet i Ejesammen med Esaus Bjerge og Lavlandet sammen med Filisterne; deskal tage Efraims Mark i Eje sammen med Samarias Mark og Ammoniterne sammen med Gilead.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Ja he ottavat perinnöksensä Etelämaan ynnä Eesaun vuoren, Alankomaan  ynnä filistealaiset; he ottavat perinnöksensä Efraimin maan ja Samarian  maan, Benjaminin ynnä Gileadin.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						南地 的 人 必 得以 掃山 、 高原 的 人 必 得 非利士地 、 也 得 以法 蓮地 、 和 撒瑪利 亞地 ． 便 雅憫人 必得 基列
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Negeb* borey binde ga Isuwa tondo mayray ŋwa, Safela* borey mo ma Filistancey ŋwa. I ga Ifraymu laabu toorimo ŋwa, da Samariya wano mo, Benyamin mo ga Jileyad mayra ŋwa. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						南 地 的 人 必 得 以 掃 山 、 高 原 的 人 必 得 非 利 士 地 、 也 得 以 法 蓮 地 、 和 撒 瑪 利 亞 地 ． 便 雅 憫 人 必 得 基 列 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						दक्खिन देश के लोग एसाव के पहाड़ के अधिकारी हो जाएंगे, और नीचे के देश के लोग पलिश्तियों के अधिकारी होंगे; और यहूदी, एप्रैम और समरिया के दिहात को अपने भाग में कर लेंगे, और बिन्यामीन गिलाद का अधिकारी होगा।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						A tak děditi budou v krajině polední s horou Ezau, i v rovině s Filistinskými; vládnouti také budou krajinou Efraimovou i krajinou Samařskou, a Beniaminovou i Galádskou.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj la sudanoj ekposedos la monton de Esav, kaj la logxantoj de la malaltajxo la Filisxtojn; ili ekposedos la kampojn de Efraim kaj la kampojn de Samario; kaj Benjamen posedos Gileadon.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Ata të Negevit do të zotërojnë malin e Esaut dhe fushën e vendit të Filistejve; do të zotërojnë edhe fushat e Efraimit dhe fushat e Samarisë dhe Beniamini do të zotërojë Galaadin.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Quelli del Negheb possederanno il monte d'Esaù e quelli della Sefèla il paese dei Filistei; possederanno il territorio di Efraim e di Samaria e Beniamino il Gàlaad
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Sunnlendingar skulu taka Esaúfjöll til eignar og Sléttumenn Filisteu. Þeir munu og taka Efraímsland og Samaríuland til eignar, og Benjamín Gíleað. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						नेगेवचे लोक एसावाच्या पर्वतावर राहतील डोंगराच्या पायथ्याशी राहणारे लोक पलिष्ट्यांचा देश आपल्या ताब्यात घेतील. ते एफ्राईमाच्या व शोमरोनच्या भूमीवर राहतील. गिलाद बन्यामीनच्या कबजात जाईल.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						ネゲブの人々はエサウの山を獲、セフェラの人々はペリシテびとを獲る。また彼らはエフライムの地、およびサマリヤの地を獲、ベニヤミンはギレアデを獲る。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Los del Néguev poseerán la región montañosa de Esaú; y los de la Sefela, la tierra de los filisteos. También poseerán los campos de Efraín y de Samaria, y los de Benjamín poseerán Galaad
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo dadka koonfur degganu waxay hantiyi doonaan buurta Ceesaw, oo kuwa bannaanka degganuna waxay hantiyi doonaan dalka reer Falastiin, oo weliba waxay hantiyi doonaan dalka reer Efrayim, iyo dalka reer Samaariya, oo reer Benyaamiinna waxay hantiyi doonaan dalka Gilecaad.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Sim lam miten Esau tang a tang ding ua; gam phaijanga miten philistia gam a tang ding ding uh: Ephriam lou leh Samari lou a tang ding uh: Benjamin in Gilead gam a tang ding.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ದಕ್ಷಿಣದವರು ಏಸಾವನ ಬೆಟ್ಟವನ್ನೂ ಬೈಲಿನವರು ಫಿಲಿಷ್ಟಿಯರನ್ನೂ ಸ್ವತಂತ್ರಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವರು; ಎಫ್ರಾಯಾಮಿನ ಹೊಲ ಗಳನ್ನು ಸಮಾರ್ಯದ ಹೊಲಗಳನ್ನು ಸಹ ಸ್ವಾಧೀನ ಮಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವರು ಮತ್ತು ಬೆನ್ಯಾವಿಾನನು ಗಿಲ್ಯಾದನ್ನು ಸ್ವತಂತ್ರಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವನು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And they of the south shall possess the mount of Esau; and they of the plain the Philistines: and they shall possess the fields of Ephraim, and the fields of Samaria: and Benjamin shall possess Gilead.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Dan zal mijn volk dat in Negeb woont, het begrgebied van Edom in bezit nemen. Die in het laagland wonen, zullen het land van de filisteinen innemen en weer beslag leggen op de velden van Efraïm en Samaria. En het volk Benjamin en Gilead weer in bezit nemen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Žitelji negepski baštinit će goru Ezavljevu, žitelji Šefele zemlju filistejsku; baštinit će kraj Efrajimov i kraj samarijski, a Benjamin će baštiniti Gilead.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A tak odziedziczą krainę południową z górą Ezawa, i równinę z Filistyóczykami; posiędą też krainę Efraimową, i krainę Samaryi, i Benjaminową i Galaadską.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คนเหล่านั้นที่อยู่ในภาคใต้จะได้ภูเขาเอซาวเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์ คนเหล่านั้นที่อยู่ในที่ราบจะได้แผ่นดินฟีลิสเตีย เขาจะได้แผ่นดินเอฟราอิมและแผ่นดินสะมาเรียเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์ และเบนยามินจะได้กิเลอาดเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At silang sa Timugan, ay mangagaari ng bundok ng Esau, at silang sa mababang lupa ay ng mga Filisteo; at kanilang aariin ang parang ng Ephraim, at ang parang ng Samaria; at aariin ng Benjamin ang Galaad. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 ネゲブ の 人々 は エサウ の 山 を 獲 、 セフェラ の 人々 は ペリシテ びと を 獲 る 。 また 彼 ら は エフライム の 地 、 および サマリヤ の 地 を 獲 、 ベニヤミン は ギレア デ を 獲 る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						തെക്കേ ദേശക്കാര്‍ ഏശാവിന്റെ പര്‍വ്വതവും താഴ്വീതിയിലുള്ളവര്‍ ഫെലിസ്ത്യദേശവും കൈവശമാക്കും; അവര്‍ എഫ്രയീംപ്രദേശത്തെയും ശമര്‍യ്യാപ്രദേശത്തെയും കൈവശമാക്കും; ബെന്യാമീനോ ഗിലെയാദിനെ കൈവശമാക്കും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Cei dela miazăzi vor stăpîni muntele lui Esau, şi cei din cîmpie ţara Filistenilor; vor stăpîni şi ţinutul lui Efraim şi al Samariei; şi Beniamin va stăpîni Galaadul.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und die gegen Mittag werden das Gebirge Esau, und die in den Gründen werden die Philister besitzen; ja sie werden das Feld Ephraims und das Feld Samarias besitzen, und Benjamin das Gebirge Gilead.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Och Sydlandets folk skall taga Esaus berg i besittning, och Låglandets folk skall taga filistéernas land; ja, också Efraims mark skall man taga i besittning, så ock Samariens mark.  Och Benjamin skall taga Gilead.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คน เหล่า นั้น ที่ อยู่ ใน ภาค ใต้ จะ ได้ ภูเขา เอ ซาว เป็น กรรมสิทธิ์ คน เหล่า นั้น ที่ อยู่ ใน ที่ราบ จะ ได้ แผ่นดิน ฟีลิสเตีย เขา จะ ได้ แผ่นดิน เอฟ รา อิมและ แผ่นดิน สะ มา เรียเป็นก ร รม สิทธิ์ และ เบน ยา มิ น จะ ได้ กิเลอาด เป็น กรรมสิทธิ์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						19
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.20" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na, ko nga whakarau o tenei ope, o nga tama a Iharaira, ko era i roto i nga Kanaani, ka riro i a ratou tae noa ki Harepata; a, ko nga whakarau o Hiruharama, ko era i Teparara, ka riro i a ratou nga pa o te tonga
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Những kẻ phu tù của cơ binh con cái Y-sơ-ra-ên ở giữa những người Ca-na-an, sẽ được đất nó cho đến Sa-rép-ta. Những phu tù của Giê-ru-sa-lem ở tại Sê-pha-rát sẽ được các thành phương nam.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Les captifs de cette armée des enfants d`Israël Posséderont le pays occupé par les Cananéens jusqu`à Sarepta, Et les captifs de Jérusalem qui sont à Sepharad Posséderont les villes du midi.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary ny babo amin'izao Zanak'Isiraely maro be izao hahalasa ny Kananita hatrany Zarefata, Ary ny babo tany Jerosalema, izay any Sefarada, dia hahalasa ny tanàna any amin'ny tany atsimo. [Na: marobe izao, izay any amin'ny Kananita hatrany Zerefata, sy ny babo, etc..]Ary hisy mpamonjy miakatra ho ao an-tendrombohitra Ziona Hitsara ny tendrombohitr'i Esao; Ary ho an'i Jehovah Jon 1:1
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Izráel fiainak ez a számûzött serege azokat, a melyek a Kananeusoké, mind Sarfátig; a jeruzsálemi számûzöttek pedig, a kik Szefarádban vannak, elfoglalják majd a déli városokat.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Abathinjwa bakule mpi yonyana bakaSirayeli baya kubahlutha abangamaKanan, bade base eTsarefa, abathinjwa baseYerusalem abaseSefaradi bahluthe imizi yelasezantsi.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">사로잡혔던 이스라엘의 뭇 자손은 가나안 사람에게 속한 땅을 사르밧까지 얻을 것이며 예루살렘의 사로잡혔던 자 곧 스바랏에 있는 자는 남방의 성읍들을 얻을 것이니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Izraelitai, sugrįžę iš tremties, užvaldys kanaaniečių kraštą iki Sareptos. Jeruzalės tremtiniai, kurie yra Sefarade, užvaldys pietų miestus.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						И переселенные из войска сынов Израилевых завладеют землею Ханаанскою до Сарепты, а переселенные из Иерусалима, находящиеся в Сефараде, получат во владение города южные.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Orang Israel Utara akan kembali dari pembuangan dan menduduki Fenisia sampai ke Zarfat. Orang-orang Yerusalem yang dibuang di Sardis, akan kembali dan memiliki kota-kota di bagian selatan Yehuda
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug ang mga binihag niining panona sa mga anak sa Israel, nga anaa sa taliwala sa mga Canaanhon, magapanag-iya bisan hangtud sa Sarepta; ug ang mga binihag sa Jerusalem, nga atua sa Sepharad, magapanag-iya sa mga ciudad sa Habagatan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သိမ်းသွားခြင်းကို ခံရ၍၊ ခါနနိလူတို့တွင်ရှိသော ဣသရေလအမျိုးအလုံးအရင်းသည် ဇရတ္တမြို့တိုင်အောင်၎င်း၊ သိမ်းသွားခြင်းကို ခံရ၍ သေဖရဒ်ပြည်၌ရှိသော ယေရုရှလင်မြို့သားတို့သည် တောင်မျက်နှာ မြို့ရွာတို့ကို ၎င်း သိမ်းယူကြလိမ့်မည်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb laj Israel li queßchapeß ut queßcßameß chi najt, aßaneb li teßêchanînk re lix chßochßeb laj cananeo. Tâcuulak toj saß li tenamit Sarepta. Ut eb laj Jerusalén li queßchapeß, li cuanqueb aran Sefarad, aßaneb li teßêchanînk reheb li tenamit li cuanqueb Neguev.Ut eb laj Israel li queßnumta saß xbêneb laj Edom teßxic saß li tzûl Sión chi taklânc saß xbêneb li cuanqueb saß xyânkeb li tzûl saß lix chßochß laj Esaú. Ut li Kâcuaß, aßan tâcuânk xcuanquil saß xbêneb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A zajatí toho vojska synov Izraelových budú vládnuť tým, čo bolo majetkom Kananejov až po Sareptu, a zajatí Jeruzalema, ktorí sú v Sefarade, budú dedične vládnuť mestami na juhu.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						इस्रएलीहरूका निर्वासितहरूले कनानीहरूको भूमि सपाराद सम्म आफ्नो बनाउनेछन्। यहूदाका मानिसहरूलाई यरूशलेम छोडनु र सपारादमा बस्न विवश पारिएको थियो। तर उनीहरूले नेगव शहरलाई अधिकार गर्नेछन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I zarobljena vojska sinova Izrailjevih naslediće šta je bilo hananejsko do Sarepte; a roblje jerusalimsko, što je u Sefaradu, naslediće južne gradove.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						og de av denne Israels hær som er bortført, skal ta det som finnes av kana'anitter like til Sarepta, og de bortførte fra Jerusalem som er i Sefarad, skal ta sydlandets byer i eie. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Kenan'dan sürülmüş olan İsrailli savaşçılar Sarefat'a kadar uzanan toprakları, Sefarat'taki Yeruşalimli sürgünler de Negev'deki kentleri mülk edinecekler. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						وسبي هذا الجيش من بني اسرائيل يرثون الذين هم من الكنعانيين الى صرفة. وسبي اورشليم الذين في صفارد يرثون مدن الجنوب.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Os cativos deste exército dos filhos de Israel possuirão os cananeus até Zarefate; e os cativos de Jerusalém, que estão em Sefarade, possuirão as cidades do Negebe.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et transmigratio exercitus huius filiorum Israhel omnia Chananeorum usque ad Saraptham et transmigratio Hierusalem quae in Bosforo est possidebit civitates austri</lang><lang id="Greek">
						και το αιχμαλωτισθεν τουτο στρατευμα των υιων Ισραηλ την γην εκεινην των Χαναναιων εως Σαρεπτα, και οι αιχμαλωτισθεντες της Ιερουσαλημ, οι εν Σεφαραδ, θελουσι κατακληρονομησει τας πολεις του νοτου
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Die ballinge van hierdie leërmag van die kinders van Israel sal die wat Kanaäniete is, tot by Sarfat verower; en die ballinge van Jerusalem, wat in Sefárad is, sal die stede van die Suidland in besit neem.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Nan moun yo te depòte yo, sòlda ki moun nan nò peyi Izrayèl la va pran peyi Kanaran an pou yo, rive lavil Sarepta. Men, moun lavil Jerizalèm yo te depòte nan peyi Sefara a va pran tout lavil Negèv yo pou yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Những kẻ phu tù của cơ binh con_cái Y-sơ-ra-ên ở giữa những người Ca-na-an , sẽ được đất nó cho_đến Sa-rép-ta . Những phu tù của Giê-ru-sa-lem ở tại Sê-pha-rát sẽ được các thành phương nam .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						וגלת החל הזה לבני ישראל אשר כנענים עד צרפת וגלת ירושלם אשר בספרד ירשו את ערי הנגב׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">The captives of this army of the children of Israel, who are among the Canaanites, will possess even to Zarephath; and the captives of Jerusalem, who are in Sepharad, will possess the cities of the Negev.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మరియు ఇశ్రాయేలీయుల దండు, అనగా వారిలో చెర పట్టబడినవారు సారెపతువరకు కనానీయుల దేశమును స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు; యెరూషలేమువారిలో చెరపట్ట బడి సెఫారాదునకు పోయినవారు దక్షిణదేశపు పట్టణ ములను స్వతంత్రించుకొందురు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						И тая пленена войска на Израиляните Ще владее земята на Ханаанците до Сарепта; И пленените Ерусалимци, които са в Сефарад, Ще владеят южните градове;
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kateri pa so bili v sužnost odpeljani iz tega krdela sinov Izraelovih, posedejo, kar je last Kanaancev tja do Sarepte; in odpeljanci v sužnost iz Jeruzalema, ki so v Sefaradu, posedejo mesta na Jugu.In rešitelji pojdejo na goro Sion, da sodijo goro Ezavovo. Kraljestvo pa bode GOSPODOVO.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و اسیران این لشکر بنی‌اسرائیل ملک کنعانیان راتا صرفه به تصرف خواهند‌آورد و اسیران اورشلیم که در صفارد هستند شهرهای جنوب را به تصرف خواهند‌آورد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Og de landflygtige i Hala og Habor skal tage Kana'anæernes Land i Eje indtil Zarepta, og de landflygtige fra Jerusalem, som er i Sefarad, skal tage Sydlandets Byer i Eje.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Ja tästä väestä, israelilaisista, viedyt pakkosiirtolaiset ottavat  perinnöksensä kanaanilaiset Sarpatiin asti. Ja Jerusalemin  pakkosiirtolaiset, jotka ovat Sefaradissa, ottavat perinnöksensä  Etelämaan kaupungit.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						在 迦南人 中 被 擄 的 以色列 眾人 、 必得 地直 到 撒勒法 ． 在 西 法拉 中 被擄 的 耶路撒冷 人 、 必得 南地 的 城邑
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Israyla* izey marga kaŋ koy tamtaray ga Kanaanancey ŋwa hala Zarefat, Urusalima waney mo kaŋ koy tamtaray, Ngey kaŋ yaŋ go Sefarad ra, I ga Negeb birney ŋwa. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						在 迦 南 人 中 被 擄 的 以 色 列 眾 人 、 必 得 地 直 到 撒 勒 法 ． 在 西 法 拉 中 被 擄 的 耶 路 撒 冷 人 、 必 得 南 地 的 城 邑 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						इस्राएलियों के उस दल में से जो लाग बंधुआई में जाकर कनानियों के बीच सारपत तक रहते हैं, और यरूशलेमियों में से जो लोग बंधुआई में जाकर सपारद में रहते हैं, वे सब दक्खिन देश के नगरों के अधिकारी हो जाएंगे।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						I zajaté vojsko toto synů Izraelských v tom, což bylo Kananejských až do Sarepty, zajatí pak Jeruzalémští v tom, což jest na konci panství, děditi budou s městy na poledne.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj tiu multo da forkondukitaj Izraelidoj en la lando Kanaana gxis Carfat kaj la forkondukitaj el Jerusalem en Sefarad ekposedos la urbojn sudajn.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Mërgimtarët e kësaj ushtrie të bijve të Izraelit që ndodhen midis Kananeasve, do të zotërojnë vendin deri në Sarepta, mërgimtarët e Jeruzalemit që ndodhen në Sefarad do të zotërojnë qytetet e Negevit.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Gli esuli di questo esercito degli Israeliti occuperanno Canaan fino a Sarèfta e gli esuli di Gerusalemme, che sono in Sefaràd, occuperanno le città del Negheb
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þeir af Ísraelsmönnum, er teknir hafa verið í vígi þessu og fluttir burt hernumdir, munu taka það til eignar, sem Kanaanítar eiga, allt til Sarefta, og þeir sem fluttir hafa verið burt hernumdir frá Jerúsalem, þeir sem eru í Sefarad, munu taka til eignar borgir Suðurlandsins. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						इस्राएलच्या लोकांना त्यांची घरे बळजबरीने सोडावी लागली, पण ते सारफथ पर्यंतचा कनानचा प्रदेश घेतील यहूदाच्या लोकांना बळजबरीने यरुशलेम सोडावे लागले व ते सफारदमध्ये राहतात. पण ते नेगेवची गावे घेतील.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						ハラにいるイスラエルの人々の捕われ人は、フェニキヤをザレパテまで取り、セパラデにいるエルサレムの捕われ人は、ネゲブの町々を獲る。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Esta tropa de cautivos de los hijos de Israel poseerá lo que fuera de los cananeos hasta Sarepta, y los de Jerusalén que están cautivos en Sefarad poseerán las ciudades del Néguev
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo ciidankan dadka Israa'iil ee maxaabiista ahu waxay hantiyi doonaan dalka reer Kancaan tan iyo Sarefta, oo Yeruusaalem maxaabiisteeda Sefaaraad joogtaana waxay hantiyi doonaan magaalooyinka koonfureed.Oo badbaadiyayaaluna waa iman doonaan Buur Siyoon, si ay buurta Ceesaw u xukumaan, oo boqortooyadana waxaa lahaan doona Rabbiga.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Kanaan mite laka hiai Isreal suan saltang mipiten Zarephath gam tna in a tan ding ua: Sephrad gama Jerusalem kho mite saltangin Sim lam khopite a tang ding uh.Zion tangah esau tang vaihawm sak dinga honkhemmite a hongkuan tou ding ua; huan, gam TOUPA a ahi ding.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇದಲ್ಲದೆ ಚಾರೆಪತಿನ ವರೆಗೂ ಕಾನಾನ್ಯರಲ್ಲಿರುವ ಇಸ್ರಾಯೇಲನ ಮಕ್ಕಳ ಈ ಸೈನ್ಯದ ಸೆರೆಯವರು ಸೆಫರಾದಿನಲ್ಲಿರುವ ಯೆರೂ ಸಲೇಮಿನ ಸೆರೆಯವರು ದಕ್ಷಿಣದ ಪಟ್ಟಣಗಳನ್ನು ಸ್ವಾಧೀ ನಮಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವರು.ಇದಲ್ಲದೆ ಚೀಯೋನ್‌ ಪರ್ವತದಲ್ಲಿ ರಕ್ಷಕರು ಏಸಾವಿನ ಬೆಟ್ಟಕ್ಕೆ ನ್ಯಾಯ ತೀರಿಸುವದಕ್ಕೋಸ್ಕರ ಏಳುವರು; ಆಗ ರಾಜ್ಯವು ಕರ್ತನದಾಗಿರುವದು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And the captivity of this host of the children of Israel shall possess that of the Canaanites, even unto Zarephath; and the captivity of Jerusalem, which is in Sepharad, shall possess the cities of the south.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">De Israëlitische ballingen zullen terugkeren naar het land van de Kanaänieten tot Sarfath in het noorden bezetten. En de mensen uit Jeruzalem, die in ballingschap waren in Sefarad in Klein-Azië, zullen terugkeren naar hun vaderland en de steden aan de rand van de Negeb veroveren.</lang><lang id="Croatian">A izgnana nekoć vojska sinova Izraelovih baštinit će Kanaan sve do Sarfate; izgnanici jeruzalemski što su u Sefaradu baštinit će gradove negepske.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A zaprowadzeni w niewolę tego wojska synów Izraelskich posiędą to, co było Chananejczyków aż do Sarepty; a zaprowadzeni w niewolę Jeruzalemczyków posiędą to, co jest na koócu paóstwa, posiędą z miastami na południe.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">พลโยธาของอิสราเอลที่เป็นเชลยจะได้ที่ซึ่งเป็นของคนคานาอันไกลไปจนถึงศาเรฟัทเป็นกรรมสิทธิ์ ส่วนพวกเชลยชาวเยรูซาเล็มที่อยู่ในเสฟาราดจะได้หัวเมืองในภาคใต้เป็นกรรมสิทธิ์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang mga bihag sa hukbong ito ng mga anak ni Israel na nasa mga taga Canaan, ay magaari ng hanggang sa Sarefat; at ang mga bihag sa Jerusalem na nasa Sepharad ay magaari ng mga bayan ng Timugan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 ハラ に い る イスラエル の 人々 の 捕 われ 人 は 、 フェニキヤ を ザレパテ まで 取 り 、 セパラデ に い る エルサレム の 捕われ 人 は 、 ネゲブ の 町々 を 獲 る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഈ കോട്ടയില്‍നിന്നു പ്രവാസികളായി പോയ യിസ്രായേല്‍മക്കള്‍ സാരെഫാത്ത്വരെ കനാന്യര്‍ക്കുംള്ളതും സെഫാരദിലുള്ള യെരൂശലേമ്യപ്രവാസികള്‍ തെക്കെദേശത്തെ പട്ടണങ്ങളും കൈവശമാക്കും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Dar prinşii de război ai acestei oştiri a copiilor lui Israel, vor stăpîni ţara Cananiţilor pînă la Sarepta, şi prinşii de război ai Ierusalimului, cari sînt la Sefarad, vor stăpîni cetăţile de miază-zi.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und die Vertriebenen dieses Heeres der Kinder Israel, so unter den Kanaanitern bis gen Zarpath sind, und die Vertriebenen der Stadt Jerusalem, die zu Sepharad sind, werden die Städte gegen Mittag besitzen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Och de bortförda av denna Israels barns här, de som bo i Kanaan allt intill Sarefat, så ock de bortförda från Jerusalem, de som leva i Sefarad, dessa skola taga Sydlandets städer i besittning.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">พล โยธา ของ อิส รา เอลที่เป็น เชลย จะ ได้ที่ ซึ่ง เป็น ของ คน คา นา อัน ไกล ไป จนถึง ศาเร ฟัทเป็น กรรมสิทธิ์ ส่วน พวก เชลย ชาว เยรูซา เล็ม ที่ อยู่ ใน เส ฟาราด จะ ได้ หัวเมือง ใน ภาค ใต้ เป็น กรรมสิทธิ์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						20
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.OBA.1.21" langNo="58"><lang id="Maori">
						A ka tae ake he kaiwhakaora ki Maunga Hiona hei whakawa mo te maunga o Ehau; a ka riro i a Ihowa te kingitanga
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Sẽ có các kẻ giải cứu lên trên núi Si-ôn đặng phán xét núi Ê-sau; còn nước thì sẽ thuộc về Ðức Giê-hô-va.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Des libérateurs monteront sur la montagne de Sion, Pour juger la montagne d`Ésaü; Et à l`Éternel appartiendra le règne.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary hisy mpamonjy miakatra ho ao an-tendrombohitra Ziona Hitsara ny tendrombohitr'i Esao; Ary ho an'i Jehovah Jon 1:1
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						És a Sion hegyére szabadítók mennek fel, hogy megítéljék az Ézsau hegyét; és az Úré lesz  a királyság.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Konyuka abasindisi entabeni yeZiyon, ukuze bazigwebe iintaba zakwaEsawu, ubukumkani bube bobu kaYehova.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">구원자들이 시온산에 올라와서 에서의 산을 심판하리니 나라가 여호와께 속하리라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Išgelbėtojai ateis į Siono kalną teisti Ezavo kalno. Ir Viešpačiui priklausys karalystė”.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						И придут спасители на гору Сион, чтобы судить гору Исава, и будет царство Господа.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Penduduk Yerusalem yang jaya akan menyerang Edom dan menaklukkannya. Maka Aku TUHAN akan memerintah sebagai raja.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano"></lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ဧသော၏တောင်ကို တရားစီရင်ခြင်းငှါ ကယ် တင်သောသူတို့သည် ဇိအုန်တောင်ပေါ်သို့ တက်ကြလိမ့် မည်။ တိုင်းနိုင်ငံသည်လည်း ထာဝရဘုရား၏ နိုင်ငံတော် ဖြစ်လိမ့်သတည်း။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ut eb laj Israel li queßnumta saß xbêneb laj Edom teßxic saß li tzûl Sión chi taklânc saß xbêneb li cuanqueb saß xyânkeb li tzûl saß lix chßochß laj Esaú. Ut li Kâcuaß, aßan tâcuânk xcuanquil saß xbêneb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A tak vyjdú záchrancovia na vrch Sion, aby súdili vrch Ezavov, a kráľovstvo bude Hospodinovo.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						विजयीहरू सियोन पर्वतमा हुनेछन्। ती मानिसहरूले एसाव पर्वतका बासिन्दाहरूमाथि शासन गर्नेछन् र राज्य परमप्रभुको हुनेछ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I izbavitelji će izaći na goru Sion da sude gori Isavovoj, i carstvo će biti Gospodnje.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Og frelsere skal dra op på Sions berg og dømme Esaus berg, og riket skal høre Herren til. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
	                    Halkı kurtaranlar Esav'ın dağlarını yönetimleri altına almak için Siyon Dağı'na çıkacaklar ve egemenlik RAB'bin olacak. 
                    </lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ويصعد مخلّصون على جبل صهيون ليدينوا جبل عيسو ويكون الملك للرب
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Subirão salvadores ao monte de Sião para julgarem o monte de Esaú; e o reino será do Senhor.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et ascendent salvatores in montem Sion iudicare montem Esau et erit Domino regnum</lang><lang id="Greek">
						και θελουσιν αναβη σωτηρες εις το ορος Σιων, δια να κρινωσι το ορος του Ησαυ και του Κυριου θελει εισθαι η βασιλεια.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Dan sal daar verlossers die berg Sion opgaan om die gebergte van Esau te oordeel, en die koninkryk sal aan die HERE toebehoort.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Yo tout, y'a moute sou mòn Siyon an pou delivre l'. Se yo ki va gouvènen tout mòn Ezaou a. Lè sa a, se Seyè a menm ki va sèl wa
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Sẽ có các kẻ giải_cứu lên trên núi Si-ôn đặng phán_xét núi Ê - sau ; còn nước thì sẽ thuộc về Ðức_Giê - hô-va .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ועלו מושעים בהר ציון לשפט את הר עשו והיתה ליהוה המלוכה׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Saviors will go up on Mount Zion to judge the mountains of Esau, and the kingdom will be Yahweh's.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మరియు ఏశావుయొక్క కొండకు తీర్పుతీర్చుటకై సీయోను కొండమీద రక్షకులు పుట్టుదురు; అప్పుడు రాజ్యము యెహోవాది యగును.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						И избавители ще възлязат в хълма Сион, За да съдят Исавовия хълм; И царството ще бъде на Господа.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In rešitelji pojdejo na goro Sion, da sodijo goro Ezavovo. Kraljestvo pa bode GOSPODOVO.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi"></lang><lang id="Danish">
						Da drager Redningsmænd fra Zions Bjerg op for at holde Dom over Esaus Bjerge. Og så skal Riget være HERRENs.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish"></lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						必有 拯救者 上到 錫安山 、 審判 以 掃山 ． 國度 就 歸 耶和華 了
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Faabakoyaŋ ga kaaru Sihiyona tondo boŋ zama ngey ma Isuwa tondo ciiti. Mayra mo ga ye ka ciya Rabbi wane. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						必 有 拯 救 者 上 到 錫 安 山 、 審 判 以 掃 山 ． 國 度 就 歸 耶 和 華 了 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						और उद्धार करनेवाले एसाव के पहाड़ का न्याय करने के लिये सिरयोन पर्वत पर चढ़ आएंगे, और राज्य यहोवा ही का हो जाएगा।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						I vstoupí vysvoboditelé na horu Sion, aby soudili horu Ezau, a tak bude Hospodinovo království.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj venos savantoj sur la monton Cion, por jugxi la monton de Esav. Kaj la regado apartenos al la Eternulo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Atëherë disa çlirimtarë do të ngjiten në malin e Sionit për të gjykuar malin e Esaut, dhe mbretëria do të jetë e Zotit.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Saliranno vittoriosi sul monte Sion per governare il monte di Esaù e il regno sarà del Signore
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Og frelsendur munu fara upp til Síonfjalls til þess að dæma Esaúfjöll, og Drottinn mun hljóta konungsvaldið. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						विजेते सियोन पर्वतावर जातील, एसाव पर्वतावर राहणाऱ्या लोकांवर ते राज्य करतील. आणि राज्य परमेश्वराच्या मालकीचे होईल.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						こうして救う者はシオンの山に上って、エサウの山を治める。そして王国は主のものとなる。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Subirán victoriosos desde el monte Sion para juzgar la región montañosa de Esaú. ¡Y el reino será de Jehovah
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo badbaadiyayaaluna waa iman doonaan Buur Siyoon, si ay buurta Ceesaw u xukumaan, oo boqortooyadana waxaa lahaan doona Rabbiga.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Zion tangah esau tang vaihawm sak dinga honkhemmite a hongkuan tou ding ua; huan, gam TOUPA a ahi ding.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇದಲ್ಲದೆ ಚೀಯೋನ್‌ ಪರ್ವತದಲ್ಲಿ ರಕ್ಷಕರು ಏಸಾವಿನ ಬೆಟ್ಟಕ್ಕೆ ನ್ಯಾಯ ತೀರಿಸುವದಕ್ಕೋಸ್ಕರ ಏಳುವರು; ಆಗ ರಾಜ್ಯವು ಕರ್ತನದಾಗಿರುವದು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And saviours shall come up on mount Zion to judge the mount of Esau; and the kingdom shall be the LORD's.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Want verlossers zullen naar de berg Sion komen en heersen over heel Edom. En de HERE zal hun koning zijn!"</lang><lang id="Croatian">Izbavitelji će uzaći na goru Sion da sude gori Ezavljevoj. I tada će nastat' kraljevstvo Jahvino.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						I wstąpią wybawiciele na górę Syon, aby sądzili górę Ezawa; a tak będzie królestwo samego Pana.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">พวกผู้ช่วยให้พ้นจะขึ้นไปที่ภูเขาศิโยนเพื่อปกครองภูเขาเอซาว และราชอาณาจักรนั้นจะตกเป็นของพระเยโฮวาห์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang mga tagapagligtas ay magsisisampa sa bundok ng Sion upang hatulan ang bundok ng Esau; at ang kaharian ay magiging sa Panginoon. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
					 	 こう し て 救 う 者 は シオン の 山 に 上 っ て 、 エサウ の 山 を 治め る 。 そして 王国 は 主 の もの と な る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഏശാവിന്റെ പര്‍വ്വതത്തെ ന്യായംവിധിക്കേണ്ടതിന്നു രക്ഷകന്മാര്‍ സീയോന്‍ പര്‍വ്വതത്തില്‍ കയറിച്ചെല്ലും; രാജത്വം യഹോവേക്കു ആകും.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Izbăvitorii se vor sui pe muntele Sionului, ca să judece muntele lui Esau. Dar împărăţia va fi a Domnului.`
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und es werden Heilande heraufkommen auf den Berg Zion, das Gebirge Esau zu richten; und das Königreich wird des HERRN sein.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Och frälsare skola draga upp på Sions berg till att döma Esaus berg.  Och så skall riket vara HERRENS.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">พวก ผู้ ช่วย ให้ พ้น จะ ขึ้น ไป ที่ ภูเขา ศิโยน เพื่อ ปกครอง ภูเขา เอ ซาว และ ราช อาณาจักร นั้น จะ ตกเป็น ของ พระ เยโฮวาห์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						21
					</lang></verse></chapter></book></text>
