<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text><book id="b.JUD" allLangs="no"><chapter id="b.JUD.1"><verse id="b.JUD.1.1" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na Hura, he pononga na Ihu Karaiti, he teina no Hemi, ki te hunga kua oti te whakatapu e te Atua Matua, he mea tiaki i roto i a Ihu Karaiti, he hunga karanga
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Giu-đe, tôi tớ của Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ và em Gia-cơ, đạt cho những kẻ đã được kêu gọi, được Ðức Chúa Trời, là Cha yêu thương, và được Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ giữ gìn:
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Jude, serviteur de Jésus Christ, et frère de Jacques, à ceux qui ont été appelés, qui sont aimés en Dieu le Père, et gardés pour Jésus Christ:
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						[Fananarana ny amin'ny mpampianatra sandoka] Joda, mpanompon'i Jesosy Kristy sady rahalahin'i Jakoba, mamangy izay olona voantso, malala ao amin'Andriamanitra Ray sy voatahiry ho an'i Jesosy Kristy;
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Júdás, Jézus Krisztusnak szolgája, Jakabnak pedig  atyafia, az elhívottaknak a kik az Atya Istentõl megszenteltettek és Jézus Krisztustól megtartattak:
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						UYuda, umkhonzi kaYesu Kristu, umzalwana ke kaYakobi,  ubhalela abangcwalisiweyo bekuThixo uYise, begcinelwe uYesu Kristu, bengababiziweyo:
					</lang><lang id="Korean">예수 그리스도의 종이요 야고보의 형제인 유다는 부르심을 입은 자 곧 하나님 아버지 안에서 사랑을 얻고 예수 그리스도를 위하여 지키심을 입은 자들에게 편지하노라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Judas, Jėzaus Kristaus tarnas, Jokūbo brolis, Dievo Tėvo pašventintiems ir Jėzuje Kristuje išsaugotiems pašauktiesiems:
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Иуда, раб Иисуса Христа, брат Иакова, призванным, которые освящены Богом Отцем и сохранены Иисусом Христом:
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Saudara-saudara yang telah dipanggil dan yang sangat dikasihi oleh Allah Bapa, serta dijaga untuk Yesus Kristus. Sebagai hamba Yesus Kristus, saya--Yudas--saudara dari Yakobus
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Si Judas, ulipon ni Jesu-Cristo ug igsoon ni Santiago,
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ယေရှုခရစ်၏ ကျွန်ဖြစ်သောယာကုပ်ညီ ငါယုဒသည် ခမည်းတော်ဘုရားသခင် သန့်ရှင်းစေတော်မူ၍၊ ယေရှုခရစ် ခေါ်ထားစောင့်မတော်မူသော သူတို့ကို ကြားလိုက်ပါ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Lâin laj Judas, laj c'anjel chiru li Jesucristo. Lâin rîtz'in laj Jacobo. Nintz'îba li hu a'in reheb laj pâbanel, li bokbileb ut rarôqueb xban li Dios Acuabej ut colbileb xban li Jesucristo.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Júda, sluha Ježiša Krista a brat Jakobov, milovaným a posväteným v Bohu Otcovi a Ježišu Kristovi zachovaným povolaným:
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						येशू ख्रीष्टको दास अनि याकूबको एक भाइ, यहूदाबाट। ती सबै मानिसहरु प्रति जो परमेश्वरद्वारा चुनिएकाछन्. पिता परमेश्वरले तिमीहरुलाई प्रेम गर्नुहुन्छ अनि तिमीहरु येशू ख्रीष्टको विश्वासमा सुरक्षित राखिएका छौ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Od Jude, Isusa Hrista sluge, a brata Jakovljevog, zvanima, koji su osvećeni Bogom Ocem i održani Isusom Hristom:</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Judas, Jesu Kristi tjener og Jakobs bror - til de kalte, som er elsket i Gud Fader og bevart for Jesus Kristus: 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						İsa Mesihin kulu, Yakupun kardeşi ben Yahudadan, Baba Tanrı tarafından sevilip İsa Mesih için korunmuş olan çağrılmışlara selam!
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						يهوذا عبد يسوع المسيح واخو يعقوب الى المدعوين المقدسين في الله الآب والمحفوظين ليسوع المسيح
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Judas, servo de Jesus Cristo, e irmão de Tiago, aos chamados, amados em Deus Pai, e guardados em Jesus Cristo:
					</lang><lang id="Latin">Iudas Iesu Christi servus frater autem Iacobi his qui in Deo Patre dilectis et Iesu Christo conservatis vocatis</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ιουδας, δουλος Ιησου Χριστου, αδελφος δε Ιακωβου, προς τους κλητους τους ηγιασμενους υπο Θεου Πατρος, και τετηρημενους υπο του Ιησου Χριστου
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Judas, 'n dienskneg van Jesus Christus en broer van Jakobus, aan die wat geroep, in God die Vader geheilig en vir Jesus Christus bewaar is:
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Mwen menm Jid, sèvitè Jezikri, frè Jak la, m'ap ekri nou lèt sa a, nou tout Bondye rele, nou menm k'ap viv ansanm nan renmen Bondye Papa a ak anba proteksyon Jezikri
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Giu-đe , tôi_tớ của Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ và em Gia-cơ , đạt cho những kẻ đã được kêu_gọi , được Ðức_Chúa_Trời , là Cha yêu_thương , và được Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ giữ_gìn :
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						יהודה עבד ישוע המשיח ואחי יעקב אל המקראים אשר הם מקדשים באלהים האב ושמורים לישוע המשיח׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to those who are called, sanctified by God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ:</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						యేసుక్రీస్తు దాసుడును, యాకోబు సహోదరుడు నైన యూదా, తండ్రియైన దేవునియందు ప్రేమింపబడి, యేసుక్రీస్తునందు భద్రము చేయబడి పిలువబడినవారికి శుభమని చెప్పి వ్రాయునది.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Горко им! защото ходят по Каиновия път, заради печалба се впускат във Валаамовата заблуда, и погиват в Кореевото упорство.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Juda, Jezusa Kristusa hlapec, a brat Jakobov, poklicanim, v Bogu Očetu ljubljenim in za Jezusa Kristusa hranjenim:
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						یهودا، غلام عیسی مسیح و برادر یعقوب، به خوانده‌شدگانی که در خدای پدر حبیب وبرای عیسی مسیح محفوظ می‌باشید.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Judas, Jesu Kriti Tjener og Broder til Jakob, til de kaldede, som ere elskede i Gud Fader og bevarede for Jesus Kristus:
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Juudas, Jeesuksen Kristuksen palvelija ja Jaakobin veli, kutsutuille, jotka ovat Isässä Jumalassa rakastetut ja Jeesukselle Kristukselle varjellut.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						耶穌基督 的 僕人 、 雅各 的 弟兄 猶大 、 寫信給 那 被召 、 在 父 神裡蒙愛 、 為 耶穌基督 保守 的 人
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ay, Yahuda, ay ya Yesu Almasihu bannya nda Yakuba nya ize mo no. Ay go ga tiro wo hantum borey kaŋ Irikoy ce se, kaŋ yaŋ goono ga goro Baaba Irikoy baakasina ra, kaŋ yaŋ Irikoy go ga hallasi mo Yesu Almasihu se. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						耶 穌 基 督 的 僕 人 、 雅 各 的 弟 兄 猶 大 、 寫 信 給 那 被 召 、 在 父 　 神 裡 蒙 愛 、 為 耶 穌 基 督 保 守 的 人 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						यहूदा की ओर से जो यीशु मसीह का दास और याकूब का भाई है, उन बुलाए हुओं के नाम जो परमेश्वर पिता में प्रिय और यीशु मसीह के लिये सुरक्षित हैं।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Judas, Ježíše Krista služebník, bratr pak Jakubův, posvěceným v Bohu Otci, a Kristu Ježíši zachovaným a k němu povolaným:
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Judas, servisto de Jesuo Kristo kaj frato de Jakobo, al la alvokitoj,  amataj en Dio, la Patro, kaj konservitaj por Jesuo Kristo:
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						mëshira, paqja dhe dashuria u shumoftë në ju.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Giuda, servo di Gesù Cristo, fratello di Giacomo, agli eletti che vivono nell'amore di Dio Padre e sono stati preservati per Gesù Cristo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Júdas, þjónn Jesú Krists, bróðir Jakobs, heilsar hinum kölluðu, sem eru elskaðir af Guði föður og varðveittir Jesú Kristi. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						येशू ख्रिस्ताचा सेवक आणि याकोबाचा भाऊ असलेल्या यहूदाकडून, देवाने ज्या तुम्हांला पाचारण केले आहे त्यांस, देवपिता तुमच्यावर प्रीती करतो व येशू ख्रिस्ताद्वारे तुम्ही सुरक्षित ठेवले जात आहात.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						イエス・キリストの僕またヤコブの兄弟であるユダから、父なる神に愛され、イエス・キリストに守られている召された人々へ。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Judas, siervo de Jesucristo y hermano de Santiago; a los llamados, amados en Dios Padre y guardados en Jesucristo
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Anigoo Yuudas ah oo ah addoonkii Ciise Masiix, Yacquubna walaalkiis ah, waxaan warqaddan u qorayaa kuwa loo yeedhay oo Ilaaha Aabbaha ahu jecel yahay, Ciise Masiixna loo dhawray.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Juda, Jesu Kris sikha leh Jakob unauin, Pa Pathiana deihtak, Jesu Kris adinga sit, sapte kiangah:
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಯೇಸು ಕ್ರಿಸ್ತನ ದಾಸನೂ ಯಾಕೋಬನ ಸಹೋ ದರನೂ ಆಗಿರುವ ಯೂದನು ತಂದೆಯಾದ ದೇವ ರಿಂದ ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧರಾದವರಿಗೂ ಯೇಸು ಕ್ರಿಸ್ತನಲ್ಲಿ ಕಾಪಾಡಲ್ಪಟ್ಟವರಿಗೂ ಕರೆಯಲ್ಪಟ್ಟವರಿಗೂ--
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Jude, the servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to them that are sanctified by God the Father, and preserved in Jesus Christ, and called:
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Van: Judas, een dienaar van Jezus Christus en een broer van Jakobus. Aan: Alle mensen die door God, de Vader, geroepen zijn. Hij houdt van u en Zijn Zoon Jezus Christus bewaart u.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Juda, sluga Isusa Krista, brat Jakovljev: ljubljenima u Bogu, Ocu, čuvanima za Isusa Krista - pozvanima.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Judas, sługa Jezusa Chrystusa a brat Jakóba, od Boga Ojca poświęconym i w Jezusie Chrystusie zachowanym i powołanym:
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ยูดาส ผู้รับใช้ของพระเยซูคริสต์ และเป็นน้องชายของยากอบ เรียน คนทั้งหลายที่ทรงชำระตั้งไว้ให้บริสุทธิ์โดยพระเจ้าพระบิดา และที่ทรงคุ้มครองรักษาไว้ในพระเยซูคริสต์ และที่ทรงเรียกไว้แล้ว</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Si Judas, na alipin ni Jesucristo, at kapatid ni Santiago, sa mga tinawag, na minamahal sa Dios Ama, at iniingatang para kay Jesucristo: 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 イエス ・ キリスト の 僕 また ヤコブ の 兄弟 で あ る ユダ から 、 父 な る 神 に 愛 さ れ 、 イエス ・ キリスト に 守 ら れ て い る 召 さ れ た 人々 へ 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						യേശുക്രിസ്തുവിന്റെ ദാസനും യാക്കോബിന്റെ സഹോദരനുമായ യൂദാ, പിതാവായ ദൈവത്തില്‍ സ്നേഹിക്കപ്പെട്ടും യേശുക്രിസ്തുവിന്നായി സൂക്ഷിക്കപ്പെട്ടും ഇരിക്കുന്നവരായ വിളിക്കപ്പെട്ടവര്‍ക്കും എഴുതുന്നതു
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Iuda, rob al lui Isus Hristos, şi fratele lui Iacov, către cei chemaţi, cari sînt iubiţi în Dumnezeu Tatăl, şi păstraţi pentru Isus Hristos:
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Judas, ein Knecht Jesu Christi, ein Bruder aber des Jakobus, den Berufenen, die da geheiligt sind in Gott, dem Vater, und bewahrt in Jesu Christo:
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Judas, Jesu Kristi tjänare och Jakobs broder, hälsar de kallade, dem som äro upptagna i Guds, Faderns, kärlek och bevarade åt Jesus Kristus.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ยู ดา ส ผู้ รับ ใช้ ของ พระ เยซู คริสต์ และ เป็น น้อง ชาย ของ ยาก อบ เรียน คน ทั้งหลาย ที่ ทรง ชำระ ตั้ง ไว้ ให้ บริสุทธิ์ โดย พระเจ้า พระ บิดา และ ที่ ทรง คุ้มครอง รักษา ไว้ ใน พระ เยซู คริสต์ และ ที่ ทรง เรียก ไว้ แล้ว</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Juudas, Jeesuse Kristuse sulane, Jakoobuse vend, Jumalas Isas armastatud ja Jeesuses Kristuses hoitud kutsutuile.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.2" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Kia whakanuia ki a koutou te mahi tohu, te rangimarie me te aroha
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						nguyền xin sự thương xót, bình an, yêu mến thêm lên cho anh em!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						que la miséricorde, la paix et la charité vous soient multipliées!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						hampitomboina ho anareo anie ny famindram-po sy ny fiadanana ary ny fitiavana.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Irgalmasság, békesség és szeretet adassék néktek bõségesen.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						uthi, Makwandiswe kuni inceba noxolo nothando.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">긍휼과 평강과 사랑이 너희에게 더욱 많을찌어다</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						tepadaugėja jums gailestingumas, ramybė ir meilė!
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						милость вам и мир и любовь да умножатся.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						mengharap: Semoga Allah memberi berkat, rahmat dan sejahtera kepadamu dengan berlimpah-limpah
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Hinaut nga ang kalooy, kalinaw, ug gugma padagayaon unta kaninyo.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သင်တို့၌ကရုဏာရှိပါစေသော။ ငြိမ်သက်ခြင်း နှင့်ချစ်ခြင်းများ ပြားပါစေသော။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Chec'ulak taxak chi nabal li ruxtân li Dios, jo' ajcui' li tuktûquil usilal ut li rahoc.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						milosrdenstvo vám i pokoj i láska nech sa rozmnoží!
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						सम्पूर्ण कृपा, शान्ति अनि प्रेम तिमीहरुमा रहोस्। खराब काम गर्ने मानिसहरुलाई परमेश्वरले दण्ड दिनु हुनेछ
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Milost i mir i ljubav da vam se umnoži.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Miskunn og fred og kjærlighet bli eder mangfoldig til del! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Merhamet, esenlik ve sevgi artan ölçüde sizin olsun.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						لتكثر لكم الرحمة والسلام والمحبة
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Misericórdia, paz e amor vos sejam multiplicados.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">misericordia vobis et pax et caritas adimpleatur</lang><lang id="Greek">
						ελεος πληθυνθειη εις εσας και ειρηνη και αγαπη.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Mag barmhartigheid en vrede en liefde vir julle vermenigvuldig word!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Mwen mande pou li gen pitye pou nou, pou li ban nou kè poze ak renmen an kantite
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						nguyền xin sự thương_xót , bình_an , yêu_mến thêm lên cho anh_em !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						רחמים ושלום ואהבה יהיו לכם למכביר׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Mercy to you and peace and love be multiplied.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మీకు కనికరమును సమాధానమును ప్రేమయు విస్తరించును గాక.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Тия са подводни скали, когато пируват с вас в дружелюбните ви гощавки, и без страх напасват себе си; безводни облаци, носени от ветровете; есенни дървета, безплодни, дваж умрели, изкоренени;
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Usmiljenje vam in mir in ljubezen naj se pomnoži!
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						رحمت و سلامتی و محبت بر شما افزون باد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Barmhjertighed og Fred og Kærlighed vorde eder mangfoldig til Del!
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Lisääntyköön teille laupeus ja rauha ja rakkaus.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						願憐恤 、 平安 、 慈愛 、 多多 的 加給 你 們
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Suuji nda laakal kanay da baakasinay ma tonton araŋ gaa. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						願 憐 恤 、 平 安 、 慈 愛 、 多 多 的 加 給 你 們 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						दया और शान्ति और प्रेम तुम्हें बहुतायत से प्राप्त होता रहे।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Milosrdenství vám a pokoj i láska budiž rozmnožena.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kompato al vi kaj paco kaj amo pligrandigxu.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Shumë të dashur, ndërsa isha ngulmues që t'ju shkruaja për shpëtimin e përbashkët, ndjeva nevojën t'ju shkruaj juve, dhe t'ju bëj thirrje të luftoni për besimin, që u qe trasmetuar shenjtorëve një herë e përgjithmonë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						misericordia a voi e pace e carità in abbondanza
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Miskunn, friður og kærleiki margfaldist yður til handa. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						देवाची करुणा, शांति आणि प्रीती तुम्हांला अधिकाधिक लाभो.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あわれみと平安と愛とが、あなたがたに豊かに加わるように。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Misericordia, paz y amor os sean multiplicados
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Naxariis iyo nabad iyo jacayl ha idiin bateen.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Hehpihnate, lemnate, itnate na tunguah hihkhanin om hen.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನಿಮಗೆ ಕರುಣೆಯೂ ಶಾಂತಿಯೂ ಪ್ರೀತಿಯೂ ಹೆಚ್ಚಾಗಲಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Mercy unto you, and peace, and love, be multiplied.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Ik wens u meer en meer Gods genade, vrede en liefde toe.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Obilovali milošću, mirom i ljubavlju!</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Miłosierdzie i pokój, i miłość niech się wam rozmnoży.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ขอพระเมตตาคุณ สันติสุข และความรักจงเพิ่มทวียิ่งขึ้นแก่ท่านทั้งหลายเถิด</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Kaawaan at kapayapaan at pagibig ang sa inyo nawa'y paramihin. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あわれみ と 平安 と 愛 と が 、 あなた がた に 豊か に 加わ る よう に 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിങ്ങള്‍ക്കു കരുണയും സമാധാനവും സ്നേഹവും വര്‍ദ്ധിക്കുമാറാകട്ടെ.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						îndurarea, pacea şi dragostea să vă fie înmulţite.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Gott gebe euch viel Barmherzigkeit und Frieden und Liebe!
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Barmhärtighet och frid och kärlek föröke sig hos eder.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ขอ พระ เมตตา คุณ สันติ สุข และ ความ รัก จง เพิ่ม ทวี ยิ่ง ขึ้น แก่ ท่าน ทั้งหลาย เถิด</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Halastust ja rahu ja armastust lisatagu teile rohkesti!
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.3" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						E nga hoa aroha, i ahau e takare tonu ana ki te tuhituhi ki a koutou mo to tatou whakaoranga tahi, i mea ahau me tuhituhi ki a koutou, me whakahauhau kia kaha te tohe ki te whakapono kua oti nei te tuku mai ki te hunga tapu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Hỡi kẻ rất yêu dấu, vì tôi đã ân cần viết cho anh em về sự cứu rỗi chung của chúng ta, tôi tưởng phải làm điều đó, để khuyên anh em vì đạo mà tranh chiến, là đạo đã truyền cho các thánh một lần đủ rồi.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Bien aimés, comme je désirais vivement vous écrire au sujet de notre salut commun, je me suis senti obligé de le faire afin de vous exhorter à combattre pour la foi qui a été transmise aux saints une fois pour toutes.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ry malala, raha manao izay zotom-po rehetra hanoratra aminareo aho hilaza ny amin'ny famonjena iombonantsika, dia nisy nahatery ahy hanoratra aminareo, hananatra mba hiezahanareo mafy hiaro ny finoana izay efa voatolotra indray mandeha monja ho an'ny olona masina.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Szeretteim, mivelhogy minden igyekezettel azon vagyok, hogy írjak néktek a közös üdvösség felõl, kénytelen voltam, hogy intõleg írjak néktek, hogy tusakodjatok a  hitért, a mely egyszer a szenteknek adatott.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Zintanda, ndikukhuthalele ngenyameko yonke nje ukunibhalela ngalo usindiso esidlelana ngalo, kwafuneka ukuba ndinibhalele,  ndinivuselele, ukuba niluzamele ukholo abalunikelwayo kwakanye abangcwele.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">사랑하는 자들아 내가 우리의 일반으로 얻은 구원을 들어 너희에게 편지하려는 뜻이 간절하던 차에 성도에게 단번에 주신 믿음의 도를 위하여 힘써 싸우라는 편지로 너희를 권하여야 할 필요를 느꼈노니</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Mylimieji, labai norėjau parašyti jums apie bendrąjį mūsų išgelbėjimą ir jaučiu reikalą rašyti jums raginimą, kad narsiai kovotumėte už tikėjimą, vieną kartą visiems laikams duotą šventiesiems.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Возлюбленные! имея все усердие писать вам об общем спасении, я почел за нужное написать вам увещание – подвизаться за веру, однажды преданную святым.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Saudara-saudara yang tercinta! Saya sungguh-sungguh bermaksud menulis surat kepadamu mengenai keselamatan yang kita sama-sama sudah alami. Tetapi sekarang saya merasa terdorong untuk menasihati kalian dengan surat ini supaya kalian terus berjuang untuk iman yang sudah satu kali diberikan Allah untuk selama-lamanya kepada umat-Nya
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Mga hinigugma, sa nagasulat ako kaninyo sa dakung kaikag mahitungod sa kaluwasan nga atong tanan, naaghat ako sa pagsulat sa pagtambag kaninyo nga makigbisug kamo sa pagpanalipod sa tinoohan nga sa makausa ra ug sa dayon gitugyan ngadto sa mga balaan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ချစ်သူတို့၊ အညီအမျှဆက်ဆံသော ကယ်တင်ခြင်းအကြောင်းအရာကို သင်တို့ထံသို့ရေး၍ ပေးလိုက် ခြင်းငှါ ငါသည်အလွန်ကြိုးစားသည်တွင်၊ သန့်ရှင်းသူတို့၌ အထက်ကအပ်ပေးခဲ့ပြီးသော ယုံကြည်ခြင်း တရား ဘက်မှာ သင်တို့သည် ကြိုးစား၍တိုက်လှန်စေခြင်းငှါ နှိုးဆော်သွေးဆောင်၍ ရေးလိုက်ရသောအကြောင်းရှိ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ex inhermân, anchal inch'ôl nak yôquin chixc'oxlanquil tz'îbac êriq'uin chirix li kacolbal sa' comonil. Aban xinq'ue retal nak tâajmânk ru nak tintz'îbak êriq'uin re xtz'âmanquil chêru nak têyal êk'e chixcolbal rix lê pâbâl. A'an li junaj chi pâbâl k'axtesinbil chak ke xban li Dios.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Milovaní, snažiac sa, jako len môžem, písať vám o našom spoločnom spasení prinútený som vám napísať a napomenúť vás, aby ste zápasili za vieru, raz ta danú svätým.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						प्रिय मित्रहरु, म तिमीहरुलाई हामी सबैले एकसाथ सहभागी भएको उद्धारको बारेमा लेख्न खूबै इच्छुक भएको छु। म तिमीहरुलाई परमेश्वरले उहाँको पवित्र मानिसहरुलाई प्रदान गर्नु भएको विश्वासको निम्ति कठिन संर्घष गर्ने उत्साह प्रदान गर्ने इच्छा गर्छु। परमेश्वरले यो विश्वास एकै पल्ट प्रदान गर्नुभयो अनि यो सबै समयको निम्ति पर्याप्त भयो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ljubazni! Starajući se jednako da vam pišem za opšte vaše spasenje, bi mi potrebno da vam pišem moleći da se borite za pravednu veru, koja je jedanput dana svetima.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						I elskede! mens jeg gjorde mig all flid for å skrive til eder om vår felles frelse, så jeg mig nødt til å skrive til eder med formaning om å stride for den tro som én gang er overgitt til de hellige. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Sevgili kardeşlerim, size ortak kurtuluşumuzla ilgili yazmaya çok gayret ettim. Bu arada sizi kutsallara ilk ve son kez emanet edilen iman uğrunda mücadeleye özendirmek için yazma gereğini duydum.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ايها الاحباء اذ كنت اصنع كل الجهد لاكتب اليكم عن الخلاص المشترك اضطررت ان اكتب اليكم واعظا ان تجتهدوا لاجل الايمان المسلّم مرة للقديسين.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Amados, enquanto eu empregava toda a diligência para escrever-vos acerca da salvação que nos é comum, senti a necessidade de vos escrever, exortando-vos a pelejar pela fé que de uma vez para sempre foi entregue aos santos.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">carissimi omnem sollicitudinem faciens scribendi vobis de communi vestra salute necesse habui scribere vobis deprecans supercertari semel traditae sanctis fidei</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Αγαπητοι, επειδη καταβαλλω πασαν σπουδην να σας γραφω περι της κοινης σωτηριας, ελαβον αναγκην να σας γραψω, προτρεπων εις το να αγωνιζησθε δια την πιστιν, ητις απαξ παρεδοθη εις τους αγιους.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Geliefdes, terwyl ek alle ywer aanwend om aan julle oor ons gemeenskaplike saligheid te skrywe, het ek die noodsaaklikheid gevoel om julle deur my skrywe te vermaan om kragtig te stry vir die geloof wat eenmaal aan die heiliges oorgelewer is.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Zanmi m' yo, mwen pa t' manke anvi ekri nou pou m' te pale nou sou jan Bondye delivre nou tout ansanm lan. Men, m' blije ekri nou koulye a pou mwen kapab ankouraje nou, pou nou pran defans lafwa Bondye te bay yon sèl fwa pou tout tan an, pou tout moun pa l' yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Hỡi kẻ rất yêu_dấu , vì tôi đã ân_cần viết cho anh_em về sự cứu_rỗi chung của chúng_ta , tôi tưởng phải làm điều đó , để khuyên anh_em vì đạo mà tranh chiến , là đạo đã truyền cho các thánh một lần đủ rồi .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אהובי בהשתדלי לכתב אליכם על דבר התשועה האחת לכלנו חובה היא בעיני לזרזכם במכתב אשר תלחמו לאמונה המסורה פעם אחת לקדושים׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Beloved, while I was very eager to write to you about our common salvation, I was constrained to write to you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered to the saints.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ప్రియులారా, మనకందరికి కలిగెడు రక్షణనుగూర్చి మీకు వ్రాయవలెనని విశేషాసక్తిగలవాడనై ప్రయత్నపడు చుండగా, పరిశుద్ధులకు ఒక్కసారే అప్పగింపబడిన బోధ నిమిత్తము మీరు పోరాడవలెనని మిమ్మును వేడుకొనుచు మీకు వ్రాయవలసివచ్చెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						свирепи морски вълни; които изпущат като пяна своите безсрамни дела; скитащи звезди, за които се пази мрачна тъмнина до века.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ljubljeni, ko sem si mnogo prizadeval, pisati vam v skupnem nam zveličanju, se mi je potrebno videlo, pisati vam opominjaje, da se vrlo borite za vero, ki je enkrat za vselej izročena svetim.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						‌ای حبیبان، چون شوق تمام داشتم که درباره نجات عام به شما بنویسم، ناچار شدم که الان به شما بنویسم و نصیحت دهم تا شما مجاهده کنیدبرای آن ایمانی که یک بار به مقدسین سپرده شد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 I elskede! da det lå mig alvorligt på Sinde at skrive til eder om vor fælles Frelse, fandt jeg det nødvendigt at skrive til eder med Formaning om at stride for den Tro, som een Gang er bleven overgiven de hellige.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Rakkaani! Kun minulla on ollut harras halu kirjoittaa teille yhteisestä pelastuksestamme, tuli minulle pakko kirjoittaa ja kehoittaa teitä kilvoittelemaan sen uskon puolesta, joka kerta kaikkiaan on pyhille annettu.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						親愛 的 弟兄 阿 、 我 想 盡心寫信給 你 們 、 論 我 們同 得 救恩 的 時候 、 就 不得不 寫信勸 你 們 、 要 為從 前 一 次 交付 聖徒 的 真道 、 竭力 的 爭辯
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Ay baakoy, ay goono g'ay hina kulu te ka hantum araŋ se faaba boŋ kaŋ goono g'iri margu nda care, amma sohõ a tilas ay gaa ay ma hantum araŋ se k'araŋ yaamar araŋ ma anniya haw ka wongu te cimbeeri* fonda se, kaŋ Irikoy no hanantey se me fo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						親 愛 的 弟 兄 阿 、 我 想 盡 心 寫 信 給 你 們 、 論 我 們 同 得 救 恩 的 時 候 、 就 不 得 不 寫 信 勸 你 們 、 要 為 從 前 一 次 交 付 聖 徒 的 真 道 、 竭 力 的 爭 辯 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						हे प्रियो, जब मैं तुम्हें उस उद्धार के विषय में लिखने में अत्यन्त परिश्रम से प्रयत्न कर रहा था, जिस में हम सब सहभागी हैं; तो मैं ने तुम्हें यह समझाना आवश्यक जाना कि उस विश्वास के लिये पूरा यत्न करो जो पवित्रा लोगों को एक ही बार सौंपा गया था।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nejmilejší, všecku snažnost vynakládaje na to, abych vám psal o obecném spasení, musil jsem psáti, vás napomínaje, abyste statečně bojovali o víru, kteráž jest jednou dána svatým.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Amataj, kiam mi faris cxian diligentecon, por skribi al vi pri nia komuna savo, mi devigxis skribi al vi, por kuragxigi vin batali por la kredo, jam per unu fojo transdonita al la sanktuloj.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Sepse depërtuan ndërmjet jush disa njerëz, që qenë shënuar që moti për këtë dënim, të pabesë që e kthejnë hirin e Perëndisë tonë në imoralitet dhe mohojnë të vetmin Zotëri Perëndi, dhe Zotin tonë Jezu Krisht.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Carissimi, avevo un gran desiderio di scrivervi riguardo alla nostra salvezza, ma sono stato costretto a farlo per esortarvi a combattere per la fede, che fu trasmessa ai credenti una volta per tutte
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þér elskaðir, mér var það ríkt í huga að rita yður um sameiginlegt hjálpræði vort. En nú kemst ég ekki hjá því að skrifa og hvetja yður til að berjast fyrir þeirri trú, sem heilögum hefur í eitt skipti fyrir öll verið í hendur seld. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						प्रिय मित्रांनो, जरी मली तुम्हांला आपल्या समाईक तारणाविषयी लिहिण्याची आतुरतेने तयारी करीत होतो तरी एका गोष्टीविषयी मला लिहावेसे वाटते. ते म्हणजे देवाने आपल्या संतांना, एकदा दिलेला विश्वास टिकविण्यासाठी लढत राहा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						愛する者たちよ。わたしたちが共にあずかっている救について、あなたがたに書きおくりたいと心から願っていたので、聖徒たちによって、ひとたび伝えられた信仰のために戦うことを勧めるように、手紙をおくる必要を感じるに至った。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Amados, mientras me esforzaba por escribiros acerca de nuestra común salvación, me ha sido necesario escribir para exhortaros a que contendáis eficazmente por la fe que fue entregada una vez a los santos
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Gacaliyayaalow, intaan aad u dadaalayay inaan idiin soo qoro wax ku saabsan badbaadada inaga dhexaysa, waxaa dirqi igu noqday inaan idiin soo qoro oo aan idinku waaniyo inaad aad ugu dadaashaan iimaankii mar la wada siiyey quduusiinta oo dhan.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Deihtakte aw, i kikop hotdamna thu na kiang ua gelh ka tup teitei lain, misiangthoute kianga ginna khatvei kepsak lamah phatuam ngai taka pang dinga honhasuan dingin na kiang ua lai gelh a kiphamoh chih kana theia.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಪ್ರಿಯರೇ, ಹುದುವಾಗಿರುವ ರಕ್ಷಣೆಯ ವಿಷಯ ದಲ್ಲಿ ನಿಮಗೆ ಬರೆಯುವದಕ್ಕೆ ಪೂರ್ಣ ಜಾಗ್ರತೆಯಿಂದ ಪ್ರಯತ್ನಮಾಡುತ್ತಿದ್ದಾಗ ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧರಿಗೆ ಒಂದೇ ಸಾರಿ ಒಪ್ಪಿಸಲ್ಪಟ್ಟ ನಂಬಿಕೆಯನ್ನು ಕಾಪಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವದಕ್ಕೆ ನೀವು ಹೋರಾಡಬೇಕೆಂದು ಎಚ್ಚರಿಸಿ ಬರೆಯುವದು ಅವಶ್ಯವೆಂದು ತೋಚಿತು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common salvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you that ye should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto the saints.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Vrienden, ik voelde mij gedrongen u te schrijven over de bevrijding die wij allemaal hebben ervaren, maar nu zie ik dat ik eerst over iets anders moet beginnen. Ik roep u op te strijden voor het geloof, dat God aan Zijn volk gegeven heeft.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Ljubljeni! Dok sam u svojoj brižljivosti kanio pisati  vam o našem zajedničkom spasenju, osjetio sam potrebu da vas  pismom potaknem da vojujete za vjeru koja je jednom zauvijek  predana svetima.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Najmilsi! Wszelką pilność czyniąc, abym wam pisał o społecznem zbawieniu, musiałem wam pisać, napominając, iżbyście bojowali o wiarę raz świętym podaną.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คำเตือนให้คริสเตียนต่อสู้อย่างจริงจังเพื่อความเชื่อท่านที่รักทั้งหลาย เมื่อข้าพเจ้าพากเพียรเขียนถึงท่านทั้งหลายในเรื่องเกี่ยวกับความรอดสำหรับคนทั่วไปนั้น ข้าพเจ้าก็เห็นว่า ข้าพเจ้าจำเป็นต้องเขียนเตือนสติท่านให้ต่อสู้อย่างจริงจังเพื่อความเชื่อซึ่งครั้งหนึ่งได้ทรงโปรดมอบไว้แก่วิสุทธิชนแล้ว</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Mga minamahal, samantalang ako'y totoong nagsisikap ng pagsulat sa inyo tungkol sa kaligtasan nating lahat, ay napilitan akong sumulat sa inyo na inaaralan kayong makipaglabang masikap dahil sa pananampalataya na ibinigay na minsan at magpakailan man sa mga banal. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 愛 する 者 たち よ 。 わたし たち が 共 に あずか っ て い る 救 に つ い て 、 あなた がた に 書き お く り た い と 心 から 願 っ て い た の で 、 聖徒 たち に よ っ て 、 ひとたび 伝え られ た 信仰 の ため に 戦 う こと を 勧め る よう に 、 手紙 を おく る 必要 を 感じ る に 至 っ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						പ്രിയരേ, നമുക്കു പൊതുവിലുള്ള രക്ഷയെക്കുറിച്ചു നിങ്ങള്‍ക്കു എഴുതുവാന്‍ സകലപ്രയത്നവും ചെയ്കയില്‍ വിശുദ്ധന്മാര്‍ക്കും ഒരിക്കലായിട്ടു ഭരമേല്പിച്ചിരിക്കുന്ന വിശ്വാസത്തിന്നു വേണ്ടി പോരാടേണ്ടതിന്നു പ്രബോധിപ്പിച്ചെഴുതുവാന്‍ ആവശ്യം എന്നു എനിക്കു തോന്നി.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Prea iubiţilor, pe cînd căutam cutot dinadinsul să vă scriu despre mîntuirea noastră de obşte, m'am văzut silit să vă scriu ca să vă îndemn să luptaţi pentru credinţa, care a fost dată sfinţilor odată pentru totdeauna.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Ihr Lieben, nachdem ich vorhatte, euch zu schreiben von unser aller Heil, hielt ich's für nötig, euch mit Schriften zu ermahnen, daß ihr für den Glauben kämpfet, der einmal den Heiligen übergeben ist.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Mina älskade, då jag nu med all iver har tagit mig för att skriva till eder om vår gemensamma frälsning, finner jag det nödigt att i min skrivelse förmana eder att kämpa för den tro som en gång för alla har blivit meddelad åt de heliga.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คำ เตือน ให้ คริสเตียน ต่อสู้ อย่าง จริงจัง เพื่อ ความ เชื่อ ท่าน ที่รัก ทั้งหลาย เมื่อ ข้าพเจ้า พากเพียร เขียน ถึง ท่าน ทั้งหลาย ใน เรื่อง เกี่ยว กับ ความ รอด สำหรับ คน ทั่วไป นั้น ข้าพเจ้า ก็ เห็น ว่า ข้าพเจ้า จำเป็น ต้อง เขียน เตือนสติ ท่าน ให้ ต่อสู้ อย่าง จริงจัง เพื่อ ความ เชื่อ ซึ่ง ครั้ง หนึ่ง ได้ ทรง โปรด มอบ ไว้ แก่ วิ สุทธิ ชน แล้ว</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Armsad, et mul oli kange hool kirjutada teile meie ühisest õndsusest, siis oli mul tungiv vajadus manitseda teid võitlemisele pühadele kord antud usu poolest.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.4" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Kua tomo puku mai hoki etahi tangata, ko era ano i tuhituhia i mua mo tenei whakataunga he, he hunga karakiakore, e whakaputa ke ana ratou i te aroha noa o to tatou Atua hei mea mo nga hiahia taikaha, a whakakahore ana ratou ki to tatou Ariki, ki a Ihu Karaiti, ko ia anake to tatou Ariki
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Vì có mấy kẻ kia lẻn vào trong vòng chúng ta là những kẻ bị định đoán phạt từ lâu rồi, kẻ chẳng tin kính đổi ơn Ðức Chúa Trời chúng ta ra việc tà ác, chối Ðấng Chủ tể và Chúa có một của chúng ta, là Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Car il s`est glissé parmi vous certains hommes, dont la condamnation est écrite depuis longtemps, des impies, qui changent la grâce de notre Dieu en dissolution, et qui renient notre seul maître et Seigneur Jésus Christ.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa misy olona sasany efa niditra misokosoko, izay voasoratra fahiny ho amin'izany fahamelohana izany, dia olona ratsy fanahy izay mamadika ny fahasoavan'Andriamanitsika ho fijejojejoana sady nandà ny Andrian-tokana, dia Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika. [ Na: mandà ny Andrian-tokana sy Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Mert belopózkodtak valami emberek, a kik régen elõre beírattak ezen ítéletre, istentelenek, kik a mi Istenünknek kegyelmét bujálkodásra fordítják, és az egyedüli Urat, az Istent, és a mi Urunkat, a Jézus Krisztust megtagadják.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Kuba kuthwethwe bantu bathile; abo babebalulelwe ngenxa engaphambili kolo lugwebo, abangahloneli Thixo, belujikela eburheletyweni ubabalo lukaThixo wethu, bemkhanyela okuphela koMnini-nto-zonke, uThixo wethu, iNkosi yethu uYesu Kristu.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">이는 가만히 들어온 사람 몇이 있음이라 저희는 옛적부터 이 판결을 받기로 미리 기록된 자니 경건치 아니하여 우리 하나님의 은혜를 도리어 색욕거리로 바꾸고 홀로 하나이신 주재 곧 우리 주 예수 그리스도를 부인하는 자니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Mat vogčiomis įsiskverbė žmonių, kuriems nuo seno surašytas toks pasmerkimas: jie bedieviai, iškreipia mūsų Dievo malonę į palaidumą ir neigia mūsų vienintelį Valdovą Dievą ir Viešpatį Jėzų Kristų.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Ибо вкрались некоторые люди, издревле предназначенные к сему осуждению, нечестивые, обращающие благодать Бога нашего в повод к распутству и отвергающиеся единого Владыки Бога и Господа нашего Иисуса Христа.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Sebab tanpa kita sadari, ada oknum-oknum tertentu yang menyelusup masuk ke tengah-tengah kita. Mereka orang-orang bejat yang memutarbalikkan berita tentang rahmat Allah kita, untuk mendapat kesempatan melampiaskan hawa nafsu mereka. Dan mereka menolak Yesus Kristus, satu-satunya Penguasa dan Tuhan kita. Sejak dahulu hukuman untuk mereka sudah dinubuatkan dalam Alkitab
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kay kaninyo nanagpakasulod sa hilum ang pipila ka mga tawo nga dugay nang gikatagana alang niining maong pagkahinukman sa silot, mga tawong dili diosnon nga nanaghimo sa hiniwi nga pagpadapat sa grasya sa atong Dios alang sa ilang pagpatuyang ug nanagpanghimakak sa atong Bugtong Agalon ug Ginoo, si Jesu-Cristo.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အဘယ်ကြောင့်နည်းဟူမူကား၊ ငါတို့ဘုရားသခင်၏ ကျေးဇူးတော်ကို ကိလေသာ၏ ညစ်ညူးခြင်း အလိုငှါမှောက်လှန်လျက်၊ တပါးတည်း အစိုးရတော်မူသောအရှင်၊ ငါတို့သခင် ယေရှုခရစ်ကို ငြင်းပယ်လျက်၊ အပြစ်ခံစေခြင်းငှါ ရှေးကစီရင် မှတ်သားနှင့်သော အဓမ္မလူအချို့တို့သည် ပရိယာယ်နှင့် အမှတ်တမဲ့ဝင်ကြပြီ။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Nintz'îba li hu a'in xban nak cuanqueb aj balak' que'xch'ic rib sa' êyânk chi mukmu. Eb a'an neque'xye nak laj pâbanel naru te'xbânu yalak c'a'ru chi mâusilal ut xban li rusilal li kaDios, mâc'a' te'xc'ul. Neque'xsach xcuanquil li Kâcua' Jesucristo, laj êchal ke. Eb a'an aj k'etoleb râtin li Dios ut chalen chak junxil cutan ac xakabanbil chak li rakba âtin sa' xbêneb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Lebo sa kradmo bočnými cestami votreli niektorí ľudia, dávno vopred zapísaní k tomu odsúdeniu, bezbožníci, ktorí obracajú milosť našeho Boha na nestudatosť a jediného samovládcu Boha a nášho Pána Ježiša Krista zapierajú.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						कोही मानिसहरु तिमीहरुको समूहमा सुटुक्क पसेका छन्। तिनीहरुले गरिरहेका कुराको निम्ति दोषी ठहर्याई सकिएकोछ। धेरै अघि, अगमवक्ताहरुले तिनीहरुको विषयमा लेखेका थिए। तिनीहरु परमेश्वरका शत्रुहरु हुन्। तिनीहरुले हाम्रा परमेश्वरको अनुग्रहलाई हर तरहको पापकर्म गर्ने अनुमति पत्र बनाएका छन्। तिनीहरु हाम्रा एकमात्र मालिक एवं प्रभु येशू ख्रीष्टलाई अस्वीकार गर्छन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Jer se uvukoše neki bezbožni ljudi, koji su davno odredjeni na ovo sudjenje, i Boga našeg blagodat pretvaraju u nečistotu, i jedinog Gospodara Boga i Gospoda našeg Isusa Hrista odriču se.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						For nogen mennesker har sneket sig inn, som denne dom allerede for lenge siden er opskrevet for: ugudelige, som forvender vår Guds nåde til skamløshet og nekter vår eneste hersker og herre, Jesus Kristus. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Çünkü Tanrımızın lütfunu sefahate araç eden, tek Efendimiz ve Rabbimiz İsa Mesihi yadsıyan bazı tanrısızlar gizlice aranıza sızdılar. Onların yargılanacakları çoktan beri yazılmıştır.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						لانه دخل خلسة اناس قد كتبوا منذ القديم لهذه الدينونة فجار يحوّلون نعمة الهنا الى الدعارة وينكرون السيد الوحيد الله وربنا يسوع المسيح
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Porque se introduziram furtivamente certos homens, que já desde há muito estavam destinados para este juízo, homens ímpios, que convertem em dissolução a graça de nosso Deus, e negam o nosso único Soberano e Senhor, Jesus Cristo.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">subintroierunt enim quidam homines qui olim praescripti sunt in hoc iudicium impii Dei nostri gratiam transferentes in luxuriam et solum Dominatorem et Dominum nostrum Iesum Christum negantes</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Διοτι εισεχωρησαν λαθραιως τινες ανθρωποι, οιτινες ησαν παλαιοθεν προγεγραμμενοι εις ταυτην την καταδικην, ασεβεις, μεταστρεφοντες την χαριν του Θεου ημων εις ασελγειαν, και αρνουμενοι τον μονον Δεσποτην Θεον και Κυριον ημων Ιησουν Χριστον.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Want sekere mense het ingesluip wat lank tevore al opgeskryf is vir hierdie oordeel, goddelose mense wat die genade van onse God verander in ongebondenheid, en die enigste Heerser, God, en onse Here Jesus Christus verloën.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Paske, gen kèk mechan ki gen tan fofile kò yo nan mitan nou. Se moun ki san respè pou Bondye. Yo pran renmen Bondye renmen nou an sèvi yon kouvèti pou fè dezòd. Yo vire do bay Jezikri ki sèl Mèt ak sèl Segnè nou an. Depi lontan yo te ekri nan Liv la ki kalite kondannasyon k'ap tann moun sa yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Vì có mấy kẻ kia lẻn vào trong vòng chúng_ta là những kẻ bị định đoán phạt từ lâu rồi , kẻ chẳng tin kính đổi ơn Ðức_Chúa_Trời chúng_ta ra việc tà ác , chối Ðấng_Chủ tể và Chúa có một của chúng_ta , là Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						כי התגנבו לבוא מקצת אנשים הכתובים מאז למשפט הזה אנשי רשע ההפכים את חסד אלהינו לזמה וכפרים באלהים המשל היחיד ובאדנינו ישוע המשיח׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">For there are certain men who crept in secretly, even those who were long ago written about for this condemnation: ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into indecency, and denying our only Master, God, and Lord, Jesus Christ.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఏలయనగా కొందరు రహస్యముగా జొరబడియున్నారు. వారు భక్తిహీనులై మన దేవుని కృపను కామాతురత్వమునకు దుర్వినియోగ పరచుచు, మన అద్వితీయనాధుడును ప్రభువునైన యేసు క్రీస్తును విసర్జించుచున్నారు; ఈ తీర్పుపొందుటకు వారు పూర్వమందే సూచింపబడినవారు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						За тях пророкува и Енох, седмият от Адама, като рече: Ето Господ иде с десетки хиляди Свои светии,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kajti priplazili so se neki ljudje, zdavnaj naprej zapisani za to sodbo, brezbožni, ki milost Boga našega krivo rabijo v razuzdanost in taje edinega Vladarja in Gospoda našega, Jezusa Kristusa.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						زیرا که بعضی اشخاص در خفا درآمده‌اند که ازقدیم برای این قصاص مقرر شده بودند؛ مردمان بی‌دین که فیض خدای ما را به فجور تبدیل نموده و عیسی مسیح آقای واحد و خداوند ما را انکارکرده‌اند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Thi der har indsneget sig nogle Mennesker, om hvem det for længe siden er forud skrevet, at de vilde falde under denne Dom: Ugudelige, som misbruge vor, Guds Nåde til Uterlighed og fornægte vor eneste Hersker og Herre Jesus Kristus.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Sillä teidän keskuuteenne on pujahtanut eräitä ihmisiä, joiden jo aikoja sitten on kirjoitettu tulevan tähän tuomioon, jumalattomia, jotka kääntävät meidän Jumalamme armon irstaudeksi ja kieltävät meidän ainoan valtiaamme ja Herramme, Jeesuksen Kristuksen.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						因為 有些 人 偷 著 進來 、 就 是 自古 被 定 受刑 罰 的 、 是 不 虔誠 的 、 將我們神 的 恩變作 放縱 情慾 的 機會 、 並且 不 認獨 一 的 主宰 我 們 〔 我 們 或 作 和 我 們 〕 主 耶穌基督
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Zama boro fooyaŋ mollo ka furo iri game ra, ngey kaŋ ciiti ka zeeriyaŋo go hantumante za gayyaŋ. Boroyaŋ no kaŋ ga wangu Irikoy, kaŋ yaŋ g'iri Irikoyo gomno bare mo ka te furkutaray kobay. I goono g'iri wane Koy follonka ze kaŋ ti iri Rabbi Yesu Almasihu. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						因 為 有 些 人 偷 著 進 來 、 就 是 自 古 被 定 受 刑 罰 的 、 是 不 虔 誠 的 、 將 我 們 　 神 的 恩 變 作 放 縱 情 慾 的 機 會 、 並 且 不 認 獨 一 的 主 宰 我 們 〔 我 們 或 作 和 我 們 〕 主 耶 穌 基 督 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						क्योंकि कितने ऐसे मनुष्य चुपके से हम में आ मिले हैं, जिन से इस दण्ड का वर्णन पुराने समय में पहिले ही से लिखा गया था: ये भक्तिहीन हैं, और हमारे परमेश्वर के अनुग्रह को लुचपन में बदल डालते है, और हमारे अद्वैत स्वामी और प्रभु यीशु मसीह का इन्कार करते हैं।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Neboť jsou podešli někteří lidé bezbožní, prve již dávno poznamenaní k tomu odsouzení; kteřížto milost Boha našeho přenášejí v chlipnost, a toho, kterýž jest sám Hospodin, Boha a Pána našeho Jezukrista zapírají.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						CXar ensxteligxis iuj homoj, jam antaux longe destinitaj por cxi tiu kondamno, malpiuloj, sxangxante la gracon de nia Dio en dibocxecon, kaj malkonfesante la solan Estron kaj nian Sinjoron Jesuo Kristo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Dhe dua t'ju kujtoj, ndonëse tashmë i dini gjithë këto, se Zoti, pasi e shpëtoi popullin e tij nga vendi i Egjiptit, pastaj i shkatërroi ata që nuk besuan.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Si sono infiltrati infatti tra voi alcuni individui - i quali sono gia stati segnati da tempo per questa condanna - empi che trovano pretesto alla loro dissolutezza nella grazia del nostro Dio, rinnegando il nostro unico padrone e signore Gesù Cristo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Því að inn hafa læðst nokkrir menn, sem fyrir löngu var ritað um að þessi dómur biði þeirra. Þeir eru óguðlegir menn, sem misnota náð Guðs vors til taumleysis og afneita vorum einasta lávarði og Drottni, Jesú Kristi. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						याचे कारण ज्यांच्याविषयी पवित्र शास्त्रात फार पूर्वीच लिहिले आहे की अशी माणसे तुमच्यात चोरुन शिरली आहेत, ते अधार्मिक लोक आहेत. अनीतीने वागण्यासाठी देवाची दया हे निमित आहे असे ते मानतात. आणि आमचा प्रभु व एकमेव धनी अशा प्रभु येशू ख्रिस्ताला ते मानत नाहीत. जी शिक्षेसाठी यापूर्वीच नेमलेली होती, अशी ही माणसे आहेत.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						そのわけは、不信仰な人々がしのび込んできて、わたしたちの神の恵みを放縦な生活に変え、唯一の君であり、わたしたちの主であるイエス・キリストを否定しているからである。彼らは、このようなさばきを受けることに、昔から予告されているのである。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Porque algunos hombres han entrado encubiertamente, los cuales desde antiguo habían sido destinados para esta condenación. Ellos son hombres impíos, que convierten la gracia de nuestro Dios en libertinaje y niegan al único Soberano y Señor nuestro, Jesucristo
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Waayo, waxaa jira niman qarsoodi idiinku soo galay, waana kuwii waa hore xukunkan loo qoray, oo ah kuwa aan cibaadada lahayn, oo nimcada Ilaaheenna ku beddela nijaas, oo inkira Ciise Masiix oo ah Sayidkeenna iyo Rabbigeenna keliya.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Mi kuatehiam a guka hong lut a om ngal ua, nidang laia pan hiai siamlouhtanna dia sehte; huaite tuh Pathian hehpihna akaikawiin, i Heutupa leh i Toupa neih sun, Jesu Kris tuh a kitheihmohbawl behlap uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಯಾಕಂದರೆ ಭಕ್ತಿಹೀನರೂ ನಮ್ಮ ದೇವರ ಕೃಪೆಯನ್ನು ನೆವ ಮಾಡಿಕೊಂಡು ನಾಚಿಕೆಗೆಟ್ಟ ಕೃತ್ಯಗಳನ್ನು ನಡಿಸುವವರೂ ನಮ್ಮ ಒಬ್ಬನೇ ಕರ್ತನಾದ ದೇವರನ್ನು ಮತ್ತು ನಮ್ಮ ಕರ್ತನಾದ ಯೇಸು ಕ್ರಿಸ್ತನನ್ನು ಅಲ್ಲಗಳೆಯುವ ಈ ಕೆಲವು ಜನರು ರಹಸ್ಯವಾಗಿ ಒಳಗೆ ಹೊಕ್ಕಿದ್ದಾರೆ; ಇವರು ಈ ದಂ
					</lang><lang id="English">
						For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus Christ.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Ik zeg dit omdat er onbetrouwbare mensen zijn binnengedrongen, die beweren dat wij er maar op los kunnen leven. Volgens hen is Gods genade zo groot dat Hij alles door de vingers ziet. Het staat allang vast dat mensen die dit zeggen en toepassen, daarvoor veroordeeld zullen worden. Zij weigeren Jezus Christus als Leider en Heer van hun leven te erkennen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Jer ušuljali se neki, odavna već zapisani  za ovaj sud, bezbožnici koji milost Boga našega promeću u razuzdanost  i niječu jedinoga gospodara i Gospodina našega Isusa Krista.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Albowiem wkradli się niektórzy ludzie, dawno już przedtem naznaczeni na to potępienie, niepobożni, którzy łaskę Boga naszego obracają w rozpustę i samego się Boga i panującego Pana naszego, Jezusa Chrystusa zapierają.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เพราะว่ามีบางคนได้เล็ดลอดเข้ามาอย่างไม่รู้ตัว ซึ่งเป็นผู้ที่ถูกเล็งไว้ล่วงหน้ามานานแล้วว่าจะได้รับการพิพากษาลงโทษอย่างนี้ เป็นคนอธรรม ที่ได้บิดเบือนพระคุณของพระเจ้าของเราไปเป็นการกระทำความชั่วช้าลามก และได้ปฏิเสธพระเจ้าคือองค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าแต่เพียงพระองค์เดียว และพระเยซูคริสต์องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าของเรา</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Sapagka't may ilang taong nagsipasok ng lihim, yaong mga itinalaga nang una pa sa kahatulang ito, mga di banal, na pinalitan ng kalibugan ang biyaya ng ating Dios, na itinatatuwa ang ating iisang Guro at Panginoong si Jesucristo. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
					 	 その わけ は 、 不信仰 な 人々 が し のび込 ん で き て 、 わたし たち の 神 の 恵み を 放縦 な 生活 に 変え 、 唯一 の 君 で あ り 、 わたし たち の 主 で あ る イエス ・ キリスト を 否定 し て い る から で あ る 。 彼 ら は 、 この よう な さばき を 受け る こと に 、 昔 から 予告 さ れ て い る の で あ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നമ്മുടെ ദൈവത്തിന്റെ കൃപയെ ദുഷ്കാമവൃത്തിക്കു ഹേതുവാക്കി ഏകനാഥനും നമ്മുടെ കര്‍ത്താവുമായ യേശുക്രിസ്തുവിനെ നിഷേധിക്കുന്ന അഭക്തരായ ചില മനുഷ്യര്‍ നുഴഞ്ഞു വന്നിരിക്കുന്നു; അവരുടെ ഈ ശിക്ഷാവിധി പണ്ടു തന്നേ എഴുതിയിരിക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Căci s'au strecurat printre voi unii oameni, scrişi de mult pentru osînda aceasta, oameni neevlavioşi, cari schimbă în desfrînare harul Dumnezeului nostru, şi tăgăduiesc pe singurul nostru Stăpîn şi Domn Isus Hristos.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Denn es sind etliche Menschen nebeneingeschlichen, von denen vorzeiten geschrieben ist solches Urteil: Die sind Gottlose, ziehen die Gnade unsers Gottes auf Mutwillen und verleugnen Gott und unsern HERRN Jesus Christus, den einigen Herrscher.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Några människor hava nämligen innästlat sig hos eder -- några om vilka det för länge sedan blev skrivet att de skulle hemfalla under den domen -- ogudaktiga människor, som missbruka vår Guds nåd till lösaktighet och förneka vår ende härskare och herre, Jesus Kristus.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เพราะว่า มี บาง คน ได้ เล็ดลอด เข้า มา อย่าง ไม่ รู้ตัว ซึ่ง เป็น ผู้ ที่ ถูก เล็ง ไว้ ล่วงหน้า มา นาน แล้ว ว่า จะ ได้ รับ การ พิพากษา ลงโทษ อย่าง นี้ เป็น คน อธรรม ที่ ได้ บิดเบือน พระ คุณ ของ พระเจ้า ของ เรา ไป เป็นการ กระทำ ความ ชั่วช้า ลามก และ ได้ ปฏิเสธ พระเจ้า คือ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า แต่ เพียง พระองค์ เดียว และ พระ เยซู คริสต์ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ของ เรา</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Sest teie sekka on poetunud mõningaid inimesi, kes juba ammu on pandud kirja tulevase hukatuse jaoks, jumalatuid, kes meie Jumala armu tarvitavad, et lodevalt elada, ning salgavad meie ainsa valitseja ja meie Issanda Jeesuse Kristuse.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.5" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na, e mea ana ahau kia whakamaharatia koutou, kua matau noa ake ano ia koutou ki tenei, i whakaorangia mai e te Ariki te iwi i te whenua o Ihipa, muri iho whakangaromia ana e ia te hunga kihai nei i whakapono
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Dầu Anh em đã học những điều nầy rồi, tôi cũng muốn nhắc lại cho anh em rằng, xưa kia Chúa giải cứu dân mình ra khỏi xứ Ê-díp-tô, sau lại tiêu diệt những kẻ không tin;
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Je veux vous rappeler, à vous qui savez fort bien toutes ces choses, que le Seigneur, après avoir sauvé le peuple et l`avoir tiré du pays d`Égypte, fit ensuite périr les incrédules;
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary ta-hampahatsiaro anareo aho, na dia efa fantatrareo rahateo aza ny zavatra rehetra, fa rehefa novonjen'ny Tompo ho afaka tany Egypta ny olona, dia naringany ihany tao aorian'izany izay tsy nino.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						lékeztetni akarlak továbbá titeket, mint a kik egyszer [már] tudjátok, hogy az Úr, a mikor a népet Égyiptom földébõl kiszabadította, viszontag azokat, a kik nem hittek, elvesztette.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ndinga ke ndinganikhumbuza, nangona nikwazi oku kakade,  ukuba iNkosi, yakuba ibasindisile abantu emhlabeni waseYiputa,  yathi ngokwesibini yabatshabalalisa abo bangakholwanga.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">너희가 본래 범사를 알았으나 내가 너희로 다시 생각나게 하고자 하노라 주께서 백성을 애굽에서 구원하여 내시고 후에 믿지 아니하는 자들을 멸하셨으며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Aš noriu jums priminti, nors jūs tai jau žinote, kad Viešpats, pirmiau išgelbėjęs tautą iš Egipto žemės, paskui pražudė tuos, kurie netikėjo.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Я хочу напомнить вам, уже знающим это, что Господь, избавив народ из земли Египетской, потом неверовавших погубил,
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Semuanya itu kalian sudah tahu. Namun saya ingin mengingatkan kalian mengenai bagaimana Tuhan menyelamatkan umat Israel dari negeri Mesir, tetapi kemudian membinasakan orang-orang yang tidak percaya di antara mereka
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Karon buot kong ipahinumdom kaninyo, bisan tuod sa makausa ug sa dayon nasayran na ninyo ang tanan, nga ang Ginoo nga nagluwas sa usa ka katawhan gikan sa yuta sa Egipto, siya sa kapulihay milaglag diha kanila niadtong wala managpanoo.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထို့ကြောင့် သင်တို့သည်သိနှင့်သော်လည်း ငါသည် သတိပေး၍ ပြောချင်သော အကြောင်းအရာ ဟူမူကား၊ ထာဝရဘုရားသည် ဣသရေလ လူတို့ကို အဲဂုတ္တုပြည်မှ ကယ်လွှတ်တော်မူပြီးလျှင်၊ မယုံကြည်သော သူတို့ကိုတဖန် ဖျက်ဆီးတော်မူ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Usta ac xch'olobaman chêru, nacuaj cui'chic xjulticanquil êre chanru nak li Kâcua' Dios quirisiheb chak lix tenamit aj Israel sa' li na'ajej Egipto. Ut mokon chic quixsacheb li inc'a' que'pâban chiru sa' xyânkeb laj Israel.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A chcem vám pripomenúť, ktorí raz viete to všetko, že Pán zachrániac ľud z Egyptskej zeme po druhé tých, ktorí neuverili, zatratil
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमीहरुले जानिसकेको कुराहरु तिमीहरुलाई स्मरण गराउनमा म सहायता गर्न चाहन्छु याद गर कि प्रभुले मिश्र देशबाट बाहिर ल्याएर उहाँका मानिसहरुलाई बचाँउनु भयो। तर उहाँले ती सबै मानिसहरुको संहार गर्नु भयो जसले विश्वास गरेनन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ali ću vam napomenuti, kad i vi znate ovo jedanput, da Gospod izbavi narod iz zemlje misirske, potom pogubi one koji ne verovaše.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men da I nu engang vet alt, vil jeg minne eder om at Herren, efterat han hadde frelst folket ut av Egyptens land, siden ødela dem som ikke trodde, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Bütün bunları bildiğiniz halde, size anımsatmak isterim ki, ilk ve son kez halkı Mısırdan kurtaran Rab iman etmeyenleri daha sonra yok etti.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						فاريد ان اذكّركم ولو علمتم هذا مرة ان الرب بعدما خلّص الشعب من ارض مصر اهلك ايضا الذين لم يؤمنوا.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Ora, quero lembrar-vos, se bem que já de uma vez para sempre soubestes tudo isto, que, havendo o Senhor salvo um povo, tirando-o da terra do Egito, destruiu depois os que não creram;
					</lang><lang id="Latin">commonere autem vos volo scientes semel omnia quoniam Iesus populum de terra Aegypti salvans secundo eos qui non crediderunt perdidit</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Θελω δε να σας υπενθυμισω, αν και σεις εγνωρισατε ηδη τουτο, οτι ο Κυριος, αφου εσωσε τον λαον εκ γης Αιγυπτου, απωλεσεν υστερον τους μη πιστευσαντας.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar ek wil julle daaraan herinner, al weet julle dit nou eenmaal, dat die Here, nadat Hy die volk uit Egipteland gered het, daarna die wat ongelowig was, omgebring het.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Atout nou deja konnen tout bagay sa yo byen pròp, mwen vle fè nou chonje ki jan, lè Bondye te fin delivre pèp Izrayèl la anba moun Lejip yo, li te detwi tout moun ki pa t' kwè yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Dầu_Anh em đã học những điều nầy rồi , tôi cũng muốn nhắc lại cho anh_em rằng , xưa kia Chúa giải_cứu dân mình ra khỏi xứ Ê - díp-tô , sau lại tiêu_diệt những kẻ không tin ;
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ויש את נפשי להזכיר אתכם את אשר כבר ידעתם כי הושיע יהוה את העם ממצרים וישמד אחרי כן את אשר לא האמינו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Now I desire to remind you, though you already know this, that the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those who didn't believe.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఈ సంగతులన్నియు మీరు ముందటనే యెరిగి యున్నను, నేను మీకు జ్ఞాపకము చేయగోరుచున్న దేమనగా, ప్రభువు ఐగుప్తులోనుండి ప్రజలను రక్షించి నను, వారిలో నమ్మకపోయినవారిని తరువాత నాశనము చేసెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						да извърши съдба на всички, и да обяви за виновни всичките нечестиви дела, които в нечестие са сторили, и за всичките жестоки думи, които нечестивите грешници са говорили против Него.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Spomniti pa vas hočem, čeprav zdaj vse to že veste, da je Gospod, ko je rešil ljudstvo iz dežele Egiptovske, pozneje pogubil tiste, ki niso verovali.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						پس می‌خواهم شما را یاد دهم، هرچند همه‌چیز را دفعه می‌دانید که بعد از آنکه خداوند، قوم را از زمین مصر رهایی بخشیده بود، بار دیگربی ایمانان را هلاک فرمود.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 Men skønt I een Gang for alle vide det alt sammen, vil jeg minde eder om, at da Herren havde frelst Folket ud af Ægyptens Land, ødelagde han næste Gang dem, som ikke troede,
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Vaikka jo kerran olette saaneet tietää kaiken, tahdon kuitenkin muistuttaa teitä siitä, että Herra, joka oli pelastanut kansan Egyptistä, toisella kertaa hukutti ne, jotka eivät uskoneet;
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						從前 主 救了 他 的 百姓 出 埃及 地 、 後來 就 把 那些 不信 的 滅絕 了 ． 這 一切 的 事 、 你 們雖 然 都 知道 、 我卻仍 要 題醒 你 們
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Baa kaŋ araŋ jin ka hayey wo kulu bay, ay ga ba ay m'araŋ fongandi, kaŋ Rabbi na nga jama faaba ka kaa Misira laabo ra, amma woodin banda a na borey kaŋ mana cimandi halaci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						從 前 主 救 了 他 的 百 姓 出 埃 及 地 、 後 來 就 把 那 些 不 信 的 滅 絕 了 ． 這 一 切 的 事 、 你 們 雖 然 都 知 道 、 我 卻 仍 要 題 醒 你 們 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						पर यद्यपि तुम सब बात एक बार जान चुके हो, तौभी मैं तुम्हें इस बात की सुधि दिलाना चाहता हूं, कि प्रभु ने एक कुल को मि  देश से छुड़ाने के बाद विश्वास न लानेवालों को नाश कर दिया।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Protož vidělo mi se vám to připomenouti, kteříž jednou již o tom víte, že když Pán lid svůj z země Egyptské vysvobodil, potom ty, kteříž nevěřící byli, zatratil.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Mi do volas rememorigi vin, kvankam vi jam per unu fojo sciigxis pri cxio,  ke la Sinjoro, savinte popolon el la Egipta lando, poste pereigis la nekredantojn.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Ai i ruajti me pranga të përjetshme në errësirë për gjyqin e ditës së madhe, edhe engjëjt që nuk e ruajtën gjendjen e tyre të parë, po e lanë banimin e tyre,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ora io voglio ricordare a voi, che gia conoscete tutte queste cose, che il Signore dopo aver salvato il popolo dalla terra d'Egitto, fece perire in seguito quelli che non vollero credere
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Ég vil minna yður á, þótt þér nú einu sinni vitið það allt, að Drottinn frelsaði lýðinn úr Egyptalandi, en tortímdi samt síðar þeim, sem ekki trúðu. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						जरी तुम्हांला या गोष्टी माहीत असल्या तरी मला तुम्हांला आठवण करुन द्यावीशी वाटते की, ज्या प्रभूने आपल्या लोकांना एकदा इजिप्त देशातून सोडवून आणल्यानंतर ज्यांनी त्याच्यावर विश्वास ठेवण्याचे नाकारले; अशांचा त्याने नंतर नाश केला
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたがたはみな、じゅうぶんに知っていることではあるが、主が民をエジプトの地から救い出して後、不信仰な者を滅ぼされたことを、思い起してもらいたい。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Ahora bien, quiero haceros recordar, ya que todo lo habéis sabido, que el Señor, al librar al pueblo una vez de la tierra de Egipto, después destruyó a los que no creyeron
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Hadda, in kastoo aad hore u tiqiineen wax kasta, waxaan jeclahay inaan idin xusuusiyo sidii Rabbigu dad uga badbaadiyey dalka Masar, dabadeedna u baabbi'iyey kuwii aan rumaysan isaga;
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huan, bangkim khatveiin thei vek mahle uchin, Toupan Aigupta gama kipana mite a suahtaksaka, huai nung gingtaloute tuh a hihmanthat dan nou hontheihsak nawn ka ut ahi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನೀವು ಇದನ್ನು ಒಂದು ಸಾರಿ ತಿಳಿದವರಾಗಿದ್ದರೂ ನಾನು ಅದನ್ನೇ ನಿಮ್ಮ ಜ್ಞಾಪಕಕ್ಕೆ ತರಬೇಕೆಂದು ಅಪೇಕ್ಷಿಸುತ್ತೇನೆ. ಅದು ಯಾವದಂದರೆ--ಕರ್ತನು (ತನ್ನ) ಪ್ರಜೆಯನ್ನು ಐಗುಪ್ತದೇಶದೊಳಗಿಂದ ರಕ್ಷಿಸಿ ದರೂ ತರುವಾಯ ಅವರೊಳಗೆ ನಂಬದೆ ಹೋದ ವರನ್ನು ಸಂಹಾರ ಮಾಡಿದನು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						I will therefore put you in remembrance, though ye once knew this, how that the Lord, having saved the people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed them that believed not.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">U weet het allemaal al, maar ik wil u er toch nog eens aan herinneren dat God Zijn hele volk uit het land Egypte heeft bevrijd; maar de mensen die Hem niet vertrouwden, heeft Hij gedood.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Želim vas podsjetiti, premda jednom zauvijek sve znate, kako je Gospodin izbavio narod iz Egipta, a zatim uništio nevjerne.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Przetoż chcę wam przypomnieć, którzy już raz o tem wiecie, że chociaż Pan lud z ziemi Egipskiej wyswobodził, przecież potem tych, którzy nie wierzyli, potracił.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ตัวอย่างของความชั่วร้ายที่ต้องรับการพิพากษาลงโทษถึงแม้ว่าท่านเคยรู้เรื่องเหล่านี้มาแล้วก็ตาม ข้าพเจ้าก็ยังปรารถนาให้ท่านทั้งหลายระลึกว่า องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าได้ทรงโปรดช่วยให้พลไพร่นั้นรอดจากแผ่นดินอียิปต์แล้ว ภายหลังพระองค์ได้ทรงทำลายคนเหล่านั้นที่ไม่เชื่อพระองค์เสีย</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ninanasa ko ngang ipaalaala sa inyo, bagama't nalalaman ninyong maigi ang lahat ng mga bagay, na nang mailigtas ng Panginoon ang isang bayan, sa lupain ng Egipto, ay nilipol niya pagkatapos yaong mga hindi nagsisipanampalataya. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた がた は みな 、 じゅうぶん に 知 っ て い る こと で は あ る が 、 主 が 民 を エジプト の 地 から 救い出し て 後 、 不信仰 な 者 を 滅ぼ さ れ た こと を 、 思い起 し て もら い た い 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിങ്ങളോ സകലവും ഒരിക്കല്‍ അറിഞ്ഞുവെങ്കിലും നിങ്ങളെ ഔര്‍പ്പിപ്പാന്‍ ഞാന്‍ ഇച്ഛിക്കുന്നതെന്തെന്നാല്‍കര്‍ത്താവു ജനത്തെ മിസ്രയീമില്‍നിന്നു രക്ഷിച്ചിട്ടും വിശ്വസിക്കാത്തവരെ പിന്നത്തേതില്‍ നശിപ്പിച്ചു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Vreau să vă aduc aminte, măcar că ştiţi odată pentru totdeauna toate aceste lucruri, că Domnul, după ce a izbăvit pe poporul Său din ţara Egiptului, în urmă a nimicit pe cei ce n'au crezut.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Ich will euch aber erinnern, die ihr dies ja schon wisset, daß der HERR, da er dem Volk aus Ägypten half, das andere Mal umbrachte, die da nicht glaubten.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men fastän I redan en gång haven fått kunskap om alltsammans, vill jag påminna eder därom, att Herren, sedan han hade frälst sitt folk ur Egyptens land, efteråt förgjorde dem som icke trodde,
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ตัวอย่าง ของ ความ ชั่ว ร้าย ที่ ต้อง รับ การ พิพากษา ลงโทษ ถึง แม้ ว่า ท่าน เคย รู้ เรื่อง เหล่า นี้ มา แล้ว ก็ตาม ข้าพเจ้า ก็ ยัง ปรารถนา ให้ท่า น ทั้งหลาย ระลึก ว่า องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ได้ ทรง โปรด ช่วย ให้ พล ไพร่ นั้น รอด จาก แผ่นดิน อี ยิปต์แล้ว ภายหลัง พระองค์ ได้ ทรง ทำลาย คน เหล่า นั้น ที่ ไม่ เชื่อ พระองค์ เสีย</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Aga ma tahan meelde tuletada teile, kes kõike juba olete korra teada saanud, et Issand, kui Ta rahva oli päästnud Egiptusest, teisel korral hukkas ära need, kes ei uskunud,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.6" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na, ko nga anahera, kihai nei i mau ki to ratou ake rohe, heoi whakarerea ana to ratou nohoanga ake, kua waiho e ia i raro i te pouri, mau tonu te here ki nga mekameka, mo te whakawa o te ra nui
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						còn các thiên sứ không giữ thứ bậc và bỏ chỗ riêng mình thì Ngài đã dùng dây xích họ trong nơi tối tăm đời đời, cầm giữ lại để chờ sự phán xét ngày lớn.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						qu`il a réservé pour le jugement du grand jour, enchaînés éternellement par les ténèbres, les anges qui n`ont pas gardé leur dignité, mais qui ont abandonné leur propre demeure;
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary ny anjely izay tsy nitana ny anjara-fanapahany, fa nandao ny fonenany, dia voahazony amin'ny fatorana mandrakizay ao amin'ny maizina ho amin'ny andro fitsarana lehibe.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						És az  angyalokat is, a kik nem tartották meg fejedelemségöket, hanem elhagyták az õ lakóhelyöket, a nagy nap ítéletére örök bilincseken, sötétségben tartotta.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Kananjalo izithunywa zezulu, ezo zazingalugcinanga ulawulo lwazo, zesuka zalishiya ikhaya lazo, izigcinele umgwebo womhla omkhulu ngemixokelelwane engunaphakade, phantsi kwesithokothoko.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">또 자기 지위를 지키지 아니하고 자기 처소를 떠난 천사들을 큰 날의 심판까지 영원한 결박으로 흑암에 가두셨으며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Taip pat ir tuos angelus, kurie neišlaikė savo prakilnumo, bet paliko savo buveinę, Jis laiko sukaustytus amžinais pančiais tamsybėje didžiosios dienos teismui.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						и ангелов, не сохранивших своего достоинства, но оставивших свое жилище, соблюдает в вечных узах, под мраком, на суд великого дня.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Ingatlah juga para malaikat yang melampaui batas-batas kekuasaan mereka, sehingga pergi meninggalkan tempat tinggal mereka. Allah membelenggu malaikat-malaikat itu dengan rantai abadi, di dalam tempat yang gelap di bawah bumi. Di sana mereka ditahan terus sampai hukuman dijatuhkan ke atas mereka pada Hari yang hebat itu nanti
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug ang mga manolunda nga wala managpabilin diha sa ilang nahimutangan hinonoa nanagpamiya sa ilang angay nga puloy-anan, kini sila iyang gikapahimutang diha sa mga talikala nga dayon ilalum sa kangitngit alang sa panudya unya sa dakung adlaw.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိုမှတပါး၊ မိမိတို့အခွင့်အရာကိုမစောင့်၊ မိမိတို့ နေရာအရပ်ကို စွန့်ပစ်သော ကောင်းကင်တမန်တို့ကို၊ ကြီးစွာသောနေ့၌ စစ်ကြောစီရင်ခြင်းအလိုငှါ၊ ထာဝရ ချည်နှောင်ခြင်းအားဖြင့် မှောင်မိုက် ထဲမှာချုပ် ထားတော် မူ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ninjultica ajcui' chêru nak cuan li ángel que'xtz'ektâna lix lok'al q'uebileb re jo' ajcui' lix na'ajeb. Anakcuan tz'aptz'ôqueb sa' li k'ojyîn xban li Dios ut bac'bôqueb riq'uin cadena toj tâcuulak xcutanquil li rakba âtin.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						a anjelov, ktorí nezachovali svojho kniežatstva, ale opustili svoj vlastný príbytok, zachoval strážených pod mrákavou vo večných putách k súdu veľkého dňa.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						अनि याद गर, ती स्वर्गदूतहरुलाई जो सित अधिकार थियो तर उहाँले राख्नु भएन। तिनीहरुले आफ्नै घर त्याग गरे। यसर्थ प्रभुले ती स्वर्गदूतहरुलाई अन्धकारमा राख्नु भयो। तिनीहरुलाई सदा रहिरहने बन्धनमा बाँध्नु भयो। उहाँले त्यो महान् दिनमा न्याय गर्न तिनीहरुलाई राख्नु भयो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I andjele koji ne držaše svoje starešinstvo nego ostaviše svoj stan čuva u večnim okovima pod mrakom za sud velikog dana.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						og om at de engler som ikke tok vare på sin høie stand, men forlot sin egen bolig, dem holder han i varetekt i evige lenker under mørket til dommen på den store dag; 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Yetkilerinin sınırı içinde kalmayıp kendilerine ayrılan yeri terk etmiş olan melekleri, büyük yargı günü için çözülmez bağlarla bağlayarak karanlığa hapsetti.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						والملائكة الذين لم يحفظوا رياستهم بل تركوا مسكنهم حفظهم الى دينونة اليوم العظيم بقيود ابدية تحت الظلام.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						aos anjos que não guardaram o seu principado, mas deixaram a sua própria habitação, ele os tem reservado em prisões eternas na escuridão para o juízo do grande dia,
					</lang><lang id="Latin">angelos vero qui non servaverunt suum principatum sed dereliquerunt suum domicilium in iudicium magni diei vinculis aeternis sub caligine reservavit</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Και αγγελους, οιτινες δεν εφυλαξαν την εαυτων αξιαν αλλα κατελιπον το ιδιον αυτων κατοικητηριον, εφυλαξε με παντοτεινα δεσμα υποκατω του σκοτους δια την κρισιν της μεγαλης ημερας
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En die engele wat hul eie beginsel nie bewaar het nie, maar hul eie woning verlaat het, het Hy vir die oordeel van die groot dag met ewige boeie onder die duisternis bewaar;
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Chonje tou ki jan zanj ki pa t' rete nan pozisyon Bondye te ba yo a men ki te kite kote l' te mete yo a, Bondye kenbe yo nan mitan fènwa a, mare nan yon chenn ki p'ap janm kase. Se la y'ap tann gwo jou jijman an
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						còn các thiên_sứ không giữ thứ_bậc và bỏ chỗ riêng mình thì Ngài đã dùng dây_xích họ trong nơi tối_tăm đời_đời , cầm_giữ lại để chờ sự phán_xét ngày lớn .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						והמלאכים אשר לא שמרו את משרתם כי אם עזבו את זבלם שמרם במוסרות עולם ובאפלה למשפט היום הגדול׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Angels who didn't keep their first domain, but deserted their own dwelling place, he has kept in everlasting bonds under darkness for the judgment of the great day.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మరియు తమ ప్రధానత్వమును నిలుపుకొనక, తమ నివాసస్థలమును విడిచిన దేవదూతలను, మహాదినమున జరుగు తీర్పువరకు కటికచీకటిలో నిత్యపాశములతో ఆయన బంధించి భద్రము చేసెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Тия са роптатели, оплаквачи, които ходят по страстите си, (и устата им говорят надуто), и заради печалба ласкаят човеците.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In angele, ki niso hranili poglavarstva svojega, temuč so zapustili lastno domovje, je shranil za sodbo velikega dneva z večnimi vezmi pod temo.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و فرشتگانی را که ریاست خود را حفظ نکردند بلکه مسکن حقیقی خود را ترک نمودند، در زنجیرهای ابدی درتحت ظلمت بجهت قصاص یوم عظیم نگاه داشته است.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						og de Engle, som ikke bevarede deres Højhed, men forlode deres egen Bolig, bar han holdt forvarede i evige Lænker under Mørke til den store Dags Dom;
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						ja että hän ne enkelit, jotka eivät säilyttäneet valta-asemaansa, vaan jättivät oman asumuksensa, pani pimeyteen iankaikkisissa kahleissa säilytettäviksi suuren päivän tuomioon;
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						又 有 不守 本位 、 離開 自己 住處 的 天使 、 主 用 鎖鍊 把 他 們永遠 拘留 在 黑暗裡 、 等候 大 日 的 審判
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Malaykey* mo kaŋ mana goro ngey boŋ mayra ra, amma i fay da ngey goray nango, Irikoy n'i gaay zaari beero ciito se hal abada sisiriyaŋ ra kubay ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						又 有 不 守 本 位 、 離 開 自 己 住 處 的 天 使 、 主 用 鎖 鍊 把 他 們 永 遠 拘 留 在 黑 暗 裡 、 等 候 大 日 的 審 判 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						फिर जो र्स्वगदूतों ने अपने पद को स्थिर न रखा वरन अपने निज निवास को छोड़ दिया, उस ने उन को भी उस भीषण दिन के न्याय के लिये अन्धकार में जो सदा काल के लिये है बन्धनों में रखा है।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						A ty anděly, kteříž neostříhali svého knížetství, ale opustili příbytek svůj, k soudu velikého toho dne vazbou věčnou pod mrákotou schoval.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj angxelojn, kiuj ne konservis sian regadon, sed forlasis sian propran logxejon, Li rezervis sub mallumo en katenoj cxiamaj gxis la jugxo en la granda tago.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						posi Sodoma dhe Gomora edhe qytetet përreth, që u dhanë pas kurvërimit dhe u dhanë pas çoroditjesh seksuale, janë vënë përpara si shembull, duke pësuar ndëshkimin e një zjarri të përjetshëm;
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						e che gli angeli che non conservarono la loro dignità ma lasciarono la propria dimora, egli li tiene in catene eterne, nelle tenebre, per il giudizio del gran giorno
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Og englana, sem ekki gættu tignar sinnar, heldur yfirgáfu eigin bústað, hefur hann í myrkri geymt í ævarandi fjötrum til dóms hins mikla dags. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तसेच ज्या देवदूतांनी आपली सार्वभौम सत्ता टिकवली नाही, परंतु आपली रहाण्याची जागा सोडून दिली, त्यांची देखील तुम्हाला आठवण करुन द्यायला पाहिजे. देवाने त्यांना सर्वकालच्या बंधनांनी जखडून काळोखात ठेवले यासाठी की शेवटच्या महान दिवशी त्यांचा न्याय करता यावा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						主は、自分たちの地位を守ろうとはせず、そのおるべき所を捨て去った御使たちを、大いなる日のさばきのために、永久にしばりつけたまま、暗やみの中に閉じ込めておかれた。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						También a los ángeles que no guardaron su primer estado sino que abandonaron su propia morada, los ha reservado bajo tinieblas en prisiones eternas para el juicio del gran día
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						oo malaa'igihii aan dhawrin madaxtinimadoodii, laakiinse rugtoodii ka tegey, wuxuu ilaa xukunka maalinta weyn ku hayaa silsilado weligood ah iyagoo gudcur ku hoos jira.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huan, angel te amau sawltak hihna jui loua, a omna ngeingei uh paisan zote tuh, ni thupi vaihawmnaa dinga mial nuaia khantawn henna hen kawmin a sit ahi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ತಮ್ಮ ಮೊದಲಿನ ಸ್ಥಿತಿಯನ್ನು ಕಾಪಾಡದೆ ತಮ್ಮ ಸ್ವಂತ ವಾಸಸ್ಥಾನವನ್ನು ಬಿಟ್ಟ ದೂತರಿಗೆ ಆತನು ನಿತ್ಯವಾದ ಬೇಡಿಗಳನ್ನು ಹಾಕಿ ಮಹಾ ದಿನದ ತೀರ್ಪಿಗಾಗಿ ಅವರನ್ನು ಕತ್ತಲೆ ಯೊಳಗೆ ಕಾದಿಟ್ಟಿದ್ದಾನೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And the angels which kept not their first estate, but left their own habitation, he hath reserved in everlasting chains under darkness unto the judgment of the great day.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Hij heeft engelen, die eerst met Hem over het heelal regeerden maar Hem ontrouw werden, gevangen gezet in de eeuwige duisternis; daar houdt Hij hen vast tot de dag van het grote oordeel.</lang><lang id="Croatian">I anđele, koji nisu čuvali svojeg dostojanstva nego su ostavili  svoje prebivalište, sačuvao je za sud velikoga Dana, okovane  u mraku vječnim okovima;</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Także Aniołów, którzy nie zachowali pierwszego stanu swego, ale opuścili mieszkanie swoje, na sąd dnia wielkiego związkami wiecznemi pod chmurą zachował.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">และเหล่าทูตสวรรค์ที่ไม่ได้รักษาเทวสภาพของตน แต่ได้ละทิ้งถิ่นฐานของตนนั้น พระองค์ก็ได้ทรงจองจำไว้ด้วยโซ่ตรวนอันเป็นนิรันดร์ ขังไว้ในที่มืดจนกว่าจะถึงการพิพากษาในวันสำคัญยิ่งนั้น</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang mga anghel na hindi nangagingat ng kanilang sariling pamunuan, kundi iniwan ang kanilang sariling tahanan, ay iniingatan niya sa mga tanikalang walang hanggan sa paghuhukom sa dakilang araw. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 主 は 、 自分 たち の 地位 を 守 ろ う と は せ ず 、 その お る べ き 所 を 捨て去 っ た 御 使 たち を 、 大いなる 日 の さばき の ため に 、 永久 に しばりつけ た まま 、 暗やみ の 中 に 閉じ込め て お か れ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						തങ്ങളുടെ വാഴ്ച കാത്തുകൊള്ളാതെ സ്വന്ത വാസസ്ഥലം വിട്ടുപോയ ദൂതന്മാരെ മഹാദിവസത്തിന്റെ വിധിക്കായി എന്നേക്കുമുള്ള ചങ്ങലയിട്ടു അന്ധകാരത്തിന്‍ കീഴില്‍ സൂക്ഷിച്ചിരിക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						El a păstrat pentru judecata zilei celei mari, puşi în lanţuri vecinice, în întunerec, pe îngerii cari nu şi-au păstrat vrednicia, ci şi-au părăsit locuinţa.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Auch die Engel, die ihr Fürstentum nicht bewahrten, sondern verließen ihre Behausung, hat er behalten zum Gericht des großen Tages mit ewigen Banden in der Finsternis.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						så ock därom, att de änglar som icke behöllo sin furstehöghet, utan övergåvo sin boning, hava av honom med eviga bojor blivit förvarade i mörker till den stora dagens dom.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">และ เหล่า ทูต สวรรค์ ที่ ไม่ ได้ รักษา เท ว สภาพ ของ ตน แต่ ได้ ละทิ้ง ถิ่น ฐาน ของ ตน นั้น พระองค์ ก็ได้ ทรง จองจำ ไว้ ด้วย โซ่ ตรวน อันเป็นนิรันดร์ ขัง ไว้ ใน ที่ มืด จนกว่า จะ ถึง การ พิพากษา ใน วัน สำคัญ ยิ่ง นั้น</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						ja et Tema Inglid, kes oma seisust ei hoidnud, vaid jätsid maha oma eluaseme, pani kinni igaveste ahelatega pilkase pimeduse alla suure päeva kohtuks;
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.7" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ka rite ki Horoma, ki Komora, ki nga pa hoki i tata ki reira, i pera me enei, te moepuku, te whai i nga kikokiko ke; kua waiho ratou hei tohu, pangia ana ratou e te whiu, ara e te ahi ka tonu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Lại như thành Sô-đôm và Gô-mô-rơ cùng các thành lân cận cũng buông theo sự dâm dục và sắc lạ, thì đã chịu hình phạt bằng lửa đời đời, làm gương để trước mặt chúng ta.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						que Sodome et Gomorrhe et les villes voisines, qui se livrèrent comme eux à l`impudicité et à des vices contre nature, sont données en exemple, subissant la peine d`un feu éternel.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary toy izany koa, Sodoma sy Gomora mbamin'ny tanàna nanodidina azy, izay nijangajanga tahaka azy koa ka lasa nanaraka nofo hafa, dia aseho ho fananarana amin'ny iaretany fijaliana amin'ny afo maharitra mandrakizay.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						képen Sodoma és Gomora és a körültök lévõ városok [is], a melyek azokhoz hasonlóan paráználkodtak, és más test után jártak, például vannak [elõttünk,] örök tûznek büntetését szenvedvén.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Njengokuba iSodom neGomora, nayo imizi engakuyo, yenza kakhulu umbulo ngohlobo olufana nolwazo ezo, imka ilandela nyama yimbi, ibekwe ekuhleni ukuba ibe ngumqondiso, iviswa ubetho lomlilo ongunaphakade.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">소돔과 고모라와 그 이웃 도시들도 저희와 같은 모양으로 간음을 행하며 다른 색을 따라 가다가 영원한 불의 형벌을 받음으로 거울이 되었느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Taip pat Sodoma ir Gomora bei aplinkiniai miestai, kurie panašiai ištvirkavo ir nusekė paskui ne tokį kūną, lieka pavyzdžiu, kentėdami amžinos ugnies bausmę.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Как Содом и Гоморра и окрестные города, подобно им блудодействовавшие и ходившие за иною плотию, подвергшись казни огня вечного, поставлены в пример, –
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Ingatlah juga kota Sodom dan Gomora serta kota-kota di sekitarnya, yang penduduknya melakukan hal-hal seperti yang dilakukan oleh malaikat-malaikat tersebut. Mereka melakukan hal-hal yang cabul dan bejat, sehingga mereka disiksa dengan hukuman api yang kekal, untuk dijadikan peringatan bagi semua orang
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Sa ingon usab ang Sodoma ug ang Gomorra ug ang silingang kalungsuran, nga sa samang paagi nanagpatuyang sa pagpakighilawas ug sa dili kinaiya nga kaulag, nahimo silang mga panig-ingnan pinaagi sa paghiagum sa silot sa kalayong dayon.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိုနည်းတူ၊ သောဒုံမြို့နှင့် ဂေါမောရမြို့မှစ၍ ပတ်ဝန်းကျင်၌ ရှိသော မြို့တို့သည်၊ အထက်က ဆိုခဲ့ပြီး သော လူဆိုးကဲ့သို့ မတရားသော မေထုန်ကိုအလွန်ပြု၍ ကိုယ်ခင်ပွန်းမဟုတ်သော သူတို့နှင့်မှားယွင်းခြင်းအမှု၌ ကျင်လည်သောကြောင့်၊ ထာဝရမီးနှင့်ကျွမ်းလောင်ခြင်း ဒဏ်ကိုခံရ၍ ပုံသက်သေထင်ရှားလျက်ရှိကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Jo'can ajcui' que'xc'ul li tenamit Sodoma ut Gomorra jo'queb ajcui' li tenamit cuanqueb chixc'atk. Juntak'êteb lix na'lebeb riq'uineb li ángel li que'mâcob. Que'muxuc caxâr ut que'mâcob ajcui' riq'uin rech cuînkilal ut riq'uin rech ixkilal. Que'xk'axtesi rib chixbânunquil chixjunil li mâusilal. Lix c'atic eb li tenamit a'an, a'an re xc'utbesinquil chiku nak cuan xtojbal rix li mâc. A'an li tâc'ulmânk mokon sa' li xam li tâcuânk chi junelic.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Jako Sodoma a Gomora a mestá okolo nich, ktoré podobným spôsobom ako títo neslýchane smilnily a odišly za iným telom, ležia pred očima na výstražný príklad a nesú trest večného ohňa.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						सदोम अनि गमोरा शहरहरु अनि वरिपरिका अन्य शहरहरुलाई स्मरण गर। तिनीहरु पनि ती स्वर्गदूतहरु जस्तै हुन्। ती शहरहरु व्यभिचार अनि अ-प्राकृतिक आनन्द मनाइरहेका थिए। तिनीहरुले अनन्त जलनको दण्ड भोग्छन्। तिनीहरुको दण्ड हाम्रो निम्ति उदाहरण हो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Kao što Sodom i Gomor, i okolni njihovi gradovi, koji su se prokurvali onako kao i oni, i hodili za drugim mesom, postaviše se ugled i muče se u večnom ognju:</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						likesom Sodoma og Gomorra og byene deromkring, som på samme måte som disse drev hor og gikk efter fremmed kjød, ligger for våre øine som et eksempel, idet de lider en evig ilds straff. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Sodom, Gomora ve çevrelerindeki kentler de benzer biçimde kendilerini fuhuş ve sapıklığa teslim ettiler. Sonsuza dek ateşte yanma cezasını çeken bu kentler ders alınacak birer örnektir.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						كما ان سدوم وعمورة والمدن التي حولهما اذ زنت على طريق مثلهما ومضت وراء جسد آخر جعلت عبرة مكابدة عقاب نار ابدية.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						assim como Sodoma e Gomorra, e as cidades circunvizinhas, que, havendo-se prostituído como aqueles anjos, e ido após outra carne, foram postas como exemplo, sofrendo a pena do fogo eterno.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">sicut Sodoma et Gomorra et finitimae civitates simili modo exfornicatae et abeuntes post carnem alteram factae sunt exemplum ignis aeterni poenam sustinentes</lang><lang id="Greek">
						καθως τα Σοδομα και τα Γομορρα και αι περιξ αυτων πολεις, εις την πορνειαν παραδοθεισαι κατα τον ομοιον με τουτους τροπον και ακολουθουσαι οπισω αλλης σαρκος, προκεινται παραδειγμα, τιμωρουμεναι με το αιωνιον πυρ.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 soos Sodom en Gomorra en die stede rondom hulle, wat op dieselfde manier as hierdie mense gehoereer en agter vreemde vlees aangeloop het, as 'n voorbeeld gestel is, terwyl hulle die straf van die ewige vuur ondergaan.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Menm jan an tou, chonje moun Sodòm ak Gomò ak tout ti bouk nan vwazinaj yo a. Yo te fè tankou zanj sa yo. Yo te lage kò yo nan tout kalite dezòd lachè, yo te menm rive nan fè gason ak gason, fi ak fi. Pou peni yo, yo lage yo nan dife k'ap boule tout tan an. Sa se yon egzanp ak yon avètisman pou tout moun
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Lại như thành Sô-đôm và Gô-mô-rơ cùng các thành lân_cận cũng buông theo sự dâm_dục và sắc lạ , thì đã chịu hình_phạt bằng lửa đời_đời , làm_gương để trước mặt chúng_ta .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						כאשר סדום ועמרה והערים סביבותיהן אשר הזנו כמוהם וילכו אחרי בשר זר נהיו כראי כי נמסרו למוסר אש עולם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Even as Sodom and Gomorrah, and the cities around them, having, in the same way as these, given themselves over to sexual immorality and gone after strange flesh, are set forth as an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఆ ప్రకారముగానే సొదొమ గొమొఱ్ఱాలును వాటి  చుట్టుపట్లనున్న  పట్టణ ములును  వీరివలెనే వ్యభిచారము చేయుచు, పరశరీరాను సారులైనందున నిత్యాగ్నిదండన అనుభవించుచు దృష్టాంత ముగా ఉంచబడెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Но, вие, възлюбени, помнете думите изговорени по-напред от апостолите на нашия Господ Исус Христос, как ви казваха:
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Kakor Sodoma in Gomora in mesta okoli njiju, ki so enako kakor oni nečistovala in hodila za drugim mesom, so postavljena za zgled, ker trpe kazen večnega ognja.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و همچنین سدوم و غموره و سایربلدان نواحی آنها مثل ایشان چونکه زناکار شدند و در‌پی بشر دیگر افتادند، در عقوبت آتش ابدی گرفتار شده، بجهت عبرت مقرر شدند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						ligesom Sodoma og Gomorra og de omliggende Stæder, der på samme Måde som disse vare henfaldne til Utugt og gik efter fremmed Kød), ere satte til et Eksempel, idet de bære en evig Ilds Straf.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						samoin kuin Sodoma ja Gomorra ja niiden ympärillä olevat kaupungit, jotka samalla tavalla kuin nekin harjoittivat haureutta ja eksyivät luonnottomiin lihanhimoihin, ovat varoittavana esimerkkinä, kärsiessään iankaikkisen tulen rangaistusta.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						又 如 所 多瑪 、 蛾摩拉 、 和 周圍 城邑 的 人 、 也照 他 們一味 的 行淫 、 隨從 逆 性 的 情慾 、 就 受 永火 的 刑罰 、 作為 鑑戒
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Wa fongu mo da Saduma* nda Gomorata* nda kwaarey kaŋ go i windanta. I na ngey boŋ no zina se ka ceeci mo ngey ma kani nda boroyaŋ kaŋ mana hima nd'a, danga mate kaŋ cine malaykey din te. Irikoy n'i ciiti nda hal abada danjo ciito k'i ciya deedandiyaŋ hari. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						又 如 所 多 瑪 、 蛾 摩 拉 、 和 周 圍 城 邑 的 人 、 也 照 他 們 一 味 的 行 淫 、 隨 從 逆 性 的 情 慾 、 就 受 永 火 的 刑 罰 、 作 為 鑑 戒 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						जिस रीति से सदोम और अमोरा और उन के आस पास के नगर, जो इन की नाई व्यभिचारी हो गए थे और पराये शरीर के पीछे लग गए थे आग के अनन्त दण्ड में पड़कर दृष्टान्त ठहरे हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Jako Sodoma a Gomora, a okolní města, když podobným způsobem, jako i tito, v smilstvo se vydali a odešli po těle cizím, předložena jsou za příklad, pokutu věčného ohně snášejíce.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kiel ankaux Sodom kaj Gomora kaj la cxirkauxaj urboj tiel same, kiel cxi tiuj, malcxastigxinte kaj foririnte post fremdan karnon, estas elmontritaj kiel ekzemplo, suferante la punon de eterna fajro.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						në të njëjtën menyrë ndotin edhe këta ëndërrues mishin, përbuzin pushtetin dhe blasfemojnë kundër dinjiteteve.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Così Sòdoma e Gomorra e le città vicine, che si sono abbandonate all'impudicizia allo stesso modo e sono andate dietro a vizi contro natura, stanno come esempio subendo le pene di un fuoco eterno
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Eins og Sódóma og Gómorra og borgirnar umhverfis þær, sem drýgt höfðu saurlifnað á líkan hátt og þeir og stunduðu óleyfilegar lystisemdir, þær liggja fyrir sem dæmi, líðandi hegningu eilífs elds. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						त्याचप्रमाणे, या देवदूतांसारखीच सदोम व गमोरा आणि त्या शहराच्या आसपासच्या नगरांनी लैंगिक अनीतीचे आचरण केले आणि अस्वभाविक लैंगिक संबधाच्या मागे ती लागली. अनंतकाळच्या अग्निच्या शिक्षेसाठी ती राखून ठेवली आहेत. एक उदाहरण म्हणून ती आपल्यासमोर ठेवली आहेत.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						ソドム、ゴモラも、まわりの町々も、同様であって、同じように淫行にふけり、不自然な肉欲に走ったので、永遠の火の刑罰を受け、人々の見せしめにされている。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Asimismo, Sodoma, Gomorra y las ciudades vecinas, que de la misma manera fornicaron y fueron tras vicios contra lo natural, son puestas por ejemplo, sufriendo la pena del fuego eterno
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Si la mid ah Sodom iyo Gomora iyo magaalooyinkii kale ee ku wareegsanaa oo sinaystay oo jidh kale uga daba orday, ayaa masaal laga dhigay, iyagoo ciqaabta dabka weligiis ah ku silcaya.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Sodom leh Gomorra, a kiang kim ua khuate toh, huchibangmaha kingaihnaa kipumpiaka, gitlouhna leklua a delh sam tak jiak un, khantawna meia gawtna thuaka, theihsakna dinga suankhiaka a om bang un.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಸೊದೋಮ ಗೊಮೋರ ದವರೂ ಹಾಗೆಯೇ ಅವುಗಳ ಸುತ್ತುಮುತ್ತಣ ಪಟ್ಟಣಗಳವರೂ ಅದೇ ರೀತಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ತಮ್ಮನ್ನು ಜಾರತ್ವಕ್ಕೆ ಒಪ್ಪಿಸಿಬಿಟ್ಟು ಅನ್ಯ ಶರೀರವನ್ನು ಅನುಸರಿಸಿದ್ದರಿಂದ ಅವರು ನಿತ್ಯವಾದ ಅಗ್ನಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಪ್ರತಿದಂಡನೆಯನ್ನು ಅನುಭವಿಸುತ್ತಾ ಉದಾಹರಣೆಗಾಗಿ ಇಡಲ್ಪಟ್ಟಿದ್ದಾರೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Even as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities about them in like manner, giving themselves over to fornication, and going after strange flesh, are set forth for an example, suffering the vengeance of eternal fire.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">En denk eens aan Sodom en Gomorra en de steden daar in de buurt. Hun inwoners werden ook ontrouw en gingen zich aan allerlei onnatuurlijke praktijken te buiten. De steden en hun inwoners werden door het vuur vernietigd. Door de straf die zij kregen, zijn zij een blijvende waarschuwing voor ons.</lang><lang id="Croatian">kao Sodoma i Gomora i okolni gradovi, koji su se poput njih podali bludu i otišli za drugom pÓuti, stoje za primjer, ispaštajući kaznu u vječnom ognju.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Jako Sodoma i Gomorra, i okoliczne miasta, gdy tymże sposobem jako i one zwszeteczniały i udały się za cudzem ciałem, wystawione są na przykład, ognia wiecznego karanie ponosząc:
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เช่นเดียวกับเมืองโสโดมและเมืองโกโมราห์และเมืองที่อยู่รอบๆนั้นที่ได้หลงตัวไปกับการผิดประเวณี และมัวเมาในกามวิตถาร ก็ได้ทรงบัญญัติไว้เป็นตัวอย่างของการที่จะต้องได้รับพระอาชญาในไฟนิรันดร์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Gayon din ang Sodoma at Gomorra, at ang mga bayang nasa palibot ng mga ito, na dahil sa pagpapakabuyo sa pakikiapid at sa pagsunod sa ibang laman, ay inilagay na pinakahalimbawa, na sila'y nagbabata ng parusang apoy na walang hanggan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 ソドム 、 ゴモラ も 、 まわり の 町々 も 、 同様 で あ っ て 、 同じ よう に 淫行 に ふけ り 、 不 自然 な 肉欲 に 走 っ た の で 、 永遠 の 火 の 刑罰 を 受け 、 人々 の 見せしめ に さ れ て い る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അതുപോലെ സൊദോമും ഗൊമോരയും ചുറ്റുമുള്ള പട്ടണങ്ങളും അവര്‍ക്കും സമമായി ദുര്‍ന്നടപ്പു ആചരിച്ചു അന്യജഡം മോഹിച്ചു നടന്നതിനാല്‍ നിത്യാഗ്നിയുടെ ശിക്ഷാവിധി സഹിച്ചുകൊണ്ടു ദൃഷ്ടാന്തമായി കിടക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Tot aşa, Sodoma şi Gomora şi cetăţile dimprejurul lor, cari se dăduseră ca şi ele la curvie şi au poftit după trupul altuia, ne stau înainte ca o pildă, suferind pedeapsa unui foc vecinic.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Wie auch Sodom und Gomorra und die umliegenden Städte, die gleicherweise wie diese Unzucht getrieben haben und nach einem andern Fleisch gegangen sind, zum Beispiel gesetzt sind und leiden des ewigen Feuers Pein.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Likaså hava ock Sodom och Gomorra med kringliggande städer, vilka på samma sätt som de förra bedrevo otukt och stodo efter annat umgänge än det naturliga, blivit satta till ett varnande exempel, i det att de få lida straff i evig eld.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เช่น เดียว กับ เมือง โสโดมและ เมือง โกโมราห์และ เมือง ที่ อยู่ รอบ ๆ นั้น ที่ ได้ หลง ตัว ไป กับ การ ผิด ประเวณี และ มัวเมา ใน กามวิตถาร ก็ได้ ทรง บัญญัติ ไว้ เป็น ตัวอย่าง ของ การ ที่ จะ ต้อง ได้ รับ พระ อาชญา ใน ไฟนิรันดร์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						nagu Soodoma ja Gomorra ja nende ümberkaudsed linnad, kes samal kombel kui needki elasid porduelu ja ajasid taga teist liha, on hoiatavaks näiteks, kannatades igavese tule nuhtlust.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.8" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko ta tenei hunga moemoea ano hoki tena; e whakapoke ana i te kikokiko, e whakahawea ana ki te kawanatanga, e korero kino ana ki nga rangatira
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nhưng mà chúng nó cũng như vậy, trong giấc mơ màng làm ô uế xác thịt mình, khinh dể quyền phép rất cao và nói hỗn các đấng tôn trọng.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Malgré cela, ces hommes aussi, entraînés par leurs rêveries, souillent pareillement leur chair, méprisent l`autorité et injurient les gloires.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Kanefa toy izany koa, ireo dia manonofy ka mandoto ny nofo sady mandà ny manana fahalehibiazana ary miteny ratsy ny manana voninahitra. [ Gr. manao blasfemia; izahao Mat. IX 3]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Hasonlóképen mégis ezek is álomba merülvén, a testet  megfertõztetik, a hatalmasságot megvetik, és a méltóságokat káromolják.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Kwangokunjalo nabo aba baphuphayo badyobha inyama,  batshitshise ubukhosi, banyelise izikhakhamela.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">그러한데 꿈꾸는 이 사람들도 그와 같이 육체를 더럽히며 권위를 업신여기며 영광을 훼방하는도다</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Taip ir šitie sapnuotojai suteršia kūną, niekina viešpatystę, piktžodžiauja šlovingiesiems.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						так точно будет и с сими мечтателями,которые оскверняют плоть, отвергают начальства и злословят высокие власти.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Demikian juga oknum-oknum itu berkhayal-khayal sampai mereka berbuat dosa terhadap badan mereka sendiri. Mereka memandang rendah kekuasaan Allah dan menghina para makhluk yang mulia di surga
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 Ngani, bisan pa niini, sa ingon nga paagi kining mga tawhana sa ilang mga pagdamgo nanaghugawhugaw sa lawas, nanagsalikway sa kagamhanan, ug nagapasipala sa mga halangdon.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ယခုယောင်ယမ်းသောအဓမ္မလူတို့သည်၊ ရှေးနည်းတူမိမိတို့ ကိုယ်ကိုညစ်ညူးစေ၍၊ အာဏာစက် ကိုပယ်လျက်၊ ဘုန်းတန်ခိုးကြီးသောသူတို့ကို ကဲ့ရဲ့တတ်ကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Usta nanauman li c'a'ru quixc'ul li tenamit Sodoma ut Gomorra, abanan toj cuanqueb ajcui' aj balak' li neque'xpâb li yal yo'obanbil na'leb. Ut neque'xtz'ajni rib riq'uin li mâc. Neque'xtz'ektâna lix cuanquil li Kâcua' ut neque'xmajecua li cuanqueb xcuanquil ut li cuanqueb xlok'al.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Podobne však aj títo, pohrúžení v spánok, telo poškvrňujú, panstvom pohŕdajú a slávam sa rúhajú.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						ती तिमीहरुका दलमा पस्ने मानिसहरु पनि त्यही अनुसरण गर्छन्। तिनीहरुलाई तिनीहरुको सपनाले डोर्याएको छ अनि तिनीहरुले स्वयंलाई अनैतिक पारेका छन्। तिनीहरु आफैलाई अनैतिक बनाउँछन्। तिनीहरु परमेश्वरलाई अस्वीकार गर्छन् अनि महिमामय स्वर्गदूतहरुको निन्दा गर्छन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Tako dakle i ovi što sanjajući telo pogane, a poglavarstva se odriču, i na slavu hule.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Og dog gjør også disse like ens: idet de går i drømme, gjør de kjødet urent, ringeakter herredømme, spotter høie makter. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Aranıza sızan bu kişiler de onlar gibi gördükleri düşlere dayanarak öz bedenlerini kirletiyor, Rabbin yetkisini hiçe sayıyor, yüce varlıklara sövüyorlar.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ولكن كذلك هؤلاء ايضا المحتلمون ينجسون الجسد ويتهاونون بالسيادة ويفترون على ذوي الامجاد.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Contudo, semelhantemente também estes falsos mestres, sonhando, contaminam a sua carne, rejeitam toda autoridade e blasfemam das dignidades.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">similiter et hii carnem quidem maculant dominationem autem spernunt maiestates autem blasphemant</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ομοιως και ουτοι ενυπνιαζομενοι την μεν σαρκα μιαινουσι, την δε εξουσιαν καταφρονουσι και τα αξιωματα βλασφημουσιν.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Tog besoedel ook hierdie mense net so in hulle dromerye die vlees en verag die heerskappy en laster die heerlike wesens.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Menm jan an tou, mesye sa yo, avèk tout vizyon y'ap plede fè yo, y'ap fè tout kalite vye bagay ak kò yo, y'ap meprize otorite Bondye, y'ap pale pouvwa ki nan syèl yo mal
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nhưng_mà chúng_nó cũng như_vậy , trong giấc mơ_màng làm ô_uế xác_thịt mình , khinh_dể quyền phép rất cao và nói hỗn các đấng tôn_trọng .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						וכן גם בעלי החלמות האלה מטמאים את הבשר ואת הממשלה ינאצו ואת השררות יחרפו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Yet in the same way, these also in their dreaming defile the flesh, despise authority, and slander celestial beings.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అటువలెనే వీరును కలలు కనుచు, శరీరమును అపవిత్రపరచుకొనుచు, ప్రభుత్వమును నిరాక రించుచు, మహాత్ములను దూషించుచు ఉన్నారు. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						В последно време ще има присмивачи, които ще ходят по своите нечестиви страсти.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Enako torej tudi ti, praznim sanjam se vdajajoč, oskrunjajo meso, zaničujejo gospostvo, preklinjajo veličanstva.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						لیکن باوجود این، همه این خواب بینندگان نیز جسد خود را نجس می‌سازند و خداوندی راخوار می‌شمارند و بر بزرگان تهمت می‌زنند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Alligevel gå også disse ligedan i Drømme og besmitte Kød, foragte Herskab og bespotte Herligheder.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Yhtäkaikki nämä uneksijat samoin saastuttavat lihan; he halveksivat herrautta, herjaavat kirkkauden henkiolentoja.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						這些 作夢 的 人 、 也像 他 們污穢 身體 、 輕慢 主治 的 、 毀謗 在 尊位 的
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Yaadin cine mo no hindirikoy din goono ga ngey gaahamey ziibandi. I goono ga _Irikoy|_ mayra ciya yaamo ka beena beeraykoyey wow. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						這 些 作 夢 的 人 、 也 像 他 們 污 穢 身 體 、 輕 慢 主 治 的 、 毀 謗 在 尊 位 的 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						उसी रीति से ये स्वप्नदर्शी भी अपने अपने शरीर को अशुद्ध करते, और प्रभुता को तुच्छ जानते हैं; और ऊंचे पदवालों को बुरा भला कहते हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Takéž podobně i tito, jako v hluboký sen pohřižení, tělo zajisté poskvrňují, panstvím pak pohrdají a důstojnosti se rouhají;
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Tamen tiel same ankaux cxi tiuj en siaj songxadoj malpurigas la karnon,  malestimas auxtoritaton, kaj insultas honorojn.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Por kryeengjëlli Mikael, kur në kundërshtim me djallin debatonte për trupin e Moisiut, nuk guxoi të shqiptojë një gjykim fyes, por tha: ''Zoti të qortoftë!''.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ugualmente, anche costoro, come sotto la spinta dei loro sogni, contaminano il proprio corpo, disprezzano il Signore e insultano gli esseri gloriosi
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Á sama hátt saurga og þessir draumvilltu menn líkamann, meta að engu drottinvald og lastmæla tignum. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						अगदी तशाच प्रकारे, हे लोक जे तुमच्या गटात आले ते स्वप्नांनी बहकले व त्यांनी आपली शरीरे विटाळली आहेत. ते प्रभूचा अधिकार बाजूला ठेवतात व ते गौरवी थोरामोठ्यांविरुद्ध (देवदूतांविरुद्ध) निंदानालस्तीची भाषा वापरतात.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						しかし、これと同じように、これらの人々は、夢に迷わされて肉を汚し、権威ある者たちを軽んじ、栄光ある者たちをそしっている。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						De la misma manera, también estos soñadores mancillan la carne, rechazan toda autoridad y maldicen las potestades superiores
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Weliba kuwan riyooda sidaas oo kalay jidhkooda u nijaaseeyaan, sayidnimadana u nacaan, oo kuwa derejada leh u caayaan.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Himahleh, huaiten leng, huchi bang mahin, a deihthusam bang un sa tuh a hihthanghuai ua, vaihawm sakna a musit ua, thupinate a gense nak uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಹಾಗೆಯೇ ಈ ದುಸ್ವಪ್ನದವರು ಶರೀರವನ್ನು ಮಲಿನ ಮಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವವರೂ ಪ್ರಭುತ್ವವನ್ನು ಅಸಡ್ಡೆ ಮಾಡು ವವರೂ ಗೌರವವುಳ್ಳವರನ್ನು ದೂಷಿಸುವವರೂ ಆಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Likewise also these filthy dreamers defile the flesh, despise dominion, and speak evil of dignities.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Maar de mensen over wie ik net sprak, trekken zich daar niets van aan. Zij laten hun fantasie de vrije loop en doen schandalige dingen met hun lichaam. Zij aanvaarden geen enkel gezag en spotten met de hemelse machten.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Uza sve to i ovi sanjari jednako skvrne tijelo, zabacuju  Veličanstvo, pogrđuju Slave.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Także też i ci jako snem zmożeni ciało plugawią, ale zwierzchnością pogardzają i przełożeóstwa bluźnią.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ผู้สอนเทียมเท็จเช่นเดียวกัน คนเพ้อฝันแต่เรื่องสกปรกโสโครกเหล่านี้ได้กระทำให้เนื้อหนังเป็นมลทิน ดูหมิ่นผู้มีอำนาจ และพูดจาให้ร้ายต่อผู้มีบรรดาศักดิ์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Gayon ma'y ang mga ito rin naman sa kanilang pagkagupiling ay inihahawa ang laman, at hinahamak ang mga paghahari, at nilalait ang mga puno. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 しかし 、 これ と 同じ よう に 、 これ ら の 人々 は 、 夢 に 迷わ さ れ て 肉 を 汚 し 、 権威 あ る 者 たち を 軽ん じ 、 栄光 あ る 者 たち を そし っ て い る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അങ്ങനെ തന്നേ ഇവരും സ്വപ്നാവസ്ഥയിലായി ജഡത്തെ മലിനമാക്കുകയും കര്‍ത്തൃത്വത്തെ തുച്ഛീകരിക്കുകയും മഹിമകളെ ദുഷിക്കയും ചെയ്യുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Totuş oamenii aceştia, tîrîţi de visările lor, îşi pîngăresc la fel trupul, nesocotesc stăpînirea şi batjocoresc dregătoriile.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Desgleichen sind auch diese Träumer, die das Fleisch beflecken, die Herrschaft aber verachten und die Majestäten lästern.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Dock göra nu också dessa människor på samma sätt, förblindade av sina drömmar: köttet besmitta de, men andevärldens herrar förakta de, och dess härlige smäda de.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ผู้ สอน เทียม เท็จ เช่น เดียวกัน คน เพ้อ ฝัน แต่ เรื่อง สกปรก โสโครก เหล่า นี้ ได้ กระทำ ให้ เนื้อ หนัง เป็น มลทิน ดูหมิ่น ผู้ มี อำนาจ และ พูด จา ให้ร้าย ต่อ ผู้ มี บรรดาศักดิ์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Nõndasamuti rüvetavad needki unenägijad oma liha, põlgavad Issanda valitsust, pilkavad aukandjaid vaime.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.9" langNo="59"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko Mikaera ia, ko te tino anahera, i ta raua ngangautanga ko te rewera, i a ia e tohe ana ki te tinana o Mohi, kihai i tae tona aro ki te kupu kanga i te whakawakanga; i mea kau ia, Ma te Ariki koe e riri
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Vả, khi chính mình thiên sứ trưởng Mi-chen chống với ma quỉ giành xác Môi-se, còn chẳng dám lấy lời nhiếc móc mà đoán phạt; người chỉ nói rằng: Cầu Chúa phạt ngươi!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Or, l`archange Michel, lorsqu`il contestait avec le diable et lui disputait le corps de Moïse, n`osa pas porter contre lui un jugement injurieux, mais il dit: Que le Seigneur te réprime!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa Mikaela arikanjely aza, raha niady tamin'ny devoly ka nifanditra ny amin'ny fatin'i Mosesy, dia tsy sahy niteny ratsy hahameloka azy, fa hoy izy: "Hananatra anao anie Jehovah".
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Pedig  Mihály arkangyal, mikor az ördöggel vitatkozván  Mózes teste felett vetélkedett, nem mert arra káromló ítéletet mondani, hanem azt mondá: Dorgáljon  meg téged az Úr!
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Kanti yena uMikayeli, isiphatha-zithunywa zezulu, oko wayebambene naye uMtyholi, bebangisana ngawo umzimba kaMoses,  akabanga nabuganga bakumzisela mgwebo wakunyelisa; wesuka wathi, INkosi mayikukhalimele.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">천사장 미가엘이 모세의 시체에 대하여 마귀와 다투어 변론할 때에 감히 훼방하는 판결을 쓰지 못하고 다만 말하되 주께서 너를 꾸짖으시기를 원하노라 하였거늘</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Kai arkangelas Mykolas, besiginčydamas su velniu, varžėsi dėl Mozės kūno, jis neišdrįso mesti piktžodiško kaltinimo, bet pasakė: “Tesudraudžia tave Viešpats!”
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Михаил Архангел, когда говорил с диаволом, споря о Моисеевом теле, не смел произнести укоризненного суда, но сказал: „да запретит тебе Господь".
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Mikhael sendiri, yang mengepalai malaikat-malaikat, tidak pernah berbuat seperti itu. Pada waktu ia bertengkar dengan Iblis dalam perselisihan tentang siapa yang akan mendapat mayat Musa, Mikhael tidak berani menghakimi Iblis dengan kata-kata penghinaan. Mikhael hanya berkata, "Tuhan akan membentak engkau!
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Apan si Miguel, ang manolunda nga punoan, sa iyang pakiglantugi batok sa yawa sa ilang panag-ilog sa lawas ni Moises, wala gani siya mangahas sa paglitok ug mapasipalahong hukom batok kaniya, kondili miingon lamang, "Ang Ginoo magabadlong unta kanimo."
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ကောင်းကင်တမန် မင်းမိက္ခေလမူကား၊ မောရှေ၏ ကိုယ်ကို အကြောင်းပြု၍ မာရ်နတ်နှင့် ငြင်းခုံသောအခါ၊ ကဲ့ရဲ့စွာသော ပြစ်တင်ခြင်းကိုမပြုဝံ့ဘဲ၊ ထာဝရဘုရားသည် သင့်ကိုဆုံးမတော်မူစေ သတည်းဟူ၍ သာပြောဆို၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ut li ángel Miguel, li k'axal nim xlok'al, inc'a' quixq'ue rib chok' aj rakol âtin sa' xbên laj tza. Nak li ángel que'xcuech'i rib riq'uin laj tza chirix lix tz'ejcual laj Moisés, li ángel inc'a' quixhob chi moco quiraj xrakbal âtin sa' xbên. Quixye ban re: Li Kâcua' Dios chik'usuk âcue, chan.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A archanjel Michal, keď v spore s diablom hovoril o telo Mojžišovo, neopovážil sa vyniesť proti nemu rúhavý súd, ale povedal: Nech ťa potresce Pán!
					</lang><lang id="Nepali"></lang><lang id="Serbian">A Mihailo Arhandjel, kad se prepiraše s djavolom i govoraše za Mojsijevo telo, ne smeše prokleti sud da izgovori, nego reče: Gospod neka ti zapreti.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Overengelen Mikael vågde dog ikke å uttale en spottende dom dengang han trettet med djevelen om Mose legeme, men sa: Herren refse dig! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Oysa Başmelek Mikail bile Musanın cesedi konusunda İblisle çekişip tartışırken, söverek onu yargılamaya kalkışmadı. Ancak, ‹‹Seni Rab azarlasın›› dedi.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						واما ميخائيل رئيس الملائكة فلما خاصم ابليس محاجا عن جسد موسى لم يجسر ان يورد حكم افتراء بل قال لينتهرك الرب.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Mas quando o arcanjo Miguel, discutindo com o Diabo, disputava a respeito do corpo de Moisés, não ousou pronunciar contra ele juízo de maldição, mas disse: O Senhor te repreenda
					</lang><lang id="Latin">cum Michahel archangelus cum diabolo disputans altercaretur de Mosi corpore non est ausus iudicium inferre blasphemiae sed dixit imperet tibi Dominus</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ο δε Μιχαηλ ο αρχαγγελος, οτε αγωνιζομενος με τον διαβολον εφιλονεικει περι του σωματος του Μωυσεως, δεν ετολμησε να επιφερη εναντιον αυτου κατηγοριαν βλασφημον, αλλ' ειπεν Ο Κυριος να σε επιτιμηση.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar toe Mígael, die aartsengel, met die duiwel in woordestryd was oor die liggaam van Moses, het hy geen oordeel van lastering durf uitspreek nie, maar het gesê: Die Here bestraf jou!
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Menm Akanj Michèl, lè li t'ap plede ak dyab la pou kadav Moyiz, li pa t' penmèt li jije dyab la yon jan pou l' te manke l' dega. Men, li annik di li: Mèt la va regle avè ou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Vả , khi chính mình thiên_sứ trưởng Mi-chen chống với ma_quỉ giành xác Môi-se , còn chẳng dám lấy lời nhiếc_móc mà đoán phạt ; người chỉ nói rằng : Cầu_Chúa phạt ngươi !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ומיכאל שר המלאכים בהתוכחו עם השטן וירב אתו על אדות גוית משה לא מלאו לבו לחרץ משפט גדופים כי אם אמר יגער יהוה בך׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But Michael, the archangel, when contending with the devil and arguing about the body of Moses, dared not bring against him an abusive condemnation, but said, "May the Lord rebuke you!"</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అయితే ప్రధానదూతయైన మిఖాయేలు అపవాదితో వాదించుచు  మోషేయొక్క  శరీరమునుగూర్చి తర్కించి నప్పుడు, దూషించి తీర్పుతీర్చ తెగింపకప్రభువు నిన్ను గద్దించును గాక అనెను. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Тия са, които правят разцепления, плътски, които нямат Духа.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Mihael pa, nadangel, ko se je s hudičem prepiral in prerekal o truplu Mojzesovem, si ni upal izreči sodbe preklinjevanja, marveč je rekel: Kaznuj te Gospod!
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						امامیکائیل، رئیس ملائکه، چون درباره جسدموسی با ابلیس منازعه می‌کرد، جرات ننمود که حکم افترا بر او بزند بلکه گفت: «خداوند تو راتوبیخ فرماید.»
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Men Overengelen Mikael turde, da han tvistedes med Djævelen og talte om Mose Legeme, ikke fremføre en Bespottelsesdom, men sagde: "Herren straffe dig!"
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta ei ylienkeli Miikaelkaan, kun riiteli ja väitteli perkeleen kanssa Mooseksen ruumiista, rohjennut lausua herjaavaa tuomiota, vaan sanoi: "Rangaiskoon sinua Herra!"
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						天使 長米迦勒 、 為摩西 的 屍首 與 魔鬼 爭辯 的 時候 、 尚且 不 敢 用 毀謗 的 話罪 責他 、 只說 、 主責備 你 罷
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Amma Munkayla kaŋ ti malaykey jine bora, waato kaŋ a goono ga yanje nda Iblisi ka kakaw Musa gaahamo boŋ, a mana farrati ka kande wowi ciiti a boŋ. Amma a ne: «Rabbi ma deeni ni gaa!» 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						天 使 長 米 迦 勒 、 為 摩 西 的 屍 首 與 魔 鬼 爭 辯 的 時 候 、 尚 且 不 敢 用 毀 謗 的 話 罪 責 他 、 只 說 、 主 責 備 你 罷 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						परन्तु प्रधान स्वर्गदूत मीकाईल ने, जब शैतान से मूसा की लोथ के विषय में वाद- विवाद करता था, तो उस को बुरा भला कहके दोष लगाने का साहस न किया; पर यह कहा, कि प्रभु तुझे डांटे।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Ješto Michal archanděl, když s ďáblem odpor maje, hádal se o tělo Mojžíšovo, neodvážil se proti němu vynésti soudu zlořečení, ale řekl: Ztresciž tě Pán.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed Mihxael, la cxefangxelo, kiam en kontrauxstaro al la diablo li disputis pri la korpo de Moseo, ne kuragxis lin akuzi insulte, sed diris:La Sinjoro vin riprocxu.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Kurse këta flasin keq për të gjitha gjërat që nuk i dinë, dhe për të gjitha gjërat që njohin në menyrë natyrale, si kafshë pa arësye, në këto gjëra prishin veten,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						L'arcangelo Michele quando, in contesa con il diavolo, disputava per il corpo di Mosè, non osò accusarlo con parole offensive, ma disse: Ti condanni il Signore
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Eigi dirfðist einu sinni höfuðengillinn Míkael að leggja lastmælisdóm á djöfulinn, er hann átti í orðadeilu við hann um líkama Móse, heldur sagði: "Drottinn refsi þér!" 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi"></lang><lang id="Japanese">
						御使のかしらミカエルは、モーセの死体について悪魔と論じ争った時、相手をののしりさばくことはあえてせず、ただ、「主がおまえを戒めて下さるように」と言っただけであった。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Pero ni aun el arcángel Miguel, cuando contendía disputando con el diablo sobre el cuerpo de Moisés, se atrevió a pronunciar un juicio de maldición contra él, sino que dijo: "El Señor te reprenda.
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiin Mikaa'iil oo ah malagga sare markuu Ibliiska kula murmayay meydkii Muuse aawadiis, kuma uu dhicin inuu xukun cay ah ku xukumo, laakiinse wuxuu ku yidhi, Rabbigu ha ku canaanto.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Himahleh, Mikael angel tungunngpenin bawn, diabol toh a kisel ua, Mosi luang thua a kinak lai un a tungthu gen sakin amah a gense ngam kei hi, Toupan hontai jaw hen, a chi zota hi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಆದರೂ ಪ್ರಧಾನ ದೇವದೂತನಾದ ಮಿಕಾಯೇಲನು ಮೋಶೆಯ ಶವದ ವಿಷಯದಲ್ಲಿ ಸೈತಾನನೊಂದಿಗೆ ವ್ಯಾಜ್ಯವಾಡಿ ವಾಗ್ವಾದ ಮಾಡಿದಾಗ ಅವನು ಸೈತಾನನನ್ನು ದೂಷಿಸುವದಕ್ಕೆ ಧೈರ್ಯ ಗೊಳ್ಳದೆ--ಕರ್ತನು ನಿನ್ನನ್ನು ಗದರಿಸಲಿ ಅಂದನು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Yet Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing accusation, but said, The Lord rebuke thee.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Wat een verschil met Michaël, één van de voornaamste engelen! (A) Toen die met de duivel streed om het lichaam van Mozes, durfde hij de duivel niet te veroordelen of te beledigen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Kad se Mihael arkanđeo s đavlom  prepirao za tijelo Mojsijevo, nije se usudio izreći pogrdan sud  protiv njega, nego reče: "Spriječio te Gospodin!"</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Lecz Michał Archanioł, gdy się z dyjabłem rozpierając wadził o ciało Mojżeszowe, nie śmiał podnieść przeciwko niemu sądu bluźnierczego, ale rzekł: Niech cię Pan zgromi.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ฝ่ายอัครเทวทูตาธิบดีมีคาเอล ครั้นเมื่อท่านโต้เถียงกับพญามารเรื่องศพของโมเสส ท่านเองก็ยังไม่บังอาจตั้งข้อกล่าวหาอย่างเย้ยหยันต่อมารเลย ได้แต่เพียงกล่าวว่า "ขอให้องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าทรงห้ามเจ้าเถิด"</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Datapuwa't ang arkanghel Miguel, nang makipaglaban sa diablo, na nakikipagtalo tungkol sa katawan ni Moises, ay hindi nangahas gumamit laban sa kaniya ng isang hatol na may pagalipusta, kundi sinabi, Sawayin ka nawa ng Panginoon. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
					 	 御 使 の かしら ミカエル は 、 モーセ の 死体 に つ い て 悪魔 と 論 じ 争 っ た 時 、 相手 を ののしり さば く こと は あえて せ ず 、 ただ 、 「 主 が おまえ を 戒め て 下さ る よう に 」 と 言 っ た だけ で あ っ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						എന്നാല്‍ പ്രധാനദൂതനായ മിഖായേല്‍ മോശെയുടെ ശരീരത്തെക്കുറിച്ചു പിശാചിനോടു തര്‍ക്കിച്ചു വാദിക്കുമ്പോള്‍ ഒരു ദൂഷണവിധി ഉച്ചരിപ്പാന്‍ തുനിയാതെകര്‍ത്താവു നിന്നെ ഭര്‍ത്സിക്കട്ടെ എന്നു പറഞ്ഞതേ ഉള്ളൂ.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Arhanghelul Mihail, cînd se împotrivea diavolului şi se certa cu el pentru trupul lui Moise, n'a îndrăznit să rostească împotriva lui o judecată de ocară, ci doar a zis: ,,Domnul să te mustre!``
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Michael aber, der Erzengel, da er mit dem Teufel stritt und mit ihm redete über den Leichnam Mose's, wagte er das Urteil der Lästerung nicht zu fällen, sondern sprach: Der HERR strafe dich!
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Icke så Mikael, överängeln; när denne tvistade med djävulen angående Moses' kropp, dristade han sig icke att över honom uttala någon smädande dom, utan sade allenast: »Herren näpse dig.»
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ฝ่าย อัครเท ว ทู ตา ธิบดี มี คาเอล ครั้น เมื่อ ท่าน โต้เถียง กับ พญา มาร เรื่อง ศพ ของ โมเสส ท่าน เอง ก็ ยัง ไม่ บังอาจ ตั้ง ข้อ กล่าวหา อย่าง เย้ย หยัน ต่อ มาร เลย ได้ แต่ เพียง กล่าว ว่า " ขอ ให้ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ทรง ห้าม เจ้า เถิด "</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Aga ei Peaingel Miikaelgi, kui ta riidles ning vaidles kuradiga Moosese keha pärast, ei julgenud lausuda pilkavat otsust, vaid ütles: „Issand sõidelgu sind!”
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.10" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko enei ia, e korerotia kinotia ana e ratou nga mea kahore nei ratou i matau; na, ko nga mea e matauria noatia ake nei e ratou pera i nga kararehe whakaarokore, he iho ratou i aua mea
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Song những kẻ nầy, hễ đều gì không biết thì khinh dể hết; và mọi điều chúng nó tự nhiên mà biết cũng như con thú vật vô tri, thì dùng mà làm hư mình.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Eux, au contraire, ils parlent d`une manière injurieuse de ce qu`ils ignorent, et ils se corrompent dans ce qu`ils savent naturellement comme les brutes.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa ireo kosa dia miteny ratsy izay zavatra rehetra tsy fantany akory; ary izay zavatra fantany fotsiny, tahaka ny fahalalan'ny biby tsy manan-tsaina kosa, no animbany ny tenany. [ Na: andotoany]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ezek pedig azokat káromolják, a miket  nem tudnak; a miket pedig természet szerint tudnak, mint az oktalan állatok, azok által megromolnak.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ke bona aba okunene izinto zonke abangazaziyo bayazinyelisa; kodwa izinto zonke abazaziyo kakuhle ngemvelo,  njengezinto eziphilileyo ezingenangqondo, bayazonakalisa ngazo ezo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">이 사람들은 무엇이든지 그 알지 못하는 것을 훼방하는도다 또 저희는 이성 없는 짐승같이 본능으로 아는 그것으로 멸망하느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Šitie šmeižia, ko neišmano, ir pažindami tik gyvuliškus instinktus, juose genda.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						А сии злословят то, чего не знают; что же по природе, как бессловесные животные, знают, тем растлевают себя.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tetapi dengan penghinaan-penghinaan, orang-orang itu menyerang segala sesuatu yang mereka tidak mengerti. Mereka sama seperti binatang-binatang yang tidak berakal, yang mengetahui hal-hal dengan nalurinya. Tetapi justru hal-hal itulah yang menyebabkan kehancuran mereka
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Apan kining mga tawhana nagapasipala sa bisan unsang butang nga dili nila masabut, ug sa mga butang nga ilang masabut pinaagi sa balatian nga dala sa kinaiya ingon sa mga mananap nga walay kabuot, pinaagi niining mga butanga sila nangalaglag.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိုသူတို့မူကား၊ မိမိတို့နားမလည်သောအရာများကို ကဲ့ရဲ့တတ်ကြ၏။ တိရစ္ဆာန်ကဲ့သို့ ပကတိအတိုင်း မိမိတို့နားလည်သော အရာများဖြင့် မိမိတို့ကိုပုပ်ပျက်စေတတ်ကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ut eb laj balak' a'in neque'xmajecua ru li c'a'ak re ru lok', li inc'a' neque'xtau ru. Chanchaneb li xul li mâc'a'eb xna'leb. Neque'xsach rib chixbânunquil li c'a'ak re ru chi mâusilal.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Ale títo sa všetkému, čoho neznajú, rúhajú, a čomu prírodou, jako nerozumné zvieratá, rozumejú, práve v tom sa kazia.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तर यी मानिसहरु जुन कुराहरु आफैले बुझेंका छैनन् त्यस बारेमा निन्दनीय शब्दहरु प्रयोग गर्छन्। अनि तिनीहरुले जे बुइछन् बुद्धिद्धारा होइन तर लाटा विवेक अनि शून्य पशुले भै बुइछन्। अनि यी कुराहरुद्वारा तिनीहरु ध्वंश हुन्छन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A ovi hule na ono što ne znadu; a šta znadu po prirodi kao nerazumna životinja, u onom se raspadaju.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Disse derimot spotter det de ikke kjenner; men det de av naturen skjønner, likesom de ufornuftige dyr, med det ødelegger de sig. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Ama bu kişiler anlamadıkları her şeye sövüyorlar. Öte yandan, akıldan yoksun hayvanlar gibi içgüdüleriyle anladıkları ne varsa, onları yıkıma götürüyor.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ولكن هؤلاء يفترون على ما لا يعلمون. واما ما يفهمونه بالطبيعة كالحيوانات غير الناطقة ففي ذلك يفسدون.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Estes, porém, blasfemam de tudo o que não entendem; e, naquilo que compreendem de modo natural, como os seres irracionais, mesmo nisso se corrompem.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">hii autem quaecumque quidem ignorant blasphemant quaecumque autem naturaliter tamquam muta animalia norunt in his corrumpuntur</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ουτοι δε οσα μεν δεν εξευρουσι βλασφημουσιν, οσα δε φυσικως ως τα αλογα ζωα εξευρουσιν, εις ταυτα φθειρονται.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar hierdie mense belaster alles wat hulle nie ken nie; en alles wat hulle, soos die redelose diere, op natuurlike wyse verstaan, daardeur gaan hulle te gronde.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Yo menm, okontrè, yo pale mal sou sa yo pa konprann. Bagay yo konnen se bagay ensten yo moutre yo tankou bèt ki san konprann. Se bagay sa yo menm k'ap pèdi yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Song những kẻ nầy , hễ đều gì không biết thì khinh_dể hết ; và mọi điều chúng_nó tự_nhiên mà biết cũng_như con thú_vật vô_tri , thì dùng mà làm hư mình .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואלה מגדפים את אשר לא ידעו ובדברים אשר יבינו מחק טבעים כבהמות הסכלות בהמה ישחיתו את נפשם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But these speak evil of whatever things they don't know. What they understand naturally, like the creatures without reason, they are destroyed in these things.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						వీరైతే తాము గ్రహింపని విషయములనుగూర్చి దూషించువారై, వివేకశూన్యములగు మృగములవలె వేటిని స్వాభావికముగా ఎరుగుదురో వాటివలన తమ్మునుతాము నాశనముచేసికొనుచున్నారు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						А вие възлюбени, като назидавате себе си в нашата пресвята вяра и се молите на Святия Дух,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ti pa preklinjajo, česarkoli ne vedo; kar pa po naravi znajo, kakor nespametne živali, v tem se pogubljajo.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						لکن این اشخاص بر آنچه نمی دانند افتراء می‌زنند و در آنچه مثل حیوان غیرناطق بالطبع فهمیده‌اند، خود را فاسدمی سازند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Disse derimod bespotte, hvad de ikke kende; og hvad de som de ufornuftige Dyr vide Besked om af Naturen, dermed ødelægge de sig selv.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Nämä sitävastoin herjaavat sitä, mitä eivät tunne; mutta minkä he järjettömäin eläinten tavoin luonnostaan ymmärtävät, sillä he turmelevat itsensä.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						但 這些 人 毀謗 他 們 所 不 知道 的 ． 他 們本性 所 知道 的 事與 那 沒 有 靈性 的 畜類 一 樣 、 在 這事 上 竟 敗壞 了 自己
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Amma borey din go ga hayey kaŋ yaŋ i si faham d'a wow. Haŋ kaŋ i ga bay mo doonay kaŋ boro zumbu nd'a boŋ, danga almanyaŋ kaŋ sinda laakal cine, hayey din do no i go ga halaci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						但 這 些 人 毀 謗 他 們 所 不 知 道 的 ． 他 們 本 性 所 知 道 的 事 與 那 沒 有 靈 性 的 畜 類 一 樣 、 在 這 事 上 竟 敗 壞 了 自 己 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						पर ये लोग जिन बातों को नहीं जानते, उन को बुरा भला कहते हैं; पर जिन बातों को अचेतन पशुओं की नाई स्वभाव ही से जानते हैं, उन में अपने आप को नाश करते हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Tito pak, čehož neznají, tomu se rouhají; a což od přirození znají, jako nerozumná hovada, v tom se poskvrňují.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed tiuj insultas ja cxion, kion ili ne scias; sed kion ili per naturo komprenas, kiel la bestoj senprudentaj, en tio ili malvirtigxas.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Mjerë ata, sepse kanë marrë rrugën e Kainit dhe u dhanë pas çoroditjes së Balaamit për fitim dhe mbaruan në rebelim e Koreut.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Costoro invece bestemmiano tutto ciò che ignorano; tutto ciò che essi conoscono per mezzo dei sensi, come animali senza ragione, questo serve a loro rovina
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En þessir menn lastmæla öllu því, sem þeir þekkja ekki, en spilla sér á því sem þeir skilja af eðlisávísun eins og skynlausar skepnur. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						पण हे लोक, ज्या गोष्टी त्यांना समजत नाहीत त्यांची हे निंदा करतात. आणि जनावरासारखे केवळ मूळ स्वभावाला अनुसरुन जे काही त्यांना समजते. अगदी त्याच गोष्टीमुळे ते नाश पावतात.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						しかし、この人々は自分が知りもしないことをそしり、また、分別のない動物のように、ただ本能的な知識にあやまられて、自らの滅亡を招いている。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Pero éstos maldicen lo que no conocen; y en lo que por instinto comprenden, se corrompen como animales irracionales
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiin kuwanu wax kastoo ayan garanaynba way caayaan, oo waxay ku baabba'aan waxay abuuristooda ku garanayaan sida xayawaanka aan caqliga lahayn.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huai miten bel thil a theih louh peuhmah uh a gense jel ua; huan ngaihtuahna neilou ganhingte banga theihsiamna pianpih a neihte un, huai lampang mahmah ah a kihehse naknak uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಆದರೆ ಈ ಜನರು ತಮಗೆ ಗೊತ್ತಿಲ್ಲದವುಗಳ ವಿಷಯವಾಗಿ ಕೆಟ್ಟದ್ದಾಗಿ ಮಾತನಾಡುತ್ತಾರೆ ಮತ್ತು ತಾವು ವಿವೇಕಶೂನ್ಯ ಮೃಗಗಳಂತೆ ಸ್ವಾಭಾವಿಕವಾಗಿ ಯಾವವುಗಳನ್ನು ತಿಳಿದುಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತಾರೋ ಅವುಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ತಮ್ಮನ್ನು ಕೆಡಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತಾರೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						But these speak evil of those things which they know not: but what they know naturally, as brute beasts, in those things they corrupt themselves.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Hij zei alleen: "De Here zal je straffen." Maar deze mannen spotten met alles wat zij niet kennen. Zij doen precies waar ze zin in hebben, net als dieren, en gaan daaraan dan ook ten gronde.</lang><lang id="Croatian">A ovi pogrđuju  ono što ne poznaju; a što po naravi kao nerazumne životinje poznaju, u tom trunu.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A ci, czego nie znają, to bluźnią; a co z przyrodzenia znają, jako bezrozumne bydła w tem się psują,
					</lang><lang id="Thai">แต่ว่าคนเหล่านี้พูดให้ร้ายถึงสิ่งที่เขาเองไม่รู้จัก แต่ได้กระทำตามสิ่งที่ตนเองรู้จักตามสัญชาตญาณ เหมือนสัตว์เดียรัจฉานที่ไม่มีความคิด เขาได้กระทำให้ตนเองเสื่อมทรามไปด้วยการนั้น</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Datapuwa't ang mga ito'y nangalipusta sa anomang bagay na hindi nila nalalaman: at sa mga bagay na talagang kanilang nauunawa, ay nangagpapakasira na gaya ng mga kinapal na walang bait. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 しかし 、 この 人々 は 自分 が 知り も し な い こと を そし り 、 また 、 分別 の な い 動物 の よう に 、 ただ 本能 的 な 知識 に あやま ら れ て 、 自ら の 滅亡 を 招 い て い る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഇവരോ തങ്ങള്‍ അറിയാത്തതു എല്ലാം ദുഷിക്കുന്നു; ബുദ്ധിയില്ലാത്ത മൃഗങ്ങളെപ്പോലെ സ്വാഭാവികമായി ഗ്രഹിക്കുന്നവയാല്‍ ഒക്കെയും തങ്ങളെത്തന്നേ വഷളാക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Aceştia, dimpotrivă, batjocoresc ce nu cunosc, şi se pierd singuri în ceeace ştiu din fire, ca dobitoacele fără minte.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Diese aber lästern alles, davon sie nichts wissen; was sie aber natürlich erkennen wie die unvernünftigen Tiere, darin verderben sie.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Dessa åter smäda vad de icke känna till; och vad de, likasom de oskäliga djuren, med sina naturliga sinnen kunna fatta, det bruka de till sitt fördärv.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">แต่ว่า คน เหล่า นี้ พูด ให้ร้าย ถึง สิ่ง ที่ เขา เอง ไม่ รู้จัก แต่ ได้ กระทำ ตาม สิ่ง ที่ ตน เอง รู้จัก ตาม สัญชาตญาณ เหมือน สัตว์ เดียรัจฉาน ที่ ไม่ มีค วาม คิด เขา ได้ กระทำ ให้ ตน เอง เสื่อมทราม ไป ด้วย การ นั้น</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Kuid need pilkavad seda, millest nad midagi ei tea; aga millest nad loomu poolest kui mõistmatud elajad aru saavad, selles nad saadavad endid hukka.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.11" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Aue te mate mo ratou! kua haere nei hoki ratou i te ara o Kaina, kua torere rawa hoki ki te he, ara ki to Paraama utu, na ko to Koraha totohe hei whakangaromanga mo ratou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Khốn nạn thay cho chúng nó, vì đã theo đường của Ca-in, lấy lòng tham lợi mà gieo mình vào sự sai lạc của Ba-la-am; và bị hư mất về sự phản nghịch của Cơ-rê.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Malheur à eux! car ils ont suivi la voie de Caïn, ils se sont jetés pour un salaire dans l`égarement de Balaam, ils se sont perdus par la révolte de Coré.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Hahita loza izy! fa efa nandeha tamin'ny lalan'i Kama, sady efa nimaona fatratra hanaraka ny fahadisoan'i Balama hahazoany tamby, ary efa ringana tamin'ny fiodinan'i Kora izy.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Jaj nékik! mert a  Kain útján indultak el, és  a Bálám tévelygéseivel bérért szakadtak ki, és  a Kóré ellenkezésével vesztek el.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Yeha ke bona! Ngokuba bahamba ngendlela kaKayin;  bakhukuliswa lulahlekiso lukaBhileham ngenxa yomvuzo;  batshabalala ephikeni likaKora.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">"화 있을찐저 이 사람들이여, 가인의 길에 행하였으며 삯을 위하여 발람의 어그러진 길로 몰려갔으며 고라의 패역을 좇아 멸망을 받았도다"</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Vargas jiems! Jie pasuko Kaino keliu, godžiai pasidavė Balaamo paklydimui dėl pelno, pražudė save Korės maištu.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Горе им, потому что идут путем Каиновым, предаются обольщению мзды, как Валаам, и в упорстве погибают, как Корей.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Celaka mereka! Mereka telah mengikuti jalan yang ditempuh oleh Kain. Agar mendapat uang, mereka menjerumuskan diri dalam lembah kesesatan, sama seperti Bileam. Dan mereka pun dihancurkan karena memberontak seperti Korah
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Alaut sila! Kay sila nanaglakaw subay sa agi ni Cain, ug tungod sa pagpanapi nagapataka silag panalagan ngadto sa kasaypanan ni Balaam, ug nangawagtang sila diha sa pagsupil ni Core.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						သူတို့သည် အမင်္ဂလာရှိကြ၏။ အကြောင်းမူကား၊ ကာဣနနောက်သို့လိုက်ကြ၏။ အခကိုရခြင်းငှါ ဗာလမ်မှားယွင်းသကဲ့သို့ အလွန်မှားယွန်းခြင်းရှိကြ၏။ ကောရ၏ငြင်းခုံခြင်းအပြစ်နှင့် ဖျက်ဆီးခြင်းသို့ရောက် ကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ra te'xc'ul. Lix na'lebeb a'an jo' lix na'leb laj Caín. Chanchaneb laj Balaam, xban nak neque'xrahi ru li tumin ut junes a'an chic neque'xc'oxla. Neque'xtz'ektâna lix chak'rab li Dios ut neque'xnimobresi rib jo' quixbânu laj Coré. Xban a'an nak te'osok'.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Beda im! Lebo odišli cestou Kainovou a, pojatí bludom Balámovej mzdy, sa vykydli a protirečením Kóreho zahynuli.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						यो तिनीहरुका निम्ति अत्यन्तै नराम्रो हुनेछ। यी मानिसहरुले कयिन हिँडेको मार्ग अनुसरण गरेका छन्। धन कमाउन तिनीहरु बालाम हिँडेको बाटोमा हिडिरहेका छन्। तिनीहरु परमेश्वरको विरोधमा कोरह झैं लडछन्। यसर्थ कोरह झैं तिनीहरु पनि सडनेछन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Teško njima! Jer putem Kainovim podjoše i u prevaru Valamove plate padoše, i u buni Korejevoj izgiboše.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Ve dem! for de har gått Kains vei og for vinnings skyld kastet sig inn i Bileams forvillelse og er gått under ved Korahs gjenstridighet. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Vay onların haline! Çünkü Kayinin yolundan gittiler. Kazanç için kendilerini Balamınkine benzer bir yanılgıya kaptırdılar. Korahınkine benzer bir isyanda mahvoldular.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ويل لهم لانهم سلكوا طريق قايين وانصبوا الى ضلالة بلعام لاجل اجرة وهلكوا في مشاجرة قورح.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Ai deles! porque foram pelo caminho de Caim, e por amor do lucro se atiraram ao erro de Balaão, e pereceram na rebelião de Coré.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">vae illis quia via Cain abierunt et errore Balaam mercede effusi sunt et contradictione Core perierunt</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ουαι εις αυτους, διοτι περιεπατησαν εις την οδον του Καιν και χαριν μισθου εξεχυθησαν εις την πλανην του Βαλααμ, και απωλεσθησαν εις την αντιλογιαν του Κορε.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Wee hulle, want hulle het die weg van Kain bewandel en om loon hulleself in die verleiding van Bíleam gestort en in die verset van Korag omgekom.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Malè pou yo! Y'ap fè menm rout ak Kayen. Pou yo ka fè kòb, yo lage kò yo nan menm move chemen Balaram lan. y'a mouri tankou Kore ki te peri nan fè rebèl ak Bondye
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Khốn_nạn thay cho chúng_nó , vì đã theo đường của Ca-in , lấy_lòng tham lợi mà gieo mình vào sự sai_lạc của Ba-la-am ; và bị hư mất về sự phản_nghịch của Cơ-rê .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אוי להם כי ברדך קין הלכו וישתקעו בתועת בלעם לקבל שכר ובמרי קרח אבדו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Woe to them! For they went in the way of Cain, and ran riotously in the error of Balaam for hire, and perished in Korah's rebellion.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అయ్యోవారికి శ్రమ. వారు కయీను నడిచిన మార్గమున నడిచిరి, బహుమానము పొందవలెనని బిలాము నడిచిన తప్పుత్రోవలో ఆతురముగా పరుగెత్తిరి, కోరహు చేసినట్టు తిరస్కారము చేసి న
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						пазете себе си в Божията любов, ожидайки милостта на нашия Господ Исус Христос за вечен живот.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Gorje jim! ker so hodili po potu Kajnovem in so zabredli v zmoto Balaamovo zaradi plačila in so poginili v Korejevem uporu.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						وای بر ایشان زیرا که به راه قائن رفته‌اند ودر گمراهی بلعام بجهت اجرت غرق شده‌اند و درمشاجرت قورح هلاک گشته‌اند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Ve dem! thi de ere gåede på Kains Vej og have styrtet sig i Bileams Vildfarelse for Vindings Skyld og ere gåede til Grunde i Horas Genstridighed.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Voi heitä, sillä he kulkevat Kainin tietä ja heittäytyvät palkan tähden Bileamin eksytykseen ja hukkuvat niskoitteluunsa niinkuin Koora!
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						他 們有禍 了 ． 因 為走 了 該隱 的 道路 、 又為利往 巴蘭 的 錯謬裡 直奔 、 並 在 可 拉 的 背叛 中 滅亡了
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Kaari ngey! Zama i na Kaynu fonda gana, ka waasu ka ngey boŋ no Balaam* darayyaŋo se alhakku sabbay se, i halaci mo Kora murteyaŋo ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						他 們 有 禍 了 ． 因 為 走 了 該 隱 的 道 路 、 又 為 利 往 巴 蘭 的 錯 謬 裡 直 奔 、 並 在 可 拉 的 背 叛 中 滅 亡 了 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						उन पर हाय! कि वे कैन की सी चाल चले, और मजदूरी के लिये बिलाम की नाई भ्रष्ट हो गए हैं: और कोरह की नाई विरोध करके नाश हुए हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Běda jim, nebo cestou Kainovou odešli, a poblouzením Balámovy mzdy po lakomství se vylili, a odporováním Kóre zahynuli.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Ve al ili! cxar ili iris sur la vojo de Kain, kaj forjxetis sin en la eraron de Bileam por dungopago, kaj pereis en la kontrauxdirado de Korahx.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Këta janë njolla në agapit tuaja, kur hanë e pinë bashkë me ju pa druajtje duke kullotur veten e tyre; ata janë re pa ujë, të shtyrë andej këndej nga erërat, drurë vjeshte pa fruta, dyfish të vdekur, të shkulur me rrënjë,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Guai a loro! Perché si sono incamminati per la strada di Caino e, per sete di lucro, si sono impegolati nei traviamenti di Balaàm e sono periti nella ribellione di Kore
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Vei þeim, því að þeir hafa gengið á vegi Kains og hrapað í villu Bíleams fyrir ávinnings sakir og tortímst í þverúð Kóra. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						या लोकांसाठी हे फार वाइट आहे! काईनाने जो मार्ग धरला तोच यांनी धरलेला आहे. आपला फायदा व्हावा म्हणून ते बलामाप्रमाणे गोंधळून मोकाट धावत सुटले आहेत आणि कोरहाच्या बंडाळीत भाग घेणाऱ्या लोकांचा नाश झाला तसाच या लोकांचा देखील नाश होत आहे.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						彼らはわざわいである。彼らはカインの道を行き、利のためにバラムの惑わしに迷い入り、コラのような反逆をして滅んでしまうのである。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						¡Ay de ellos! Porque han seguido el camino de Caín; por recompensa se lanzaron en el error de Balaam y perecieron en la insurrección de Coré
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Waa u hoog iyaga, waayo, waxay raaceen jidkii Qaabiil, oo faa'iido aawadeed ayay Balcaam qaladkiisii ugu yaaceen, oo waxay ku halligmeen fallaagadii Qorax.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						A tung ua a gik hi! Kaina lampi a jui ua, punna delhin Balaam mohnaah hahtaiin a tai ua, Kora thukalhna ah a mangthangta uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಅವರು ಕಾಯಿನನ ಮಾರ್ಗ ಹಿಡಿದವರೂ ಪ್ರತೀಕಾರ ಹೊಂದುವದಕ್ಕಾಗಿ ಬಿಳಾಮನ ದೋಷವನ್ನು ಮಾಡುವದಕ್ಕೆ ದುರಾಶೆ ಯಿಂದ ಓಡುವವರೂ ಕೋರಹನಂತೆ ಎದುರು ಮಾತನಾಡಿ ನಾಶವಾಗುವವರೂ ಆಗಿರುವ ಅವರಿಗೆ ಅಯ್ಯೋ!
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Woe unto them! for they have gone in the way of Cain, and ran greedily after the error of Balaam for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Het ziet er heel slecht voor hen uit. Zij volgen het voorbeeld van Kaïn, die zijn broer vermoordde. Zij zijn net als Bileam, die voor geld alles wilde doen. Zij gaan Korach achterna, die tegen God in opstand kwam en dat met de dood moest bekopen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Jao njima! Putom Kajinovim pođoše, i zabludi se Bileamovoj  za plaću podaše, i propadoše od pobune Korahove.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Biada im! bo się drogą Kainową udali, a za błędem Baalamowej zapłaty puścili się i przeciwieóstwem Korego poginęli.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">วิบัติจงมีแก่เขา เพราะเขาได้ดำเนินในทางของคาอิน และได้วิ่งพล่านไปตามความผิดพลาดของบาลาอัมเพราะเห็นแก่สินจ้าง และได้พินาศไปในการกบฏอย่างโคราห์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Sa aba nila! sapagka't sila'y nagsilakad sa daan ni Cain, at nagsidaluhong na walang pagpipigil sa kamalian ni Balaam dahil sa upa, at nangapahamak sa pagsalangsang ni Core. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 彼 ら は わざわい で あ る 。 彼 ら は カイン の 道 を 行 き 、 利 の ため に バラム の 惑わし に 迷い 入 り 、 コラ の よう な 反逆 を し て 滅 ん で しま う の で あ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അവര്‍ക്കും അയ്യോ കഷ്ടം! അവര്‍ കയീന്റെ വഴിയില്‍ നടക്കയും കൂലി കൊതിച്ചു ബിലെയാമിന്റെ വഞ്ചനയില്‍ തങ്ങളേത്തന്നേ ഏല്പിക്കയും കോരഹിന്റെ മത്സരത്തില്‍ നശിച്ചുപോകയും ചെയ്യുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Vai de ei! Căci au urmat pe calea lui Cain! S'au aruncat în rătăcirea lui Balaam, din dorinţa de cîştig! Au pierit într'o răscoală ca a lui Core!
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Weh ihnen! denn sie gehen den Weg Kains und fallen in den Irrtum des Bileam um Gewinnes willen und kommen um in dem Aufruhr Korahs.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Ve dem!  De hava trätt in på Kains väg, de hava för löns skull störtat sig i Balaams villfarelse och hava gått förlorade till följd av en gensträvighet lik Koras.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">วิบัติ จง มี แก่ เขา เพราะ เขา ได้ ดำเนิน ใน ทาง ของ คา อิน และ ได้ วิ่ง พล่าน ไป ตาม ความ ผิด พลาด ของ บา ลา อัม เพราะ เห็นแก่ สินจ้าง และ ได้ พินาศ ไป ใน การก บฏ อย่าง โคราห์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Häda neile, et nad on läinud Kaini teed ja on andunud Bileami pettusele tasu eest, ja Korahi kombel vastuhakkamisega on läinud hukka!
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.12" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						He toka moana ratou i roto i a koutou hakari aroha, i a ratou e hakari tahi ana me koutou, he hepara e whangai ana i a ratou ano, kahore hoki e mataku; he kapua waikore e akina ana e nga hau; he rakau kua ngahoro nei nga rau, he mea huakore, ka rua nei nga matenga, he mea kua unuhia ake i nga pakiaka
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Những kẻ đó là dấu vít trong đám tiệc anh em, như người chăn chiên chỉ tưởng nuôi mình cho no nê, không lo sợ gì; như đám mây không nước, theo gió đưa đi đây đi đó, như cây tàn mùa thu, không có trái, hai lần chết, trốc lên bựt rễ;
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ce sont des écueils dans vos agapes, faisant impudemment bonne chère, se repaissant eux-mêmes. Ce sont des nuées sans eau, poussées par les vents; des arbres d`automne sans fruits, deux fois morts, déracinés;
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ireo no harambato voasaron-drano eo amin'ny fanasam-pifankatiavanareo, raha miara-mihinana aminareo izy, dia mpiandry mamahan-tena, nefa tsy matahotra; rahona tsy misy rano, entin'ny rivotra, ireo; hazo fararano, nefa tsy misy voany, indroa maty, voafongotra; [ Na: Ireo no pentimpentina]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ezek szennyfoltok a ti szeretetvendégségeiteken, tartózkodás nélkül veletek lakmároznak, magokat hízlalják; víztelen, szelektõl hányt-vetett fellegek; elhervadt, gyümölcstelen, kétszer meghalt és tõbõl kiszaggatott fák;
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Aba zizixhobo zamatye aselwandle ezidlweni zenu zothando,  bezingxala ukudla nani, bezidlisa okwabo ngokungenakoyika.  Bangamafu angenamanzi, aqhutywaqhutywa yimimoya; bayimithi evuthulukileyo, engenaziqhamo, efe kabini, enyothulwe iingcambu;
					</lang><lang id="Korean">저희는 기탄없이 너희와 함께 먹으니 너희 애찬의 암초요 자기 몸만 기르는 목자요 바람에 불려가는 물없는 구름이요 죽고 또 죽어 뿌리까지 뽑힌 열매 없는 가을 나무요</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jie kaip dėmės jūsų meilės pokyliuose, kai vaišinasi su jumis ir nesidrovėdami tunka. Jie­lyg bevandeniai debesys, vaikomi vėjų, tarytum bevaisiai medžiai rudenį, du kartus mirę ir išrauti.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Таковые бывают соблазном на ваших вечерях любви; пиршествуя с вами, без страха утучняют себя. Это безводные облака, носимые ветром; осенние деревья, бесплодные, дважды умершие, исторгнутые;
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Pada waktu kalian mengadakan pesta makan, sikap orang-orang itu memuakkan di antaramu. Sebab mereka makan dengan rakus tanpa malu-malu, dan hanya mementingkan diri sendiri. Mereka seperti awan yang ditiup oleh angin, tetapi tidak menurunkan hujan. Mereka juga seperti pohon yang tidak menghasilkan buah walaupun musim buah-buahan; pohon-pohon yang telah dicabut akarnya dan sudah mati sama sekali
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kini sila maoy mga buling diha sa inyong mga kombira sa gugma, nga sa walay pagkaikog managhudyaka sa pag-inom-kaon sa walay pagtagad sa uban gawas sa ilang kaugalingon lamang; kini sila mga panganud nga walay dalang ulan, nga ginataral sa hangin; kini sila larag nga mga kahoy nga walay mga bunga, makaduha pil-a ang pagkapatay, nangaibot;
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						မေတ္တာပွဲလုပ်၍ သင်တို့နှင့်အတူ စားသောက်သောအခါ အားမနာဘဲ၊ မိမိတို့ကိုဝစွာကျွေး၍ ပွဲ၌ အစွန်းအကွက်ဖြစ်ကြ၏။ ရေမရှိ၊ လေတိုက်၍လွင့်သော မိုဃ်းတိမ်ကဲ့သို့၎င်း၊ ညှိုးနွမ်း၍ အသီးမတင်၊ နှစ်ကြိမ် သေ၍ နှုတ်ပစ်သော သစ်ပင်ကဲ့သို့၎င်း၊
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Xutânal chok' êre nak cuanqueb laj balak' sa' êyânk nak nequebânu lê nink'e re sahil ch'ôlej. Eb laj balak' ca'aj cui' li numcua'ac ut num uc'ac neque'xbânu ut inc'a' neque'xutânac. Junes xch'olaninquileb rib neque'xc'oxla. Eb laj balak' a'an chanchaneb li chok li mâc'a' hab chi sa', li nac'ame' yalak bar xban li ik'. Laj balak' mâc'a' neque'oc cui'. Chanchaneb li che' li inc'a' neque'ûchin, li namich'man chi junaj cua ut nachakic.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Tí sú škvrnami na vašich hodoch lásky, ktorí sa spolu hostia bez bázne sami seba pasúc, bezvodné oblaky, vetrami pomimo unášané, pozdnojasenné stromy jalové, dvakrát zomrelé, vykorenené,
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						यी मानिसहरु तिमीहरुको समूह भोजमा भएका फोहोर दागहरु जस्तै हुन्। तिनीहरु तिमीहरुको भोजनमा साथ दिन्छन् अनि निर्भय साथ खान्छन्। तिनीहरु आफ्नै स्वार्थ केन्द्रित गोठालाहरु हुन्। ती वृष्टिहीन मेघहरु हुन्। बतासले तिनीहरुलाई चारैतिर उडाउँछ। तिनीहरु ती बृक्षहरु हुन् जुन समयमा फल दिँदैनन्, अनि भूँइबाट उखेलिन्छन्। यसरी तिनीहरु पूर्णरुपले मर्छन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ovo su oni što pogane vaše milostinje jedući s vama bez straha i gojeći se; oblaci bezvodni, koje vetrovi raznose; jesenska drveta nerodljiva, koja su dvaput umrla, i iz korena iščupana;</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Disse er skamflekkene ved eders kjærlighets-måltider, uten blygsel holder de gilde med eder og forer sig selv; vannløse skyer som drives avsted av vinden; trær, nakne som om høsten, ufruktbare, to ganger død, oprykket med rot; 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Sevgi şölenlerinizde sizinle birlikte pervasızca yiyip içen bu kişiler birer kara lekedir. Yalnız kendilerini besleyen çobanlardır. Rüzgarın sürüklediği yağmursuz bulutlara, iki kez ölmüş, kökünden sökülmüş, sonbaharın meyvesiz ağaçlarına benzerler.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						هؤلاء صخور في ولائمكم المحبية صانعين ولائم معا بلا خوف راعين انفسهم. غيوم بلا ماء تحملها الرياح اشجار خريفية بلا ثمر ميتة مضاعفا مقتلعة.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Estes são os escolhidos em vossos ágapes, quando se banqueteiam convosco, pastores que se apascentam a si mesmos sem temor; são nuvens sem água, levadas pelos ventos; são árvores sem folhas nem fruto, duas vezes mortas, desarraigadas;
					</lang><lang id="Latin">hii sunt in epulis suis maculae convivantes sine timore semet ipsos pascentes nubes sine aqua quae a ventis circumferuntur arbores autumnales infructuosae bis mortuae eradicatae</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ουτοι ειναι κηλιδες εις τας αγαπας σας, συμποσιαζοντες αφοβως, βοσκοντες εαυτους, νεφελαι ανυδροι υπο ανεμων περιφερομεναι, δενδρα φθινοπωρινα ακαρπα, δις αποθανοντα, εκριζωθεντα,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Hulle is skandvlekke in julle liefdemaaltye, wat sonder vrees saam fees hou en hulleself voer, waterlose wolke deur winde rondgedrywe, bome in die nasomer, wat sonder vrugte is, twee maal gestorwe, ontworteld;
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Moun sa yo, se gate yo vin gate manje n'ap fè pou frè yo. Yo san ront konsa. Yo vin manje, yo vin bwè kont kò yo san chonje moun; se pròp tèt yo ase yo konnen. Yo tankou nwaj van ap gaye nan syèl la san bay lapli. Yo tankou pyebwa ki pa janm donnen, menm nan sezon rekòt. Wi, yo tankou pyebwa yo derasinen epi ki fin mouri nèt
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Những kẻ đó là dấu vít trong đám tiệc anh_em , như người chăn_chiên chỉ tưởng nuôi mình cho no_nê , không lo_sợ gì ; như đám mây không nước , theo gió đưa đi đây đi đó , như cây tàn mùa thu , không có trái , hai lần chết , trốc lên bựt rễ ;
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						הלא צורי מכשול המה בסעודתיכם של אהבה ובקלות ראש יאכלו וישתו עמכם ורעים את נפשם עננים הם בבלי מים הנדפים מפני רוח עצי חרף באין פרי אשר מתו פעמים ונעקרו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">These are hidden rocky reefs in your love feasts when they feast with you, shepherds who without fear feed themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds; autumn leaves without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						వీరు నిర్భయముగా మీతో సుభోజనము చేయుచు, తమ్మునుతాము నిర్భయ ముగా పోషించుకొనుచు, మీ ప్రేమవిందులలో దొంగ మెట్టలుగా ఉన్నారు. వీరు గాలిచేత ఇటు అటు కొట్టుకొనిపోవు నిర్జల మేఘములుగాను, కాయలు రాలి ఫలములు లేక, రెండు మారులు చచ్చి వేళ్లతో పెళ్లగింప బడిన చెట్లుగాను,
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						И към едни, които са в съмнение, бивайте милостиви;
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ti so pri bratovskih pojedinah vaših zapreke, ko se goste z vami in brez strahu sami sebe paso; so oblaki brez vode, ki jih gonijo vetrovi, drevesa poznojesenska, brez sadu, dvakrat mrtva, izkoreninjena;
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اینها درضیافت های محبتانه شما صخره‌ها هستند چون با شما شادی می‌کنند، و شبانانی که خویشتن رابی خوف می‌پرورند و ابرهای بی‌آب از بادهارانده شده و در ختان صیفی بی‌میوه، دوباره مرده و از ریشه‌کنده شده،
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Disse ere Skærene ved eders Kærlighedsmåltider, fordi de uden Undseelse frådse med og pleje sig selv; de ere vandløse Skyer, som drives forbi af Vinden; bladløse Træer uden Frugt, to Gange døde, oprykkede med Rode;
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						He likapilkkuina teidän rakkausaterioillanne julkeasti kemuilevat ja itseään kestitsevät. He ovat vedettömiä, tuulten ajeltavia pilviä, paljaita, syksyisiä puita, hedelmättömiä, kahdesti kuolleita, juurineen maasta reväistyjä,
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						這樣 的 人 、 在 你 們的愛 席上 、 與 你 們同喫 的 時候 、 正是 礁石 ． 〔 或 作 玷污 〕 他 們作 牧人 、 只 知 餧養 自己 、 無所 懼怕 ． 是 沒有雨 的 雲彩 、 被風飄蕩 ． 是 秋天沒 有 果子 的 樹 、 死 而 又 死 、 連根 被 拔出 來
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Borey din ya danga hari ra tondi tuganteyaŋ no araŋ baakasinay batuyaŋey ra. I si humburu mo waati kaŋ i ga ŋwa araŋ banda. Kurukoyaŋ no kaŋ ga ngey boŋ kuru, beene buruyaŋ no kaŋ sinda hari, kaŋ haw goono ga gaaray. Tuuriyaŋ no kaŋ sinda ize heemar waate, kaŋ yaŋ bu sorro hinka, kaŋ yaŋ i dagu mo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						這 樣 的 人 、 在 你 們 的 愛 席 上 、 與 你 們 同 喫 的 時 候 、 正 是 礁 石 ． 〔 或 作 玷 污 〕 他 們 作 牧 人 、 只 知 餧 養 自 己 、 無 所 懼 怕 ． 是 沒 有 雨 的 雲 彩 、 被 風 飄 蕩 ． 是 秋 天 沒 有 果 子 的 樹 、 死 而 又 死 、 連 根 被 拔 出 來 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						यह तुम्हारी प्रेम सभाओं में तुम्हारे साथ खाते- पीते, समुद्र में छिपी हुई चट्टान सरीखे हैं, और बेधड़क अपना ही पेट भरनेवाले रखवाले हैं; वे निर्जल बादल हैं; जिन्हें हवा उड़ा ले जाती है; पतझड़ के निष्फल पेड़ हैं, जो दो बार मर चुके हैं; और जड़ से उखड़ गए हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Tiť jsou na hodech vašich poskvrny, když s vámi hodují bezstoudně, sami se pasouce; jsouce jako oblakové bez vody, jimiž vítr sem i tam točí, stromové uvadlí, neužiteční, dvakrát mrtví a vykořenění,
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Ili estas la subakvaj rokoj en viaj agapoj, kun vi kunfestenante, sentime sin pasxtante; nuboj senakvaj, per vento disportataj; auxtunaj arboj senfruktaj, dufoje mortintaj, elradikigitaj;
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						valë deti të egra që shkumbëzojnë paudhësitë e tyre, yje të këputur për të cilët është ruajtur terri i errësirës për gjithmon.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Sono la sozzura dei vostri banchetti sedendo insieme a mensa senza ritegno, pascendo se stessi; come nuvole senza pioggia portate via dai venti, o alberi di fine stagione senza frutto, due volte morti, sradicati
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þessir menn eru blindsker við kærleiksmáltíðir yðar, er þeir sitja að veislum með yður og háma í sig blygðunarlaust. Þeir eru vatnslaus ský, sem rekast fyrir vindum, tré, sem bera ekki ávöxt að hausti, tvisvar dauð og rifin upp með rótum. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						हे लोक तुमच्या भातामध्ये दडलेले धोकादायक खडे, असल्यासारखे आहेत. ते खुशाल तुमच्याबरोबर जेवणखाणे करतात, ते फक्त स्वत:च चरत राहाणारे असे मेंढपाळ आहेत, ते पाणी नसलेल्या ढगांसारखे असून ते वाऱ्यामुळे वाहवत जातात. ते लोक म्हणजे हिवाळ्यातील फळहीन व समूळ उपटली गेलेली आणि दोनदा मेलेली झाडे आहेत.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						彼らは、あなたがたの愛餐に加わるが、それを汚し、無遠慮に宴会に同席して、自分の腹を肥やしている。彼らは、いわば、風に吹きまわされる水なき雲、実らない枯れ果てて、抜き捨てられた秋の木、
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Estos que participan en vuestras comidas fraternales son manchas, apacentándose a sí mismos sin temor alguno. Son nubes sin agua, llevadas de acá para allá por los vientos. Son árboles marchitos como en otoño, sin fruto, dos veces muertos y desarraigados
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwanu waa dhagaxyo qarsoon oo ku dhex jira cashooyinkiinna jacaylka markay idinla faysteeyaan iyagoo aan cabsanaynin; waxayna yihiin adhijirro naftooda jira, iyo daruuro aan biyo lahayn oo dabaylo kaxeeyaan, iyo geedo jiilaal oo aan midho lahayn, oo laba goor dhintay, oo la rujiyey;
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Hiaite tuh ahi uh, na itna-ankuangluina ua hihmelhemtu leh lauhuai kiselte- amau mah kikem, angsung ngaihtuaha, maingaltaka tathangte; mei tuipai lou, huih mut lengte ahi ua; phavanga sing, gah lou, nihvei sisa, a zung toh bohkhiakte ahi ua;
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಳಂಕರಾದ ಇವರು ನಿಮ್ಮ ಪ್ರೇಮ ಭೋಜನಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ನಿರ್ಭಯವಾಗಿ ತಿಂದು ತಮ್ಮನ್ನು ತಾವೇ ಪೋಷಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತಾರೆ. ಇವರು ಗಾಳಿಯಿಂದ ಬಡಿಸಿಕೊಂಡು ಹೋಗುವ ನೀರಿಲ್ಲದ ಮೇಘಗಳೂ ಎರಡು ಸಾರಿ ಸತ್ತವರೂ ಹಣ್ಣು ಬಿಡದೆ ಒಣಗಿಹೋಗಿ ಬೇರು ಸಹಿತ ಕಿತ್ತುಬಿದ್ದ ಮರಗಳೂ
					</lang><lang id="English">
						These are spots in your feasts of charity, when they feast with you, feeding themselves without fear: clouds they are without water, carried about of winds; trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Deze mensen bederven de feestelijke maaltijden die u met elkaar houdt. Het is hun alleen om eten en drinken begonnen. Zij schamen zich nergens voor en denken alleen maar aan zichzelf. Zij zijn als wolken die over dorstig land drijven, zonder regen te geven; Zij lijken op vruchtbomen die zelfs in de oogsttijd geen vruchten geven en daarom omgehakt worden; al het leven is er uit.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Oni su ljage  na vašim agapama, bezobzirno se s vama gosteći i napasajući se;  oblaci bezvodni što ih vjetrovi raznose, stabla besplodna u kasnoj  jeseni, dvaput usahla, iskorijenjena,</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Cić są na świętych ucztach waszych zmazani, którzy z wami godując bez wstydu, sami się pasą; są obłoki bezwodne, które od wiatrów tam i sam unoszone bywają; drzewa zwiędłe nieużyteczne, dwakroć zmarłe i wykorzenione;
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คนเหล่านี้เป็นรอยด่างในการประชุมเลี้ยงผูกรักของท่านทั้งหลาย ขณะเขาร่วมการเลี้ยงกับท่าน เขาเลี้ยงแต่ตนเองโดยไม่เกรงกลัวเลย เขาเป็นเมฆที่ปราศจากน้ำที่ถูกพัดลอยไปตามลม เป็นต้นไม้ที่ผลของมันเหี่ยวแห้งไปจึงไม่มีผลอยู่เลย และตายมาสองหนแล้ว เพราะถูกถอนออกทั้งราก</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ang mga ito'y pawang mga batong natatago sa inyong piging ng pagiibigan, kung sila'y nakikipagpiging sa inyo, mga pastor na walang takot na nangagpapasabsab sa kanilang sarili; mga alapaap na walang tubig, na tinatangay ng mga hangin; mga punong kahoy sa taginaw na walang bunga, na makalawang namatay, na binunot pati ugat; 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 彼 ら は 、 あなた がた の 愛餐 に 加わ る が 、 それ を 汚 し 、 無 遠慮 に 宴会 に 同席 し て 、 自分 の 腹 を 肥や し て い る 。 彼 ら は 、 いわば 、 風 に 吹 き ま わ さ れ る 水 な き 雲 、 実 ら な い 枯れ 果て て 、 抜き捨て られ た 秋 の 木 、
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ഇവര്‍ നിങ്ങളുടെ സ്നേഹസദ്യകളില്‍ മറഞ്ഞുകിടക്കുന്ന പാറകള്‍; നിങ്ങളോടുകൂടെ വിരുന്നുകഴിഞ്ഞു ഭയംകൂടാതെ നിങ്ങളെത്തന്നേ തീറ്റുന്നവര്‍; കാറ്റുകൊണ്ടു ഔടുന്ന വെള്ളമില്ലാത്ത മേഘങ്ങള്‍; ഇലകൊഴിഞ്ഞും ഫലമില്ലാതെയും രണ്ടുരു ചത്തും വേരറ്റും പോയ വൃക്ഷങ്ങള്‍;
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Sînt nişte stînci ascunse la mesele voastre de dragoste, unde se ospătează fără ruşine împreună cu voi, şi se îndoapă deabinele; nişte nori fără apă, mînaţi încoace şi încolo de vînturi, nişte pomi tomnatici fără rod, de două ori morţi, desrădăcinaţi;
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Diese Unfläter prassen bei euren Liebesmahlen ohne Scheu, weiden sich selbst; sie sind Wolken ohne Wasser, von dem Winde umgetrieben, kahle, unfruchtbare Bäume, zweimal erstorben und ausgewurzelt,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Det är dessa som få hålla gästabud med eder, där de sitta såsom skamfläckar vid edra kärleksmåltider och oförsynt se sig själva till godo.  De äro skyar utan vatten, skyar som drivas bort av vindarna.  De äro träd som stå nakna på senhösten, ofruktbara, i dubbel måtto döda, uppryckta med rötterna.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คน เหล่า นี้ เป็น รอย ด่าง ใน การ ประชุม เลี้ยง ผูก รัก ของ ท่าน ทั้งหลาย ขณะ เขา ร่วม การ เลี้ยง กับ ท่าน เขา เลี้ยง แต่ ตน เอง โดย ไม่ เกรง กลัว เลย เขา เป็น เมฆ ที่ ปราศจาก น้ำ ที่ ถูก พัด ลอย ไป ตาม ลม เป็นต้น ไม้ ที่ ผล ของ มัน เหี่ยวแห้ง ไป จึง ไม่ มี ผลอ ยู่ เลย และ ตาย มาส อง หน แล้ว เพราะ ถูก ถอน ออก ทั้ง ราก</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Nemad on teie armastussöömaaegadel mustuselaigud, kes kartmatult ühes pidutsevad iseendid nuumates; nad on tuulte aetavad veeta pilved, sügisesed viljata puud, kahekordselt surnud, juurtega välja kistud,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.13" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						He ngaru pua no te moana, e whakatutu ana i te huka o to ratou whakama; he whetu atiutiu noa, pouri kerekere te wahi kua rite mo ratou mo ake tonu atu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						như sóng cuồng dưới biển, sôi bọt ô uế của mình; như sao đi lạc, sự tối tăm mù mịt đã dành cho chúng nó đời đời!
					</lang><lang id="French">
						des vagues furieuses de la mer, rejetant l`écume de leurs impuretés; des astres errants, auxquels l`obscurité des ténèbres est réservée pour l`éternité.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						onjan-dranomasina mitopatopa mamorivory ny fahamenarany; kintana mifindrafindra, ka voatahiry ho azy mandrakizay ny fahamaintisan'ny maizina.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Tengernek megvadult habjai, a magok rútságát tajtékozók; tévelygõ csillagok, a kiknek a sötétség homálya van fenntartva örökre.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						bangamaza alwayo olwandle, elephuza awawo amahlazo;  baziinkwenkwezi eziphalaphalayo, begcinelwe isithokothoko sobumnyama ngonaphakade.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">자기의 수치의 거품을 뿜는 바다의 거친 물결이요 영원히 예비된 캄캄한 흑암에 돌아갈 유리하는 별들이라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jie lyg šėlstančios jūros bangos, kurios spjaudo savo begėdystę, lyg žvaigždės klajoklės, kurioms per amžius skirta juodžiausia tamsybė.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						свирепые морские волны, пенящиеся срамотами своими; звезды блуждающие, которым блюдется мрак тьмы на веки.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Sama seperti ombak yang ganas di laut menimbulkan buih, begitu juga mereka membuihkan perbuatan-perbuatan yang memalukan. Mereka adalah seperti bintang-bintang yang mengembara dan yang sudah disediakan tempatnya oleh Allah di dalam kegelapan yang paling dahsyat untuk selama-lamanya
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						kini sila mabangis nga mga balud sa dagat nga nagapabola sa ilang kaugalingong pagkamakauulaw; kini sila laag nga mga bitoon kang kinsa ang kangi-ob sa kangitngit gitagana hangtud sa kahangturan.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						မိမိရှက်ခြင်းအကြောင်းကို ပွက်စေတတ်သော လှိုင်းတံပိုးရိုင်းကဲ့သို့၎င်း၊ ကြယ်ပျံကဲ့သို့၎င်းဖြစ်ကြ၏။ ထို ကြယ်ပျံတို့အဘို့တခဲနက်သော ထာဝရမှောင်မိုက်ကို သိုထားလျက်ရှိ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Nak na-el chak xcuokx li palau xban xcacuil rok li ha', nalemeb rib chire li ha' lix tz'ajnil li ha'. Jo'can ajcui' lix xutâneb laj balak' xban li mâusilal li neque'xbânu. Chanchaneb li chahim li yal naxbeni rib yalak bar chiru choxa. Eb li cuînk a'in ac xakabanbileb chi xic chi junaj cua toj sa' xchamal ut xk'ojyînal li tojba mâc.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						divoké vlny morské, vypeňujúce svoje vlastné hanebnosti, bludné hviezdy, ktorým je zachovaná mrákava tmy na večnosť.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिनीहरु समुद्रका भयानक छाल जस्तै हुन्। छालले फिँज सृष्टि गर्छ। यी मानिसहरुले, छालले फिँज उत्पन्न गरे भै लज्जापूर्ण कुराहरु गर्छन्। यी मानिसहरु ती ताराहरु जस्तै हुन् जो आकाशमा निरुद्देश्य घुम्छन्। तिनीहरुको निम्ति चुक झैं कालो ठाँउ सदैवको लागि राखिएको छ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Besni valovi morski, koji se pene svojim sramotama, zvezde lažne, kojima se čuva mrak večne tame.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						ville havsbårer som utskummer sin egen skam; villfarende stjerner, for hvem mørkets natt er rede til evig tid. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Köpüğünü savuran denizin azgın dalgaları gibi ayıplarını çevreye savururlar. Serseri yıldızlar gibidirler. Onları sonsuza dek sürecek koyu karanlık bekliyor.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						امواج بحر هائجة مزبدة بخزيهم. نجوم تائهة محفوظ لها قتام الظلام الى الابد.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						ondas furiosas do mar, espumando as suas próprias torpezas, estrelas errantes, para as quais tem sido reservado para sempre o negrume das trevas.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">fluctus feri maris despumantes suas confusiones sidera errantia quibus procella tenebrarum in aeternum servata est</lang><lang id="Greek">
						κυματα αγρια θαλασσης επαφριζοντα τας ιδιας αυτων αισχυνας, αστερες πλανηται, δια τους οποιους το ζοφερον σκοτος ειναι τετηρημενον εις τον αιωνα.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 woeste golwe van die see wat hulle eie skandes laat opskuim, dwaalsterre vir wie die donkerheid van die duisternis vir ewig bewaar word.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Yo tankou lanm lanmè lè lanmè a move. Y'ap pouse kim salte yo met deyò. Yo tankou zetwal ki pèdi rout yo. Bondye sere yon plas pou yo kote ki fè pi nwa a pou tout tan
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						như sóng cuồng dưới biển , sôi bọt ô_uế của mình ; như sao đi lạc , sự tối_tăm mù_mịt đã dành cho chúng_nó đời_đời !
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						משברי ים עזים אשר יגרשו בשתם ככבים תעים אשר חשך אפלה צפון להם עדי עד׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">wild waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, for whom the blackness of darkness has been reserved forever.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						తమ అవమానమను నురుగు వెళ్ల గ్రక్కువారై, సముద్రముయొక్క ప్రచండమైన అలలుగాను, మార్గము తప్పితిరుగు చుక్కలుగాను ఉన్నారు; వారికొరకు గాఢాంధకారము నిరంతరము భద్రము చేయబడి యున్నది.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						други спасявайте, като ги изтръгвате из огъня; а към други показвайте милост, със страх, като се гнусите даже и от осквернената от плътта дреха.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						divji morski valovi, ki izpenjavajo lastno sramoto; zvezde tavajoče, katerim je mrak teme shranjen vekomaj.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و امواج جوشیده دریا که رسوایی خود را مثل کف برمی آورند و ستارگان آواره هستند که برای ایشان تاریکی ظلمت جاودانی مقرر است.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						vilde Bølger på Hav, som udskumme deres egen Skam; vild farende Stjerner; for dem er Mørke og Mulm bevaret til evig Tid.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						rajuja meren aaltoja, jotka vaahtoavat omia häpeitään, harhailevia tähtiä, joille pimeyden synkeys ikuisiksi ajoiksi on varattu.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						是 海裡 的 狂 浪 、 湧出 自己 可 恥 的 沫子 來 ． 是 流蕩 的 星 、 有 墨黑 的 幽暗 為 他 們永遠 存留
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 I ga hima teeku bonday futoyaŋ kaŋ goono ga ngey boŋ haawi kufo bangandi. Handariyayzeyaŋ no kaŋ go boŋdaray ra. Irikoy na kubay bi tik kaŋ ga duumi soola ka jisi i se. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						是 海 裡 的 狂 浪 、 湧 出 自 己 可 恥 的 沫 子 來 ． 是 流 蕩 的 星 、 有 墨 黑 的 幽 暗 為 他 們 永 遠 存 留 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						ये समुद्र के प्रचण्ड हिलकोरे हैं, जो अपनी लज्जा का फेन उछालते हैं: ये डांवाडोल तारे हैं, जिन के लिये सदा काल तक घोर अन्धकार रखा गया है।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Vzteklé vody mořské, vymítajíce jako pěny svou mrzkost, hvězdy bludné, jimžto mrákota tmy zachována jest na věčnost.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						sovagxaj marondoj, elsxauxmantaj siajn hontindajxojn; steloj vagantaj, por kiuj la nigreco de mallumo por eterne estas rezervata.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Dhe për këta profetizoi edhe Enoku, i shtati pas Adamit, duke thënë: ''Ja, Zoti erdhi me mijërat e tij të shenjtë,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						come onde selvagge del mare, che schiumano le loro brutture; come astri erranti, ai quali è riservata la caligine della tenebra in eterno
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þeir eru ofsalegar hafsbylgjur, sem freyða eigin skömmum, reikandi stjörnur, sem eiga dýpsta myrkur í vændum til eilífðar. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						ते लोक आपल्या लज्जास्पद कामामुळे फेसाळणाऱ्या समुद्राच्या लाटांप्रमाणे आहेत, ते जणू काळ्याकुटृ अंधारात दडलेले तारे असे आहेत.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						自分の恥をあわにして出す海の荒波、さまよう星である。彼らには、まっくらなやみが永久に用意されている。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Son fieras olas del mar que arrojan la espuma de sus propias abominaciones. Son estrellas errantes para las cuales está reservada para siempre la profunda oscuridad de las tinieblas
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						iyo hirar kacsan oo badda, oo ceebtoodu xumbaynayso, iyo xiddigo ambaday, oo madowga gudcurka weligood loo hayaa.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Tuipi kihawt vonvon, amau zahlakna thankhia ahi ua; aksi vialvak, amau dia khantawna mial bingbikbek sit sakte ahi uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಸ್ವಂತ ಅವಮಾನವೆಂಬ ನೊರೆಯನ್ನು ಕಾರುವ ಸಮುದ್ರದ ಹುಚ್ಚು ತೆರೆಗಳೂ ಆಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ. ಅಲೆಯುವ ನಕ್ಷತ್ರ ಗಳಾದ ಇವರ ಪಾಲಿಗೆ ಕಾರ್ಗತ್ತಲೆಯು ಸದಾಕಾಲ ಇಟ್ಟಿರುವದು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, to whom is reserved the blackness of darkness for ever.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Zij zijn net als woeste golven op zee, die schuimkoppen krijgen; zij laten zich zc door hun schandalige begeerten opzwepen, dat er allerlei vuiligheid naar boven komt. Dwaalsterren zijn het, die hun einde zullen vinden in de eeuwige duisternis.</lang><lang id="Croatian">bijesno morsko valovlje  što ispjenjuje svoje sramote, zvijezde lutalice kojima je spremljena  crna tmina dovijeka.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Wały wściekłe morskie, wyrzucające swoje sprośności, gwiazdy błąkające się, którym chmura ciemności zachowana jest na wieki.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เป็นคลื่นที่บ้าคลั่งในมหาสมุทร ที่ซัดฟองของความบัดสีของตนเองขึ้นมา เขาเป็นดาวที่ลอยลับไป เป็นผู้ที่ตกอยู่ในความมืดทึบตลอดกาล</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Mga mabangis na alon sa dagat, na pinagbubula ang kanilang sariling kahihiyan; mga bituing gala na siyang pinaglaanan ng pusikit ng kadiliman magpakailan man. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 自分 の 恥 を あわ に し て 出 す 海 の 荒波 、 さまよ う 星 で あ る 。 彼 ら に は 、 まっくら なやみ が 永久 に 用意 さ れ て い る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						തങ്ങളുടെ നാണക്കേടു നുരെച്ചു തള്ളുന്ന കൊടിയ കടല്‍ത്തിരകള്‍; സദാകാലത്തേക്കും അന്ധതമസ്സു സൂക്ഷിച്ചുവെച്ചിരിക്കുന്ന വക്ര ഗതിയുള്ള നക്ഷത്രങ്ങള്‍ തന്നേ.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						nişte valuri înfuriate ale mării, cari îşi spumegă ruşinile lor, nişte stele rătăcitoare, cărora le este păstrată negura întunerecului pentru vecie.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						wilde Wellen des Meeres, die ihre eigene Schande ausschäumen, irre Sterne, welchen behalten ist das Dunkel der Finsternis in Ewigkeit.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						De äro vilda havsvågor som uppkasta sina egna skändligheters skum.  De äro irrande stjärnor, åt vilka det svarta mörkret är förvarat till evig tid.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เป็น คลื่น ที่ บ้า คลั่ง ใน มหาสมุทร ที่ ซัด ฟอง ของ ความ บัดสี ของ ตน เอง ขึ้น มา เขา เป็น ดาว ที่ ลอย ลับ ไป เป็น ผู้ ที่ ตก อยู่ ใน ความ มืด ทึบ ตลอด กาล</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						metsikud merelained, mis vahutavad välja oma häbi, eksijad tähed, kellele pilkane pimedus on varutud igaveseks ajaks.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.14" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						I poropititia ano hoki enei e Enoka, e te tuawhitu i muri i a Arama, i a ia i mea, Na, kei te haere mai te Ariki me nga mano tini o tana hunga tapu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ấy cũng vì họ mà Hê-nóc, là tổ bảy đời kể từ A-đam, đã nói tiên tri rằng:
					</lang><lang id="French">
						C`est aussi pour eux qu`Énoch, le septième depuis Adam, a prophétisé en ces termes: Voici, le Seigneur est venu avec ses saintes myriades,
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary Enoka koa, ilay fahafito nandimby an'i Adama, dia efa naminany ny amin'ireny olona ireny ka nanao hoe: "Indro, tonga Jehovah mbamin'ny masiny tsy omby alinalina
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ezekrõl is prófétált  pedig Énok, a ki Ádámtól fogva a hetedik volt, mondván: Ímé eljött az Úr az õ sok ezer szentjével,
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Waprofeta ke nangabo uEnoki, owesixhenxe ukususela kuAdam,  esithi, Yabonani, yeza iNkosi namawakawaka abangcwele bayo,
					</lang><lang id="Korean">아담의 칠세 손 에녹이 사람들에게 대하여도 예언하여 이르되 보라 주께서 그 수만의 거룩한 자와 함께 임하셨나니</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Apie juos pranašavo ir septintasis nuo Adomo, Henochas: “Štai atėjo Viešpats su miriadais savo šventųjų
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						О них пророчествовал и Енох, седьмый от Адама, говоря: „се, идет Господь со тьмами святых Ангелов Своих –
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Henokh, keturunan ketujuh dari Adam, dahulu pernah menubuatkan tentang orang-orang itu. Henokh berkata, "Lihat, Tuhan akan datang dengan beribu-ribu malaikat-Nya yang suc
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Mahitungod usab kanila si Enoc, usa sa ikapitong kaliwatan sukad kang Adan, naghimog profesiya nga nag-ingon, "Tan-awa, ang Ginoo nahiabut uban sa iyang balaang mga panon,
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အာဒံမှဆင်းသက်၍ ခုနှစ်ဆက်မြောက်သောသူ ဧနောက်က၊ ထာဝရဘုရားသည် ခပ်သိမ်းသော သူတို့ကို တရားစီရင်တော်မူ၍၊ မတရားသောသူတို့သည် မတရားသဖြင့် ပြုသောအဓမ္မအမှုရှိသမျှတို့၏ အပြစ်ကို၎င်း၊ မတရားသောလူဆိုးတို့သည် ဘုရားသခင်ကို ပြစ်မှား၍ ပြောသောကြမ်းတမ်းသော စကား ရှိသမျှတို့၏ အပြစ်ကို၎င်းဘော်ပြခြင်းငှါ၊
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Laj Enoc, a'an lix cuukil chak chirix laj Adán. Quiâtinac chirixeb li cuînk a'in jo' quic'ute' chiru xban li Dios. Laj Enoc quixye: —Abihomak, chan. Tol-êlk li Kâcua' rochben li q'uila ok'ob chi ángel.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A prorokoval aj o nich siedmy od Adama Enoch, keď povedal: Hľa prišiel Pán so svojimi svätými myriadami
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						आदमका सातौं सन्तान हनोकले तिनीहरुको बारेमा येसो भनेका छन् “हेर, प्रभु उहाँका हजारौं हजारौं पवित्र दूतहरुसंग आउँनु हुँदैछ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ali i za ovakve prorokova Enoh, sedmi od Adama, govoreći: Gle, ide Gospod s hiljadama svetih andjela svojih</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Disse var det også Enok, den syvende fra Adam, spådde om da han sa: Se, Herren kommer med sine mange tusen hellige 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Ademden sonraki altıncı kuşaktan olan Hanok, bu adamlara ilişkin şu peygamberlikte bulundu: ‹‹İşte Rab herkesi yargılamak üzere on binlerce kutsalıyla geliyor. Tanrı yoluna aykırı, tanrısızca yapılan bütün işlerden ve tanrısız günahkârların kendisine karşı söylediği bütün ağır sözlerden ötürü Rab, bütün insanlara suçluluklarını gösterecektir.››
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						وتنبأ عن هؤلاء ايضا اخنوخ السابع من آدم قائلا هوذا قد جاء الرب في ربوات قديسيه
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Para estes também profetizou Enoque, o sétimo depois de Adão, dizendo: Eis que veio o Senhor com os seus milhares de santos,
					</lang><lang id="Latin">prophetavit autem et his septimus ab Adam Enoc dicens ecce venit Dominus in sanctis milibus suis</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Προεφητευσε δε περι τουτων και ο Ενωχ, εβδομος απο Αδαμ, λεγων Ιδου, ηλθεν ο Κυριος με μυριαδας αγιων αυτου,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En Henog, die sewende van Adam af, het ook teen hulle geprofeteer en gesê: Kyk, die Here het gekom met sy heilige tien duisendtalle,
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Depi lontan, Enòk, ki te vin sèt jenerasyon apre Adan, te pale sou yo, lè l' te di: Koute. Men Bondye ap vini ak tout lame moun pa li yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ấy cũng vì họ mà Hê-nóc , là tổ bảy đời kể từ A-đam , đã nói tiên_tri rằng :
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						וגם חנוך השביעי לאדם נבא לאלה לאמר הנה יהוה בא ברבבת קדשיו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">About these also Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied, saying, "Behold, the Lord came with ten thousands of his holy ones,</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ఆదాము మొదలుకొని యేడవ వాడైన హనోకుకూడ వీరినిగూర్చి ప్రవచించి  యిట్లనెను ఇదిగో  అందరికిని  తీర్పు తీర్చుటకును, వారిలో భక్తి హీనులందరును భక్తిహీనముగా చేసిన వారి భక్తిహీన క్రియలన్నిటిని గూర్చియు, 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						А на Онзи, Който може да ви предпази от препъване, и да ви постави непорочни в радост пред Своята слава,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Prorokoval je pa tudi tem sedmi od Adama, Enoh, govoreč: Glej, prišel je Gospod z miriadami svetih svojih,
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						لکن خنوخ که هفتم ازآدم بود، درباره همین اشخاص خبر داده، گفت: «اینک خداوند با هزاران هزار از مقدسین خود یهودا آمد
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 Men om disse har også Enok, den syvende fra Adam, profeteret, da han sagde: "Se, Herren kom med sine hellige Titusinder
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Heistäkin Eenok, Aadamista seitsemäs, on ennustanut, sanoen: "Katso, Herra tulee tuhannen tuhansine pyhinensä
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						亞當 的 七 世 孫 以諾 、 曾 豫 言這些 人說 、 看 哪 、 主帶 著 他 的 千 萬 聖者 降臨
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Annuhu mo kaŋ ga ti Adamu haama iyyanta na annabitaray te borey din boŋ ka ne: «Wa guna, Rabbi kaa da nga hanante zambar-zambarey, 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						亞 當 的 七 世 孫 以 諾 、 曾 豫 言 這 些 人 說 、 看 哪 、 主 帶 著 他 的 千 萬 聖 者 降 臨 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						और हनोक ने भी जो आदम से सातवीं पीढ़ी में था, इन के विषय में यह भविष्यद्ववाणी की, कि देखो, प्रभु अपने लाखों पवित्रों के साथ आया।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Prorokoval pak také o nich sedmý od Adama Enoch, řka: Aj, Pán s svatými tisíci svými béře se,
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj al ili ankaux HXanohx, la sepa post Adam, profetis, dirante:Jen la Sinjoro venis kun Siaj sanktaj miriadoj,
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						për të bërë gjyqin kundër të gjithëve dhe për të bindur të gjithë të pabesët në mes tyre për të gjitha veprat e paudhësisë dhe për të gjitha fjalët fyese që mëkatarët e pabesë folën kundër tij''.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Profetò anche per loro Enoch, settimo dopo Adamo, dicendo: «Ecco, il Signore è venuto con le sue miriadi di angeli per far il giudizio contro tutti
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Um þessa menn spáði líka Enok, sjöundi maður frá Adam, er hann segir: "Sjá, Drottinn er kominn með sínum þúsundum heilagra 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						हनोख, आदामापासूनचा सातवा मनुष्य यानेसुद्धा या लोकांविषयी असेच भाकीत केले आहे: “पाहा हजारो पवित्र देवदूतांसह प्रभु येत आहे.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						アダムから七代目にあたるエノクも彼らについて預言して言った、「見よ、主は無数の聖徒たちを率いてこられた。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Acerca de los mismos también profetizó Enoc, séptimo después de Adán, diciendo: "He aquí, el Señor vino entre sus santos millare
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Enoog oo ahaa farcankii toddobaad oo Aadan isna kuwanuu wax ka sii sheegay isagoo leh, Bal eega, Rabbigu wuxuu yimid isagoo wata quduusiintiisii aan tirada lahayn,
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huan, Enok, Adam akipana sagihnain hiaite tungtang nagenkholin, Ngai un, Toupa tuh a mi siangthou singkhatte toh a hongpai ahi, chiin,
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇಂಥವರ ವಿಷಯದಲ್ಲಿಯೇ ಆದಾಮನಿಂದ ಏಳನೆಯವನಾದ ಹನೋಕನು ಸಹ--ಇಗೋ, ಕರ್ತನು ತನ್ನ ಹತ್ತು ಸಾವಿರ ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧರನ್ನು ಕೂಡಿಕೊಂಡು
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And Enoch also, the seventh from Adam, prophesied of these, saying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thousands of his saints,
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Wat Henoch zei, die van de zevende generatie na Adam was, is ook op hen van toepassing: "Daar komt de Here met de tienduizenden die bij Hem horen, om over alle mensen recht te spreken.</lang><lang id="Croatian">O njima prorokova sedmi od Adama, Henok: "Gle, dođe Gospodin  sa Desttisućama svojim</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A prorokował też o nich siódmy od Adama Enoch, mówiąc: Oto Pan idzie z świętymi tysiącami swoimi,
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เอโนคคนที่เจ็ดนับแต่อาดัมได้พยากรณ์ถึงคนเหล่านี้ด้วยว่า "ดูเถิด องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าได้เสด็จมาพร้อมกับพวกวิสุทธิชนของพระองค์หลายหมื่น</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang mga ito naman ang hinulaan ni Enoc, na ikapito sa bilang mula kay Adam, na nagsabi, Narito, dumating ang Panginoon, na kasama ang kaniyang mga laksalaksang banal, 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 アダム から 七 代 目 に あた る エノク も 彼 ら に つ い て 預言 し て 言 っ た 、 「 見 よ 、 主 は 無数 の 聖徒 たち を 率い て こ られ た 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ആദാംമുതല്‍ ഏഴാമനായ ഹനോക്കും ഇവരെക്കുറിച്ചു
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Şi pentru ei a proorocit Enoh, al şaptelea patriarh dela Adam, cînd a zis: ,,Iată că a venit Domnul cu zecile de mii de sfinţi ai Săi,
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Es hat aber auch von solchen geweissagt Henoch, der siebente von Adam, und gesprochen: "Siehe, der HERR kommt mit vielen tausend Heiligen,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Om dessa var det ock som Enok, den sjunde från Adam, profeterade och sade: »Se, Herren kommer med sina mångtusen heliga,
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เอ โน คค น ที่ เจ็ด นับ แต่ อา ดัมได้พยาก รณ์ถึง คน เหล่า นี้ ด้วยว่า " ดูเถิด องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ได้ เสด็จ มา พร้อม กับ พวก วิ สุทธิ ชน ของ พระองค์ หลาย หมื่น</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Ent nende kohta on ka Eenok, seitsmes Aadamast, ennustanud, öeldes: „Vaata, Issand tuleb Oma pühade kümnetuhandetega
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.15" langNo="60"><lang id="Maori">
						Kia whakaritea he whakawa mo nga tangata katoa, kia riria hoki te hunga karakiakore o ratou mo a ratou mahi takahi i te karakia katoa, i he ai ratou ki te karakia, mo nga kupu pakeke katoa i korerotia e te hunga hara, e te hunga karakiakore, mon a
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nầy, Chúa ngự đến với muôn vàn thánh, đặng phán xét mọi người, đặng trách hết thảy những người không tin kính về mọi việc không tin kính họ đã phạm, cùng mọi lời sỉ hổ mà người kẻ có tội không tin kính đó đã nói nghịch cùng Ngài.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						pour exercer un jugement contre tous, et pour faire rendre compte à tous les impies parmi eux de tous les actes d`impiété qu`ils ont commis et de toutes les paroles injurieuses qu`ont proférées contre lui des pécheurs impies.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						hitsara ny olona rehetra sy hampiaiky ny olona ratsy fanahy rehetra ny asan'ny haratsiam-panahy rehetra, izay nataony tamin'ny haratsiam-panahiny sy ny teny sarotra rehetra izay nitenenan'ny mpanota ratsy fanahy hanohitra Azy."
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Hogy  ítéletet tartson mindenek felett, és feddõzzék mindazok ellen, a kik közöttök istentelenek, istentelenségöknek minden cselekedetéért, a melyekkel istentelenkedtek, és minden kemény beszédért, a melyet az istentelen bûnösök szóltak õ ellene.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						ukuba ibagwebe bonke, ibohlwaye bonke abangahloneli Thixo kubo, ngenxa yemisebenzi yabo yonke yokungahloneli Thixo,  abayenze bengahloneli Thixo, nangenxa yazo zonke izinto ezilukhuni, ababezithethile ngayo aboni abangahloneli Thixo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">이는 뭇사람을 심판하사 모든 경건치 않은 자의 경건치 않게 행한 모든 경건치 않은 일과 또 경건치 않은 죄인의 주께 거스려한 모든 강퍅한 말을 인하여 저희를 정죄하려 하심이라 하였느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						įvykdyti teismo visiems ir apkaltinti visų bedievių dėl visų bedieviškų darbų, kuriuos jie bedieviškai vykdė, ir dėl visų piktų žodžių, kuriuos prieš Jį kalbėjo bedieviai nusidėjėliai”.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						сотворить суд над всеми и обличить всех между ними нечестивых во всех делах, которые произвело их нечестие, и во всех жестоких словах, которые произносили на Него нечестивые грешники".
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						untuk menghakimi semua orang. Tuhan akan menghukum orang-orang jahat karena perbuatan-perbuatan mereka yang bejat. Dan Ia akan menghukum orang berdosa dan durhaka karena semua kata penghinaan yang diucapkannya.
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						 aron iyang igapatuman ang paghukom sa tanan, ug sa pagpadayag sa pagkamasad-anon sa tanang mga tawong dili diosnon, diha sa ilang tanang dili diosnong binuhatan nga ilang nahimo sa dili diosnong paagi, ug sa tanang mapait nga mga butang nga batok kaniya gikapamulong sa mga makasasala nga dili diosnon."
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						အတိုင်းမသိ များစွာသော မိမိသန့်ရှင်းသူတို့နှင့်တကွကြွလာတော် မူလိမ့်မည်ဟု ပရောဖက်ပြု၍ ဟောပြောလေ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Tâchâlk chi rakoc âtin sa' xbêneb chixjunil ut chixch'olobanquil lix mâqueb riq'uin lix yehom xbânuhomeb jo' eb ajcui' riq'uin li xic' aj âtin xyehomeb chirix li Kâcua', chan laj Enoc.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						učiniť súd proti všetkým a náležite skárať všetkých ich bezbožníkov pre všetky skutky ich bezbožnosti, ktorými páchali bezbožnosť, a pre všetky tvrdé reči spupné, ktoré hovorili proti nemu, hriešnici, bezbožní.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						प्रभुले हरेक मानिसको न्याय गर्नु हुनेछ। प्रभु सबै मानिसहरुको न्याय गर्न अनि जो परमेश्वरका विरुद्ध छन्, तिनीहरुलाई दण्ड दिन आउँनु हुँदैछ। परमेश्वरले तिनीहरुले गरेको परमेश्वर विरोधी जम्मै कुराहरुको निम्ति तिनीहरु सबैलाई दण्ड दिनुहुनेछ। उहाँले यी पापीहरुलाई, जो परमेश्वरका विरुद्धमा जति कर्णकदु कुरा गरे ती सबैको निम्ति दण्ड दिनु हुनेछ।”
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Da učini sud svima, i da pokara sve bezbožnike za sva njihova bezbožna dela kojima bezbožnost činiše, i za sve ružne reči njihove koje bezbožni grešnici govoriše na Nj.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						for å holde dom over alle og refse alle de ugudelige for alle de ugudelige gjerninger som de gjorde, og for alle de hårde ord som de talte mot ham, de ugudelige syndere. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish"></lang><lang id="Arabic">
						ليصنع دينونة على الجميع ويعاقب جميع فجارهم على جميع اعمال فجورهم التي فجروا بها وعلى جميع الكلمات الصعبة التي تكلم بها عليه خطاة فجار.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						para executar juízo sobre todos e convencer a todos os ímpios de todas as obras de impiedade, que impiamente cometeram, e de todas as duras palavras que ímpios pecadores contra ele proferiram.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">facere iudicium contra omnes et arguere omnes impios de omnibus operibus impietatis eorum quibus impie egerunt et de omnibus duris quae locuti sunt contra eum peccatores impii</lang><lang id="Greek">
						δια να καμη κρισιν κατα παντων και να ελεγξη παντας τους ασεβεις εξ αυτων δια παντα τα εργα της ασεβειας αυτων, τα οποια επραξαν και δια παντα τα σκληρα, τα οποια ελαλησαν κατ' αυτου αμαρτωλοι ασεβεις.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 om gerig te hou oor almal en al die goddelose mense onder hulle te straf oor al hulle goddelose werke wat hulle goddelooslik gedoen het, en oor al die harde woorde wat die goddelose sondaars teen Hom gespreek het.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						L'ap jije tout moun; l'ap kondannen tout mechan yo pou tout move bagay yo te fè kont Bondye. Moun sa yo ki te san respè pou Bondye, l'ap kondannen yo pou tout move paròl yo te di sou li
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nầy , Chúa ngự đến với muôn_vàn thánh , đặng phán_xét mọi người , đặng trách hết_thảy những người không tin kính về mọi việc không tin kính họ đã phạm , cùng mọi lời sỉ hổ mà người kẻ có tội không tin kính đó đã nói nghịch cùng Ngài .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						לעשות משפט בכלם ולהוכיח כל רשעי ארץ על כל מעשי רשעתם ועל כל הקשות אשר דברו עליו חטאים אנשי רשע׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">to execute judgment on all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their works of ungodliness which they have done in an ungodly way, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him."</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						భక్తిహీనులైన పాపులు  తనకు విరోధముగా చెప్పిన కఠినమైన మాటలన్నిటినిగూర్చియు వారిని ఒప్పించుటకును, ప్రభువు తన  వేవేల పరిశుద్ధుల పరివారముతో వచ్చెను.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						на единствения Бог наш Спасител, чрез Исуса Христа нашия Господ, да бъде слава и величие, и преди всичките векове, и сега, и до всичките векове. Амин.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						izvršit sodbo nad vsemi in kaznovat vse brezbožne za vsa dela brezbožnosti, ki so jih brezbožno storili, in za vse trde besede, ki so jih govorili zoper njega grešniki brezbožni.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						تا برهمه داوری نماید و جمیع بی‌دینان راملزم سازد، بر همه کارهای بی‌دینی که ایشان کردند و برتمامی سخنان زشت که گناهکاران بی‌دین به خلاف او گفتند.»
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						for at holde Dom over alle og straffe alle de ugudelige for alle deres Ugudeligheds Gerninger, som de have bedrevet, og for alle de formastelige Ord, som de have talt imod ham, de ugudelige Syndere!"
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						tuomitsemaan kaikkia ja rankaisemaan kaikkia jumalattomia kaikista heidän jumalattomista teoistansa, joita he jumalattomuudessaan ovat tehneet, ja kaikesta julkeasta, mitä nuo jumalattomat syntiset ovat häntä vastaan puhuneet".
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						要 在 眾人 身 上行 審判 、 證實 那 一 切 不敬虔 的 人 、 所 妄行 一切 不敬虔 的 事 、 又 證實 不敬虔 之 罪人 所 說頂 撞 他 的 剛愎話
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 zama a ma ciiti te borey kulu se ka borey kulu kaŋ wangu Irikoy zeeri mo ngey Irikoy wangay goyey kaŋ i te Irikoy wangay ra sabbay se, da sanni yaamey kulu kaŋ zunubikooney kaŋ yaŋ ti Irikoy wangey salaŋ a boŋ sabbay se.» 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						要 在 眾 人 身 上 行 審 判 、 證 實 那 一 切 不 敬 虔 的 人 、 所 妄 行 一 切 不 敬 虔 的 事 、 又 證 實 不 敬 虔 之 罪 人 所 說 頂 撞 他 的 剛 愎 話 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						कि सब का न्याय करे, और सब भक्तिहीनों को उन के अभक्ति के सब कामों के विषय में, जो भक्तिहीन पापियों ने उसके विरोध में कही हैं, दोषी ठहराए।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Aby učinil soud všechněm a trestal všecky, kteříž by koli mezi nimi byli bezbožní, ze všech skutků bezbožnosti jejich, v nichž bezbožnost páchali, i ze všech tvrdých řečí, kteréž mluvili proti němu hříšníci bezbožní.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						por fari jugxon kontraux cxiuj, kaj por kondamni cxiujn malpiulojn pri cxiuj malpiajxoj, kiujn ili malpie faris, kaj pri cxiuj obstinaj paroloj,  kiujn malpiaj pekuloj parolis kontraux Li.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Këta janë murmuritës, që ankohen për fatin e tyre, që ecin sipas pasioneve të tyre; dhe goja e tyre flet fjalë krenarie dhe u bëjnë lajka njerëzve për dobi të vet.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						e per convincere tutti gli empi di tutte le opere di empietà che hanno commesso e di tutti gli insulti che peccatori empi hanno pronunziato contro di lui»
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    til að halda dóm yfir öllum og til að sanna alla óguðlega menn seka um öll þau óguðlegu verk, sem þeir hafa drýgt, og um öll þau hörðu orð, sem óguðlegir syndarar hafa talað gegn honum." 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						तो अखिल जगातील लोकांचा न्याय करील आणि सर्व लोकांना त्यांनी केलेल्या अधर्माच्या कामासाठी आणि देवाची चाड न बाळगणाऱ्या पापी लोकांनी त्याच्याविरुद्ध जे कठोर, वाईट शब्द आपल्या तोंडावाटे काढले त्याकरीता तो त्यांना दोषी ठरवील.”
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						それは、すべての者にさばきを行うためであり、また、不信心な者が、信仰を無視して犯したすべての不信心なしわざと、さらに、不信心な罪人が主にそむいて語ったすべての暴言とを責めるためである」。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						para hacer juicio contra todos y declarar convicta a toda persona respecto a todas sus obras de impiedad que ellos han hecho impíamente y respecto a todas las duras palabras que los pecadores impíos han hablado contra él.
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						inuu xukun ku soo dejiyo kulli, iyo inuu kuwa aan cibaadada lahayn oo dhan ku caddeeyo shuqulladoodii cibaadola'aanta ahaa oo ay cibaadola'aanta ku sameeyeen, iyo waxyaalihii adkaa oo dhan oo ay dembilayaasha aan cibaadada lahaynu isaga ka sheegeen.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						mi tengteng tunga vaihawm ding leh, Pathian limsak loute tengteng Pathian limsak louhna na Pathian limsak loutunga a sep tengteng uah leh, Pathian limsak loumikhialten a tunga thukhauh tak a gen tengteng ua siamlouh tangsak dingin.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಎಲ್ಲರಿಗೆ ನ್ಯಾಯ ತೀರಿಸುವದಕ್ಕೂ ಅವರಲ್ಲಿ ಭಕ್ತಿಹೀನರೆಲ್ಲರು ಮಾಡಿದ ಭಕ್ತಿಯಿಲ್ಲದ ಅವರ ಎಲ್ಲಾ ಕೃತ್ಯಗಳ ವಿಷಯವಾಗಿ ಮತ್ತು ಭಕ್ತಿಯಿಲ್ಲದ ಪಾಪಿಷ್ಠರು ತನಗೆ ವಿರೋಧವಾಗಿ ಆಡಿದ ಎಲ್ಲಾ ಕಠಿಣವಾದ ಮಾತುಗಳ ವಿಷಯವಾಗಿ ಅವರಿಗೆ ಮನದಟ್ಟು ಮಾಡುವದಕ್ಕೂ ಬಂದನು ಎಂಬ ದಾಗಿ ಪ್ರವಾದಿಸಿದನು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						To execute judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard speeches which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Hij zal alle onbetrouwbare mensen straffen voor hun verzet tegen God en voor de grote mond die zij tegen Hem hebben opgezet."</lang><lang id="Croatian">suditi svima i pokarati sve bezbožnike  za sva njihova bezbožna djela kojima bezbožno sagriješiše i za  sve drzovite riječi koje grešni bezbožnici izrekoše protiv njega."</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Aby uczynił sąd wszystkim i karał wszystkich niezbożników między nimi ze wszystkich niepobożności ich, które niezbożnie płodzili i ze wszystkich przykrości, które mówili przeciwko niemu niezbożni grzesznicy.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">เพื่อทรงพิพากษาปรับโทษคนทั้งปวง และทรงกระทำให้ทุรชนทั้งปวงรู้สึกตัวถึงการอธรรมที่เขาได้กระทำด้วยใจชั่ว และรู้สึกตัวถึงการหยาบช้าทั้งหมดที่ทุรชนคนบาปเหล่านั้นได้กล่าวร้ายต่อพระองค์"</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Upang isagawa ang paghuhukom sa lahat, at upang sumbatan ang lahat ng masasama sa lahat ng kanilang mga gawang masasama na kanilang ginawang may kasamaan, at sa lahat ng mga bagay na mabibigat na sinalita laban sa kaniya ng mga makasalanang masasama. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 それ は 、 すべて の 者 に さばき を 行 う ため で あ り 、 また 、 不信心 な 者 が 、 信仰 を 無視 し て 犯 し た すべて の 不信 心なし わざと 、 さらに 、 不信心 な 罪人 が 主に そむ い て 語 っ た すべて の 暴言 と を 責め る ため で あ る 」 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						“ഇതാ കര്‍ത്താവു എല്ലാവരെയും വിധിപ്പാനും അവര്‍ അഭക്തിയോടെ ചെയ്ത ഭക്തിവിരുദ്ധമായ സകല പ്രവൃത്തികളുംനിമിത്തം ഭക്തികെട്ട പാപികള്‍ തന്റെ നേരെ പറഞ്ഞ സകലനിഷ്ഠൂരങ്ങളും നിമിത്തവും ഭക്തികെട്ടവരെ ഒക്കെയും ബോധംവരുത്തുവാനും ആയിരമായിരം വിശുദ്ധന്മാരോടു കൂടെ വന്നിരിക്കുന്നു” എന്നു പ്രവചിച്ചു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						ca să facă o judecată împotriva tuturor, şi să încredinţeze pe toţi cei nelegiuiţi, de toate faptele nelegiuite, pe cari le-au făcut în chip nelegiuit, şi de toate cuvintele de ocară, pe cari le-au rostit împotriva Lui aceşti păcătoşi nelegiuiţi.``
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Gericht zu halten über alle und zu strafen alle Gottlosen um alle Werke ihres gottlosen Wandels, womit sie gottlos gewesen sind, und um all das Harte, das die gottlosen Sünder wider ihn geredet haben."
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						för att hålla dom över alla och bestraffa alla de ogudaktiga för alla de ogudaktiga gärningar som de hava övat, och för alla de förmätna ord som de i sin syndiga ogudaktighet hava talat mot honom.»
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">เพื่อ ทรง พิพากษา ปรับโทษ คน ทั้งปวง และ ทรง กระทำ ให้ ทุรชน ทั้งปวง รู้สึก ตัว ถึง การ อธรรม ที่ เขา ได้ กระทำ ด้วย ใจ ชั่ว และ รู้สึก ตัว ถึง การ หยาบช้า ทั้งหมด ที่ ทุรชน คน บาป เหล่า นั้น ได้ กล่าว ร้าย ต่อ พระองค์ "</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						pidama kohut kõigile ja nuhtlema kõiki jumalatuid kõigi nende jumalakartmatute tegude eest, mis nad jumalatuses on teinud, ja kõigi kõvade sõnade eest, mis jumalatud patused Tema vastu on rääkinud!”
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.16" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						He hunga amuamu ratou, he kowhetewhete, e haere ana i runga i o ratou hiahia ake, tetere rawa ano hoki nga kupu e korero nei o ratou mangai, he hunga whakapai kanohi ratou, he mea kia riro ai he mea ma ratou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ấy đều là người kẻ hay lằm bằm, hay phàn nàn luôn về số phận mình, làm theo sự ham muốn mình, miệng đầy những lời kiêu căng, và vì lợi mà nịnh hót người ta.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ce sont des gens qui murmurent, qui se plaignent de leur sort, qui marchent selon leurs convoitises, qui ont à la bouche des paroles hautaines, qui admirent les personnes par motif d`intérêt.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ireo dia mpimonomonona sy mpimoimoy, mandeha araka ny filany (ary ny vavany manao teny miavonavona loatra) ka mandoka olona mba hahazoany zavatra.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ezek zúgolódók, panaszolkodók, a magok kívánságai szerint járók; szájok kevélységet szól, haszonlesésbõl személyimádók.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Aba ngabakrokri abasolayo, behamba ngokweenkanuko zabo,  umlomo wabo uthetha iindumbisa zamazwi, bencoma ubuso bomntu ngenxa yenzuzo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">이 사람들은 원망하는 자며 불만을 토하는 자며 그 정욕대로 행하는 자라 그 입으로 자랑하는 말을 내며 이를 위하여 아첨하느니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jie visada murma, nepatenkinti savo dalia, gyvena geismais; jų lūpos kalba išpūstus žodžius, jie pataikauja žmonėms dėl savo naudos.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Это ропотники, ничем не довольные, поступающие по своим похотям(нечестиво и беззаконно); уста их произносят надутые слова; они оказывают лицеприятие для корысти.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Orang-orang itu selalu saja menggerutu dan menyalahkan orang lain. Mereka hidup menurut keinginan-keinginan mereka yang berdosa. Mereka membual mengenai diri sendiri, dan menjilat orang supaya mendapat keuntungan
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Kini sila mga bagolbolan, tigmulo, nanaggawi pahiuyon sa ilang kaugalingong mga pangibog, ug ang ilang mga baba nagasultig mga pasiatab, nga nagaulog-ulog sa mga tawo aron sa pagpamintaha kanila.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိုသူတို့သည် မြည်တမ်း၏ အပြစ်တင်တတ်သောသူ၊ ကိုယ်တပ်မက်ခြင်းအတိုင်း ကျင့်တတ်သောသူ၊ ထောင်လွှားသော စကားကိုပြောတတ်သောသူ၊ ကိုယ်အကျိုးစီးပွားကြောင့် သူ့မျက်နှာကို ထောက်ထား ခန့်ညားတတ်သော သူဖြစ်ကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb a'in aj cuech'oneleb. Mâc'a' nacuulac chiruheb. Ca'aj cui' li c'a'ru naxrahi ru li tz'ejcualej neque'xbânu. Neque'âtinac re xnimobresinquileb ribeb. Neque'xk'unbesi junak riq'uin k'unil âtin yal re li c'a'ru neque'raj riq'uin.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						To sú reptáci, žehrajúci na svoj osud, ktorí chodia podľa svojich žiadostí, a ktorých ústa hovoria nadutosti, a ktorí licomerne pre zisk obdivujú osoby.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						यी मानिसहरु सदैव विरोध जनाउँछन् अनि अरुको त्रुटि खोज्छन्। तिनीहरुले सदैव तिनीहरुले गर्न चाहेका कुकर्महरु गर्छन्। तिनीहरु आफ्नै गर्व गर्छन्। तिनीहरुले अन्य मानिसहरुको विषयमा राम्रो कुरा भन्नुको एउटा कारण तिनीहरु जे चाहन्छन् त्यो प्राप्त गर्नु हो।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ovo su nezadovoljni vikači, koji po željama svojim žive, i usta njihova govore ponosite reči, i za dobitak gledaju ko je ko.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Disse er folk som knurrer og klager over sin skjebne, enda de farer frem efter sine lyster, og deres munn taler skrytende ord, enda de smigrer for folk for vinnings skyld. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Bunlar hep yakınıp söylenir, kendi tutkularının peşinden giderler. Ağızlarından kurumlu sözler çıkar, kendi çıkarları için başkalarını pohpohlarlar.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						هؤلاء هم مدمدمون متشكون سالكون بحسب شهواتهم وفمهم يتكلم بعظائم يحابون بالوجوه من اجل المنفعة.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Estes são murmuradores, queixosos, andando segundo as suas concupiscências; e a sua boca diz coisas muito arrogantes, adulando pessoas por causa do interesse.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">hii sunt murmuratores querellosi secundum desideria sua ambulantes et os illorum loquitur superba mirantes personas quaestus causa</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ουτοι ειναι γογγυσται, μεμψιμοιροι, περιπατουντες κατα τας επιθυμιας αυτων, και το στομα αυτων λαλει υπερηφανα, και κολακευουσι προσωπα χαριν ωφελειας.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Hulle is murmureerders wat oor hul lot klae, en volgens hulle begeerlikhede wandel; en hulle mond spreek trotse woorde, terwyl hulle mense vlei ter wille van voordeel.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Moun sa yo toujou ap bougonnen, y'ap plede plengnen sou sitiyasyon yo. Se enterè yo ase y'ap chache. Depi yo louvri bouch yo, se vante y'ap vante tèt yo. Y'ap flate tout moun pou yo tire avantaj sou yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ấy đều là người kẻ hay lằm_bằm , hay phàn_nàn luôn về số_phận mình , làm theo sự ham_muốn mình , miệng đầy những lời kiêu_căng , và vì lợi mà nịnh_hót người_ta .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אלה הם הרגנים והמתאוננים ההלכים אחרי תאותיהם אשר פיהם ידבר עתק הדרי פנים עקב שחד׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">These are murmurers and complainers, walking after their lusts (and their mouth speaks proud things), showing respect of persons to gain advantage.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						వారు తమ దురాశలచొప్పున నడుచుచు,లాభమునిమిత్తము మనుష్యులను కొనియాడుచు,6 సణుగువారును తమ గతినిగూర్చి నిందించువారునై యున్నారు; వారి నోరు డంబమైన మాటలు పలుకును. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Откровението от Исуса Христа, което Му даде Бог, за да покаже на слугите Си онова, което има да стане скоро; а Христос прати та го яви чрез ангела Си на Своя слуга Иоан,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ti so godrnjači, pritoževalci, ki hodijo po svojih poželenjih, in usta njih govore šopirno, občudujoč osebe zaradi koristi.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اینانند همهمه‌کنان و گله‌مندان که برحسب شهوات خود سلوک می‌نمایند و به زبان خود سخنان تکبرآمیزمی گویند و صورتهای مردم را بجهت سودمی پسندند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Disse ere de, som knurre, som klage over deres Skæbne, medens de vandre efter deres Begæringer, og deres Mund taler overmodige Ord, medens de for Fordels Skyld vise Beundring for Personer.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						He ovat napisijoita, kohtalonsa nurkujia ja vaeltavat himojensa mukaan; heidän suunsa puhuu pöyhkeitä, ja he mielistelevät ihmisiä oman etunsa tähden.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						這些 心 是 私下 議論 、 常發 怨言 的 、 隨從 自己 的 情慾 而行 、 口中 說誇 大 的話 、 為 得 便宜 諂媚人
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Borey din ga ti jancekoyaŋ da guutukoyaŋ. I goono ga ngey ibaay laaley gana, i meyey mo goono ga fooma sanniyaŋ ci. I goono ga me kaanay te zama ngey ma du riiba. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						這 些 心 是 私 下 議 論 、 常 發 怨 言 的 、 隨 從 自 己 的 情 慾 而 行 、 口 中 說 誇 大 的 話 、 為 得 便 宜 諂 媚 人 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						ये तो असंतुष्ट, कुड़कुड़ानेवाले, और अपने अभिलाषाओं के अनुसार चलनेवाले हैं; और अपने मुंह से घमण्ड की बातें बोलते हैं; और वे लाभ के लिये मुंह देखी बड़ाई किया करते हैं।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Tiť jsou reptáci žalobní, podle žádostí svých chodíce, jejichž ústa mluví pýchu, pochlebujíce osobám některým pro svůj užitek.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Ili estas murmuremuloj, plendemuloj, irantaj laux siaj voluptoj (dum ilia busxo parolas fanfaronajxojn) kaj favorantaj personojn pro profito.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Por ju, shumë të dashur, mbani mend fjalët që ju kanë parathënë apostujt e Zotit tonë Jezu Krisht.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Sono sobillatori pieni di acredine, che agiscono secondo le loro passioni; la loro bocca proferisce parole orgogliose e adulano le persone per motivi interessati
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þessir menn eru möglarar, umkvörtunarsamir og lifa eftir girndum sínum. Munnur þeirra mælir ofstopaorð og þeir meta menn eftir hagnaði. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						हे लोक कुरकुर करणारे व दोष दाखविणारे आहेत, ते आपल्या वासनांप्रमाणे चालणारे आणि आपल्या तोंडाने बढाया मारणारे लोक आहेत, ते आपल्या फायद्यासाठी इतरंचा तोंडपूजेपणा करतात.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						彼らは不平をならべ、不満を鳴らす者であり、自分の欲のままに生活し、その口は大言を吐き、利のために人にへつらう者である。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Éstos se quejan de todo y todo lo critican, andando según sus propios malos deseos. Su boca habla arrogancias, adulando a las personas para sacar provecho
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwanu waa kuwa gunuunaca, oo cawda, oo damacyadooda xaaraanta ah ka daba orda, afkooduna wuxuu ku hadlaa hadallo isweyneyn ah, dadkana way u kala eexdaan inay faa'iido helaan aawadeed.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huaite tuh phunhatte leh ngohhatte ahi ua, amau utna bengjel in a om ua, a kamte khawng un leng kiotsakna thu a gen gawpgawp a, punna deih manin i a deih uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇವರು ಗುಣುಗುಟ್ಟು ವವರೂ ದೂರುವವರೂ ತಮ್ಮ ದುರಾಶೆಗಳನ್ನನುಸರಿಸಿ ನಡೆಯುವವರೂ ಆಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ. ಇವರ ಬಾಯಿಯು ದೊಡ್ಡ ದೊಡ್ಡ ಮಾತುಗಳನ್ನು ಆಡುತ್ತದೆ. ಇವರು ಸ್ವಪ್ರಯೋಜನಕ್ಕಾಗಿ ಮುಖಸ್ತುತಿ ಮಾಡುತ್ತಾರೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own lusts; and their mouth speaketh great swelling words, having men's persons in admiration because of advantage.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Zij doen niets dan mopperen en zeuren; zij willen alleen hun eigen zin doen. Praatjesmakers zijn het. En ls zij eens aardig zijn, doen zij het om er beter van te worden.</lang><lang id="Croatian">To su rogoborni nezadovoljnici koji hode putom svojih požuda, usta im zbore naduto, ulaguju se u lice radi dobitka.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Ci są szemracze utyskujący sobie, według pożądliwości swoich chodzący, i których usta mówią bardzo harde słowa; pochlebiając osobom dla swego pożytku.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คนเหล่านี้มักเป็นคนบ่น เป็นคนโพนทะนา เป็นคนดำเนินตามตัณหาอันชั่วของตัว และปากเขากล่าวคำโอ้อวดต่างๆ เป็นคนยกยอผู้อื่นเพื่อหวังประโยชน์ของตน</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ang mga ito'y mga mapagbulong, mga madaingin, na nangagsisilakad ayon sa kanilang masasamang pita (at ang kanilang bibig ay nangagsasalita ng mga kapalaluan), nangagpapakita ng galang sa mga tao dahil sa pakikinabangin. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 彼 ら は 不平 を ならべ 、 不満 を 鳴ら す 者 で あ り 、 自分 の 欲 の まま に 生活 し 、 その 口 は 大言 を 吐 き 、 利 の ため に 人 に へつら う 者 で あ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അവര്‍ പിറുപിറുപ്പുകാരും തങ്ങളുടെ ഗതിയെക്കുറിച്ചു ആവലാധി പറയുന്നവരുമായി സ്വന്തമോഹങ്ങളെ അനുസരിച്ചു നടക്കുന്നു. അവരുടെ വായ് വമ്പുപറയുന്നു; കാര്‍യ്യസാദ്ധ്യത്തിന്നായി അവര്‍ മുഖസ്തുതി പ്രയോഗിക്കുന്നു.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Ei sînt nişte cîrtitori, nemulţămiţi cu soarta lor; trăiesc după poftele lor; gura le este plină de vorbe trufaşe, şi slăvesc pe oameni pentru cîştig.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Diese murren und klagen immerdar und wandeln dabei nach ihren Lüsten; und ihr Mund redet stolze Worte, und achten das Ansehen der Person um Nutzens willen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						De äro människor som alltid knorra och knota över sin lott, medan de likväl vandra efter sina egna begärelser.  Och deras mun talar stora ord, under det att de dock av egennytta söka vara människor till behag.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คน เหล่า นี้ มัก เป็น คน บ่น เป็น คน โพนทะนา เป็น คน ดำเนิน ตาม ตัณหา อัน ชั่ว ของ ตัว และ ปาก เขา กล่าว คำ โอ้อวด ต่างๆ เป็น คน ยกยอ ผู้ อื่น เพื่อ หวัง ประโยชน์ ของ ตน</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Need on nurisejad, saatusega rahulolematud, kes käivad oma himude järgi ja kelle suu räägib ülbeid sõnu, meelitades inimesi kasu pärast.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.17" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						E nga hoa aroha, kia mahara koutou ki nga kupu i korerotia i mua e nga apotoro a to tatou Ariki, a Ihu Karaiti
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Nhưng anh em, là kẻ rất yêu dấu, hãy nhớ lấy những lời mà các sứ đồ của Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ chúng ta đã nói trước.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Mais vous, bien-aimés, souvenez-vous des choses annoncées d`avance par les apôtres de notre Seigneur Jésus Christ.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa tsarovinareo, ry malala, ny teny voalazan'ny Apostolin'i Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika fahiny;
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ti azonban, szeretteim, emlékezzetek meg azokról a beszédekrõl, a melyeket a mi Urunk Jézus Krisztus apostolai mondottak.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ke nina, zintanda, wakhumbuleni amazwi abethethwe ngenxa engaphambili ngabo abapostile beNkosi yethu uYesu Kristu.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">사랑하는 자들아 너희는 우리 주 예수 그리스도의 사도들의 미리한 말을 기억하라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						O jūs, mylimieji, prisiminkite žodžius, kurie anksčiau buvo paskelbti mūsų Viešpaties Jėzaus Kristaus apaštalų.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Но вы, возлюбленные, помните предсказанное Апостолами Господа нашего Иисуса Христа.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tetapi Saudara-saudaraku yang tercinta, ingatlah akan apa yang dahulu dikatakan oleh rasul-rasul Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Apan kamo, mga hinigugma, kinahanglan inyong hinumduman ang mga gisulti kaniadto sa mga apostoles sa atong Ginoong Jesu-Cristo;
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ချစ်သူတို့၊ နောက်ဆုံးသောကာလ၌၊ မိမိတို့မတရားသော တပ်မက်ခြင်းအတိုင်း ကျင့်နေ၍၊ ပြက်ယယ်ပြုတတ်သော သူတို့သည် ပေါ်ကြလိမ့်မည်ဟု
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ut lâex ex inhermân, tento nak tâcuânk sa' êch'ôl eb li âtin li que'xye chak lix apóstol li Kâcua' Jesucristo.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Ale vy, milovaní, rozpamätajte sa na slová, predpovedané od apoštolov nášho Pána Ježiša Krista,
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						प्रिय मित्रहरु, हाम्रा प्रभु येशू ख्रीष्टका प्रेरितले के अगमवाणी गरेका छन्, याद गर।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A vi, ljubazni, opominjite se reči koje napred kazaše apostoli Gospoda našeg Isusa Hrista,</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men I, elskede, kom i hu de ord som forut er talt av vår Herre Jesu Kristi apostler, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Ama siz, sevgili kardeşlerim, Rabbimiz İsa Mesihin elçileri tarafından önceden söylenen sözleri anımsayın.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						واما انتم ايها الاحباء فاذكروا الاقوال التي قالها سابقا رسل ربنا يسوع المسيح.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Mas vós, amados, lembrai-vos das palavras que foram preditas pelos apóstolos de nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo;
					</lang><lang id="Latin">vos autem carissimi memores estote verborum quae praedicta sunt ab apostolis Domini nostri Iesu Christi</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Αλλα σεις, αγαπητοι, ενθυμηθητε τους λογους τους προειρημενους υπο των αποστολων του Κυριου ημων Ιησου Χριστου,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar julle, geliefdes, moet die woorde onthou wat tevore gespreek is deur die apostels van onse Here Jesus Christus,
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Men, nou menm, zanmi m' yo, toujou chonje paròl apòt Segnè Jezikri yo te di nou davans lan
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Nhưng anh_em , là kẻ rất yêu_dấu , hãy nhớ lấy những lời mà các sứ đồ của Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ chúng_ta đã nói trước .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואתם האהובים זכרו את הדברים הנאמרים מקדם ביד שליחי אדנינו ישוע המשיח׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But you, beloved, remember the words which have been spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అయితే ప్రియులారా, అంత్యకాలమునందు తమ భక్తిహీనమైన దురాశలచొప్పున నడుచు పరిహాసకులుం దురని
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						който възвести Божието слово и свидетелството Исус Христово – и всичко що е видял.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Vi pa, ljubljeni, spominjajte se besed, ki so jih naprej govorili apostoli Gospoda našega Jezusa Kristusa, da so vam rekli:
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اما شما‌ای حبیبان، بخاطر آورید آن سخنانی که رسولان خداوند ما عیسی مسیح پیش گفته‌اند،
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 I derimod, I elskede! kommer de Ord i Hu, som forud ere talte af vor Herres Jesu Kristi Apostle;
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta te, rakkaani, muistakaa nämä sanat, mitkä meidän Herramme Jeesuksen Kristuksen apostolit ovat edeltäpäin puhuneet,
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						親愛 的 弟兄 阿 、 你 們 要 記念 我 們主 耶穌基督 之 使徒 從 前所說的話
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Amma araŋ, ay baakoy, wa fongu nda sanney kaŋ iri Rabbi Yesu Almasihu diyey jin ka ci. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						親 愛 的 弟 兄 阿 、 你 們 要 記 念 我 們 主 耶 穌 基 督 之 使 徒 從 前 所 說 的 話 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						पर हे प्रियों, तुम उन बातों को स्मरण रखो; जो हमारे प्रभु यीशु मसीह के प्रेरित पहिले कह चुके हैं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Ale vy, nejmilejší, pamatujte na slova předpověděná od apoštolů Pána našeho Jezukrista.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed vi, amataj, memoru la dirojn antauxe parolitajn de la apostoloj de nia Sinjoro Jesuo Kristo;
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Ata ju thoshnin që në kohën e fundit do të ketë tallës që do të ecin sipas pasioneve të tyre të paudhësisë.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ma voi, o carissimi, ricordatevi delle cose che furono predette dagli apostoli del Signore nostro Gesù Cristo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En, þér elskaðir, minnist þeirra orða, sem áður hafa töluð verið af postulum Drottins vors Jesú Krists. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						पण, तुम्ही प्रियजनहो, आपल्या प्रभु येशू ख्रिस्ताच्या प्रेषितांनी पूर्वी सांगितलेले शब्द आठवा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						愛する者たちよ。わたしたちの主イエス・キリストの使徒たちが予告した言葉を思い出しなさい。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Pero vosotros, amados, acordaos de las palabras que antes han sido dichas por los apóstoles de nuestro Señor Jesucristo
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiinse idinku, gacaliyayaalow, xusuusta hadalladii rasuulladii Rabbigeenna Ciise Masiix ay hore idinkula hadleen.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Himahleh, deihtakte aw, noujaw i Toupa Jesu Kris sawltakten thu a genkholhte uh theigige un;
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಪ್ರಿಯರೇ, ನೀವಾದರೋ ನಮ್ಮ ಕರ್ತನಾದ ಯೇಸು ಕ್ರಿಸ್ತನ ಅಪೊಸ್ತಲರು ಮೊದಲು ಹೇಳಿದ ಮಾತುಗಳನ್ನು ಜ್ಞಾಪಕಮಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳಿರಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						But, beloved, remember ye the words which were spoken before of the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ;
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Vergeet niet, vrienden, wat de apostelen van onze Here Jezus Christus vroeger hebben gezegd:</lang><lang id="Croatian">A vi, ljubljeni, sjetite se riječi što ih prorekoše apostoli  Gospodina našega Isusa Krista.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Lecz wy, najmilsi! pamiętajcie na słowa przepowiedziane od Apostołów Pana naszego Jezusa Chrystusa;
					</lang><lang id="Thai">แต่ว่าท่านที่รักทั้งหลาย ท่านจงระลึกถึงคำพยากรณ์เมื่อก่อนของเหล่าอัครสาวกของพระเยซูคริสต์ องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าของเราที่ได้กล่าวไว้</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Nguni't kayo, mga minamahal, ay alalahanin ninyo ang mga salitang nang una'y sinabi ng mga apostol ng ating Panginoong Jesucristo; 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 愛 する 者 たち よ 。 わたし たち の 主 イエス ・ キリスト の 使徒 たち が 予告 し た 言葉 を 思い出 し なさ い 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിങ്ങളോ, പ്രിയരേ, നമ്മുടെ കര്‍ത്താവായ യേശുക്രിസ്തുവിന്റെ അപ്പൊസ്തലന്മാര്‍ മുന്‍ പറഞ്ഞ വാക്കുകളെ ഔര്‍പ്പിന്‍ .
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Dar voi, prea iubiţilor, aduceţi-vă aminte de vorbele vestite mai dinainte de apostolii Domnului nostru Isus Hristos.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Ihr aber, meine Lieben, erinnert euch der Worte, die zuvor gesagt sind von den Aposteln unsers HERRN Jesu Christi,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men kommen ihåg, I mina älskade, vad som har blivit förutsagt av vår Herres, Jesu Kristi, apostlar,
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">แต่ว่า ท่าน ที่รัก ทั้งหลาย ท่าน จง ระลึก ถึง คำ พยากรณ์ เมื่อ ก่อน ของ เหล่า อัครสาวก ของ พระ เยซู คริสต์ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ของ เรา ที่ ได้ กล่าว ไว้</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Aga teie, armsad, tuletage endile meelde need sõnad, mis meie Issanda Jeesuse Kristuse apostlid on ette kuulutanud,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.18" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						I mea hoki ratou ki a koutou, Tera e puta mai te hunga whakamanumanu a te wa whakamutunga, e haere ana i runga i o ratou hiahia karakiakore
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Các sứ đồ đó nói với anh em rằng, trong các thời kỳ sau rốt, sẽ có mấy người hay nhạo báng làm theo lòng ham muốn không tin kính của mình.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Ils vous disaient qu`au dernier temps il y aurait des moqueurs, marchant selon leurs convoitises impies;
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						fa efa nilaza taminareo hoe izy: Amin'ny andro farany dia hisy mpaniratsira, mandeha araka ny filan'ny haratsiam-panahiny.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Mert azt mondták néktek, hogy az  utolsó idõben lesznek csúfolódók, a kik az õ istentelen kívánságai szerint járnak.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ngokuba babesithi kuni, Kuya kubakho abagxeki ngexesha lokugqibela, behamba ngokwezabo iinkanuko zokungahloneli Thixo.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">그들이 너희에게 말하기를 마지막 때에 자기의 경건치 않은 정욕대로 행하며 기롱하는 자들이 있으리라 하였나니</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Jie sakė jums, kad paskutiniais laikais atsiras šaipūnų, kurie gyvens savo bedieviškais geismais.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Они говорили вам, что в последнее время появятсяругатели, поступающие по своим нечестивым похотям.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Mereka memberitahukan terlebih dahulu kepadamu bahwa menjelang akhir zaman akan muncul orang-orang yang akan mengejek kalian, yaitu orang-orang yang hidup menurut keinginan-keinginan mereka yang berdosa
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						sila miingon kaninyo, "Sa ulahiayng panahon may manungha nga mga mayubiton, nga managpahiuyon sa ilang kaugalingong dili diosnon nga mga pangibog."
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ငါတို့သခင်ယေရှုခရစ်၏ တမန်တော်တို့သည် ဟောပြောနှင့်သော စကားများကို  အောက်မေ့ကြလော့။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb li apóstol que'xye êre nak tânach'ok chak roso'jiqueb li cutan te'châlk eb laj balak' aj majecuanel. A' li mâc li naxrahi ru lix tz'ejcualeb, a'an li neque'xbânu.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						že vám hovoril, že v poslednom čase budú posmievači, ktorí budú chodiť podľa svojich bezbožných žiadostí.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						प्रेरितले तिमीहरुलाई भनेका थिए, “आखिरमा त्यहाँ मानिसहरु हुने छन् जो परमेश्वरबारे आक्षेप गर्नेछन्। तिनीहरुले आफ्नो इच्छा पूरा गर्नेछन् अनि परमेश्वर विरुद्धका कुराहरु गर्नेछन्।”
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Jer vam kazaše da će u poslednje vreme postati rugači, koji će hoditi po svojim željama i bezbožnostima.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						hvorledes de sa til eder at det i den siste tid skal komme spottere som farer frem efter sine ugudelige lyster! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Size demişlerdi ki, ‹‹Dünyanın son günlerinde alay edenler, tanrısızlığa yönelip kendi tutkularına göre yaşayanlar olacaktır.››
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						فانهم قالوا لكم انه في الزمان الاخير سيكون قوم مستهزئون سالكين بحسب شهوات فجورهم.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						os quais vos diziam: Nos últimos tempos haverá escarnecedores, andando segundo as suas ímpias concupiscências.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">quia dicebant vobis quoniam in novissimo tempore venient inlusores secundum sua desideria ambulantes impietatum</lang><lang id="Greek">
						οτι σας ελεγον οτι εν εσχατω καιρω θελουσιν εισθαι εμπαικται, περιπατουντες κατα τας ασεβεις επιθυμιας αυτων.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 dat hulle vir julle gesê het: In die laaste tyd sal daar spotters wees wat volgens hul eie goddelose begeerlikhede wandel.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Yo te di nou konsa: Lè dènye jou yo va rive, va gen anpil moun k'ap san respè pou bagay Bondye yo, moun k'ap pase nou anba betiz, moun k'ap viv dapre vye lide lanvi yo gengnen
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Các sứ đồ đó nói với anh_em rằng , trong các thời_kỳ sau_rốt , sẽ có mấy người hay nhạo_báng làm theo lòng ham_muốn không tin kính của mình .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						בדברם אליכם לאמר הנה באחרית הימים יבאו לצים ההלכים אחרי תאות רשעם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">They said to you that "In the last time there will be mockers, walking after their own ungodly lusts."</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మన ప్రభువైన యేసుక్రీస్తు అపొస్తలులు పూర్వ మందు మీతో చెప్పిన మాటలను జ్ఞాపకము చేసికొనుడి.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Блажен, който прочита, и ония, които слушат думите на това пророчество и пазят написаното в него; защото времето е близу.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						V zadnjem času bodo posmehovalci, živeči po svojih poželenjih brezbožnosti.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						چون به شما خبر دادند که در زمان آخر مستهزئین خواهند آمد که برحسب شهوات بی‌دینی خود رفتار خواهند کرد.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						thi de sagde eder: I den sidste Tid skal der være Spottere, som vandre efter deres Ugudeligheders Begæringer.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						sanoen teille: "Viimeisenä aikana tulee pilkkaajia, jotka vaeltavat jumalattomuutensa himojen mukaan".
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						他 們曾對你們說過 、 末世 必有 好 譏誚 的 人 、 隨從 自己 不敬虔 的 私慾而行
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Zama i ne araŋ se kaŋ alwaati bananta ra hahaarakoyaŋ ga kaa. I ga ngey ibaay laaley gana Irikoy wangay ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						他 們 曾 對 你 們 說 過 、 末 世 必 有 好 譏 誚 的 人 、 隨 從 自 己 不 敬 虔 的 私 慾 而 行 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						वे तुम से कहा करते थे, कि पिछले दिनों में ऐसे ठट्ठा करनेवाले होंगे, जो अपनी अभक्ति के अभिलाषाओं के अनुसार चलेंगे।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Nebo jsou pověděli vám, že v posledním času budou posměvači, podle svých bezbožných žádostí chodící.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						nome, ke ili diris al vi:En la lasta tempo estos mokemuloj, irantaj laux siaj propraj voluptoj malpiaj.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Këta janë ata që shkaktojnë përçarjet, njerëz mishor, që s'kanë Frymën.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Essi vi dicevano: «Alla fine dei tempi vi saranno impostori, che si comporteranno secondo le loro empie passioni»
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þeir sögðu við yður: "Á síðasta tíma munu koma spottarar, sem stjórnast af sínum eigin óguðlegu girndum." 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						त्यांनी सांगितले, “काळाच्या शेवटी देवाविषयी थट्टेने बोलणारे लोक असतील, ते त्यांच्या स्वत:च्याच अधार्मिक इच्छांच्या मागे जातील.”
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						彼らはあなたがたにこう言った、「終りの時に、あざける者たちがあらわれて、自分の不信心な欲のままに生活するであろう」。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						porque ellos os decían: "En los últimos tiempos habrá burladores que andarán según sus propias pasiones, como impíos que son.
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Waxay idinku yidhaahdeen, Ugu dambaysta waxaa jiri doona kuwa wax ku majaajilooda, oo daba socda damacyadooda aan cibaadada lahayn.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						hunnanungah te Pathian limsak loulam amau utna bang jela omin, nuihsanhatte a hongom ding uhi, chih na kiang ua a gendan khawng uh.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಭಕ್ತಿಗೆ ವಿರುದ್ಧವಾದ ತಮ್ಮ ಆಶೆಗಳನ್ನು ಅನುಸರಿಸಿ ನಡೆಯುವ ಕುಚೋದ್ಯಗಾರರು ಅಂತ್ಯಕಾಲದಲ್ಲಿ ಇರುವರೆಂದು ಅವರು ನಿಮಗೆ ಹೇಳಿದರು.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						How that they told you there should be mockers in the last time, who should walk after their own ungodly lusts.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">"Tegen het einde van de tijd zullen er spotters komen, die zich aan hun onreine verlangens overgeven."</lang><lang id="Croatian">Oni vam govorahu: "U posljednje  će vrijeme biti podrugljivaca koji će se povoditi za bezbožnim  požudama svojim."</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Iż wam powiadali, że w ostateczny czas będą naśmiewcy, chodzący według swoich niezbożnych pożądliwości.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คือว่า พวกอัครสาวกนั้นได้บอกท่านทั้งหลายว่า "ในสมัยสุดท้ายจะมีคนเยาะเย้ยบังเกิดขึ้น เขาเป็นคนที่ดำเนินตามตัณหาอันชั่วของตัว"</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Kung paanong sinabi sa inyo, Magkakaroon ng mga manunuya sa huling panahon, na magsisilakad ayon sa kanikanilang masasamang pita. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 彼 ら は あなた がた に こう 言 っ た 、 「 終り の 時 に 、 あざけ る 者 たち が あらわれ て 、 自分 の 不信心 な 欲 の まま に 生活 する で あ ろ う 」 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അന്ത്യകാലത്തു ഭക്തികെട്ട മോഹങ്ങളെ അനുസരിച്ചു നടക്കുന്ന പരിഹാസികള്‍ ഉണ്ടാകും എന്നു അവര്‍ നിങ്ങളോടു പറഞ്ഞുവല്ലോ.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Cum vă spuneau că în vremurile din urmă vor fi batjocoritori, cari vor trăi după poftele lor nelegiuite.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						da sie euch sagten, daß zu der letzten Zeit werden Spötter sein, die nach ihren eigenen Lüsten des gottlosen Wesens wandeln.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						huru de sade till eder: »I den yttersta tiden skola bespottare uppstå, som vandra efter sina egna ogudaktiga begärelser.»
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คือ ว่า พวก อัครสาวก นั้น ได้ บอก ท่าน ทั้งหลาย ว่า " ใน สมัย สุดท้าย จะ มีค น เยาะ เย้ย บังเกิด ขึ้น เขา เป็น คน ที่ ดำเนิน ตาม ตัณหา อัน ชั่ว ของ ตัว "</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						kui nad teile ütlesid, et viimsel ajal tuleb pilkajaid, kes käivad oma õelate himude järgi.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.19" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na enei nga titorehanga, he hunga hiahia hoki ki te kikokiko kahore nei i a ratou te Wairua
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Ấy chính chúng nó là kẻ gây nên phe đảng, thuộc về tánh xác thịt, không có Ðức Thánh Linh.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						ce sont ceux qui provoquent des divisions, hommes sensuels, n`ayant pas l`esprit.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ireo no mahatonga fisarahana, dia olona araka ny nofo ihany, fa tsy mba manana ny Fanahy. [ Na: tsy mba manana fanahy]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						ek azok, a kik különszakadnak, érzékiek, kikben nincsen [Szent ]Lélek.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Aba ngabazahlukanisayo, bengabemvelo, uMoya bengenaye.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">이 사람들은 당을 짓는 자며 육에 속한 자며 성령은 없는 자니라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tai tie, kurie įneša susiskaldymą, sieliniai, neturintys Dvasios žmonės.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Это люди, отделяющие себя(от единства веры), душевные, не имеющие духа.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Mereka inilah orang-orang yang menimbulkan perpecahan. Mereka tidak dikuasai oleh Roh Allah, melainkan oleh keinginan-keinginan tabiat duniawi
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Mao kini sila ang nagahimog mga pagbahinbahin, mga tawong kalibutanon nga wala magabaton sa Espiritu.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိုသူတို့သည်သင်းခွဲသောသူ၊ ဝိညာဉ်တော်နှင့် ကင်းသော ဇာတိပကတိလူဖြစ်ကြ၏။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Eb li cuînk a'in, a'aneb li neque'yo'oban jachoc ib. Neque'xrahi ru lix mâusilal li ruchich'och' ut li Santil Musik'ej mâc'a' riq'uineb.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						To sú tí, ktorí sa oddeľujú, telesní, nemajúci ducha.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						यी मानिसहरु तिनीहरुका पापमय आत्माले खोजेको मात्र गर्छन्। तिनीहरुको आत्मा हुँदैन।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Ovo su oni što se odvajaju (od jedinosti vere), i jesu telesni, koji duha nemaju.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Disse er de som skiller sig ut, naturlige mennesker, som ikke har ånd. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Bunlar bölücü, insan doğasıyla sınırlı, Kutsal Ruhtan yoksun kişilerdir.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						هؤلاء هم المعتزلون بانفسهم نفسانيون لا روح لهم
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Estes são os que causam divisões; são sensuais, e não têm o Espírito.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">hii sunt qui segregant animales Spiritum non habentes</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Ουτοι ειναι οι αποχωριζοντες εαυτους, ζωωδεις, Πνευμα μη εχοντες.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Dit is hulle wat skeuring maak, sinnelike mense wat die Gees nie het nie.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Se moun sa yo k'ap simen divizyon. Yo kite egzijans lachè dominen yo. Se pa Lespri Bondye a k'ap dirije lavi yo
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Ấy chính chúng_nó là kẻ gây nên phe_đảng , thuộc về tánh xác_thịt , không có Ðức_Thánh_Linh .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						אלה הם הפרשים מן הצבור אנשים נפשיים ורוח אין בהם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">These are they who cause divisions, and are sensual, not having the Spirit.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అట్టివారు ప్రకృతి సంబంధులును ఆత్మ లేనివారునైయుండి భేదములు కలుగజేయుచున్నారు.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Иоан до седемте църкви, които са в Азия: Благодат и мир да бъде на вас от Онзи, Който е, и Който е бил, и Който иде, и от седемте духове, които са пред неговия престол,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Ti so, ki napravljajo razkole, živinski, ne imajoč duha.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اینانند که تفرقه‌ها پیدا می‌کنند و نفسانی هستند که روح را ندارند.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Disse ere de, som volde Splittelser, sjælelige, som ikke have Ånd.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Nämä juuri saavat aikaan hajaannusta, he ovat sielullisia, henkeä heillä ei ole.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						這 就 是 那些 引人 結黨 、 屬乎血氣 、 沒有 聖靈 的 人
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Borey din ga ti borey kaŋ yaŋ goono ga fay-fayyaŋ te, i goono ga ngey Adam-ize daa laala gana, i sinda Biya _Hanno|_ mo. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						這 就 是 那 些 引 人 結 黨 、 屬 乎 血 氣 、 沒 有 聖 靈 的 人 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						ये तो वे है, जो फूट डालते हैं; ये शारीरिक लोग हैं, जिन में आत्मा नहीं।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Toť jsou ti, kteříž se sami odtrhují, lidé hovadní, Ducha Kristova nemající.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Tiuj estas la apartigantoj, lauxsentaj, ne havantaj la Spiriton.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Por ju, shumë të dashur, duke ndërtuar veten tuaj mbi besimin tuaj shumë të shenjtë, duke u lutur në Frymën e Shenjtë,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Tali sono quelli che provocano divisioni, gente materiale, privi dello Spirito
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Þessir menn eru þeir, sem valda sundrungu, holdlegir menn, sem eigi hafa andann. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						असे लोक फूट पाडतात. ते त्यांच्या मूळ स्वभावाप्रमाणे चालतात. त्यांना आत्मा नाही.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						彼らは分派をつくる者、肉に属する者、御霊を持たない者たちである。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Éstos son los que causan divisiones. Son sensuales y no tienen al Espíritu
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwanu waa kuwa dadka kala erya, oo nafta dunida u nool iyagoo aan Ruuxa lahayn.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Huai mite tuh sa mi, Kha neilou, pawl tuamte bawlte tuh ahi uhi.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಇವರು ತಮ್ಮನ್ನು ತಾವು ಪ್ರತ್ಯೇಕಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುವವರೂ ಪ್ರಾಕೃತಮನುಷ್ಯರೂ ಆತ್ಮವಿಲ್ಲದವರೂ ಆಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						These be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the Spirit.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Die mannen maken onderscheid tussen de ene christen en de andere. Zij doen dat omdat zij louter menselijk zijn en de Geest van God niet hebben.</lang><lang id="Croatian">To su sijači razdora, sjetilnici koji nemaju  Duha.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Cić są, którzy się sami odłączają, bydlęcy, ducha Chrystusowego nie mający.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">คนเหล่านี้คือคนที่แยกตัวออกมาและประพฤติตัวตามโลกียวิสัย และปราศจากพระวิญญาณ</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ang mga ito ang nagsisigawa ng paghihiwalay, malalayaw, na walang taglay na Espiritu. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 彼 ら は 分派 を つく る 者 、 肉 に 属 する 者 、 御 霊 を 持 た な い 者 たち で あ る 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						അവര്‍ ഭിന്നത ഉണ്ടാക്കുന്നവര്‍, പ്രാകൃതന്മാര്‍, ആത്മാവില്ലാത്തവര്‍.
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Ei sînt aceia cari dau naştere la dezbinări, oameni supuşi poftelor firii, cari n'au Duhul.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Diese sind es, die da Trennungen machen, Fleischliche, die da keinen Geist haben.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Det är dessa människor som vålla söndringar, dessa som äro »själiska» och icke hava ande.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">คน เหล่า นี้ คือ คน ที่ แยก ตัว ออก มา และ ประพฤติ ตัว ตามโลกียวิสัย และ ปราศจาก พระ วิญญาณ</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Need on need, kes tekitavad lõhenemisi, maised, kellel ei ole Vaimu.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.20" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko koutou ia, e nga hoa aroha, hanga ake koutou hei whare ki runga ki to koutou whakapono tapu rawa, me te inoi ano i roto i te Wairua Tapu
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Hỡi kẻ rất yêu dấu, về phần anh em, hãy tự lập lấy trên nền đức tin rất thánh của mình, và nhơn Ðức Thánh Linh mà cầu nguyện,
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Pour vous, bien-aimés, vous édifiant vous-mêmes sur votre très sainte foi, et priant par le Saint Esprit,
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Fa ianareo kosa, ry malala, dia ataovy izay handrosoanareo amin'ny finoanareo masina indrindra, ka mivavaha ao amin'ny Fanahy Masina;
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Ti pedig szeretteim, épülvén a ti szentséges hitetekben, imádkozván Szent Lélek által,
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Ke nina, zintanda, zakheni elukholweni lwenu olungcwele kanye, nithandaza nikuMoya oyiNgcwele.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">사랑하는 자들아 너희는 너희의 지극히 거룩한 믿음 위에 자기를 건축하며 성령으로 기도하며</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Bet jūs, mylimieji, statydami save ant savo švenčiausiojo tikėjimo, melsdamiesi Šventojoje Dvasioje,
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						А вы, возлюбленные, назидая себя на святейшей вере вашей, молясь Духом Святым,
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tetapi kalian, Saudara-saudaraku, binalah terus hidupmu berdasarkan percayamu kepada Yesus Kristus. Imanmu itu sangat suci. Sementara itu berdoalah dengan kuasa Roh Allah
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Apan kamo, mga hinigugma, kinahanglan managtubo diha sa inyong balaan uyamot nga tinoohan; pag-ampo kamo diha sa Espiritu Santo;
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ချစ်သူတို့၊ သင်တို့သည် မိမိတို့အလွန်သန့်ရှင်းသော ယုံကြည်ခြင်းအပေါ်မှာ မိမိတို့ကို တည်ဆောက် လျက်၊ သန့်ရှင်းသောဝိညာဉ်တော်အားဖြင့် ဆုတောင်း ပဌာနပြုလျက်၊
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						A'ut lâex, ex inhermân, cauhak taxak êch'ôl sa' lê santil pâbâl. Ut chextijok riq'uin xcuanquil li Santil Musik'ej.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						Ale vy, milovaní budujúc sa na svojej presvätej viere,
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तर प्रिय मित्रहरु, तिमीहरु स्वयंलाई दृढ तुल्याउनका निम्ति तिमीहरुका अति पवित्र विश्वास उपयोग गर। पवित्र आत्मासित प्रार्थना गर।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A vi, ljubazni, nazidjujte se svojom svetom verom, i molite se Bogu Duhom Svetim.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men I, elskede, opbygg eder på eders høihellige tro, bed i den Hellige Ånd, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Ama siz, sevgili kardeşlerim, kendinizi tümden kutsal olan imanınızın temeli üzerinde geliştirin. Kutsal Ruhun yönetiminde dua edin.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						واما انتم ايها الاحباء فابنوا انفسكم على ايمانكم الاقدس مصلّين في الروح القدس
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Mas vós, amados, edificando-vos sobre a vossa santíssima fé, orando no Espírito Santo,
					</lang><lang id="Latin">vos autem carissimi superaedificantes vosmet ipsos sanctissimae vestrae fidei in Spiritu Sancto orantes</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Σεις ομως, αγαπητοι, εποικοδομουντες εαυτους επι την αγιωτατην πιστιν σας, προσευχομενοι εν Πνευματι Αγιω,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Maar julle, geliefdes, moet julleself opbou in jul allerheiligste geloof en in die Heilige Gees bid
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Men, nou menm, mezanmi, annou kontinye grandi toujou nan konfyans nou k'ap fè nou viv pou Bondye nèt ale. Avèk pouvwa Sentespri a, annou lapriyè san rete
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Hỡi kẻ rất yêu_dấu , về phần anh_em , hãy tự_lập lấy trên nền đức_tin rất thánh của mình , và nhơn Ðức_Thánh_Linh mà cầu_nguyện ,
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואתם האהובים הבנו באמונתכם הנעלה על כל בקדשתה והתפללו ברוח הקדש׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">But you, beloved, keep building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						ప్రియులారా, మీరు విశ్వసించు అతిపరిశుద్దమైనదానిమీద మిమ్మును మీరు కట్టుకొనుచు, పరిశుద్ధాత్మలో ప్రార్థనచేయుచు,
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						и от Исуса Христа, който е верният свидетел, първороденият от мъртвите и началникът на земните царе. На Този, Който ни люби, и ни е развързал от греховете ни чрез кръвта Си,
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Vi pa, ljubljeni, sezidavajte se na presveti veri svoji in molite v svetem Duhu,
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						اما شما‌ای حبیبان، خود را به ایمان اقدس خود بنا کرده و در روح‌القدس عبادت نموده،
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						I derimod, I elskede! opbygger eder selv på eders helligste Tro; beder i den Helligånd;
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta te, rakkaani, rakentakaa itseänne pyhimmän uskonne perustukselle, rukoilkaa Pyhässä Hengessä
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						親愛 的 弟兄 阿 、 你 們卻 要 在 至聖 的 真 道上 造就 自己 、 在 聖靈 裡 禱告
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Amma araŋ, ay baakoy, wa araŋ boŋ cina araŋ cimbeeri hanna boŋ. Wa adduwa te Biya Hanno ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						親 愛 的 弟 兄 阿 、 你 們 卻 要 在 至 聖 的 真 道 上 造 就 自 己 、 在 聖 靈 裡 禱 告 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						पर हे प्रियों तुम अपने अति पवित्रा विश्वास में अपनी उन्नति करते हुए और पवित्रा आत्मा में प्रार्थना करते हुए।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Ale vy, nejmilejší, vzdělávajíce se na té nejsvětější víře vaší, v Duchu svatém modléce se,
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Sed vi, amataj, konstruante vin sur via plej sankta fido, pregxante en la Sankta Spirito,
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						ruhuni në dashurinë e Perëndisë, duke pritur mëshirën e Zotit tonë Jezu Krisht, për jetën e përjetshme.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Ma voi, carissimi, costruite il vostro edificio spirituale sopra la vostra santissima fede, pregate mediante lo Spirito Santo
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En þér, elskaðir, byggið yður sjálfa upp í yðar helgustu trú. Biðjið í heilögum anda. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						पण तुम्ही प्रिय मित्रांनो, आपल्यापवित्र शिकविण्यात आलेल्या विश्वासात परस्परांना आध्यात्मिक रीतीने बळकट करा. पवित्र आत्म्याने युक्त होऊन प्रार्थना करा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						しかし、愛する者たちよ。あなたがたは、最も神聖な信仰の上に自らを築き上げ、聖霊によって祈り、
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Pero vosotros, oh amados, edificándoos sobre vuestra santísima fe y orando en el Espíritu Santo
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Laakiinse, gacaliyayaalow, nafsaddiinna ku dul dhisa rumaysadkiinna aad quduuska u ah, oo Ruuxa Quduuska ah ku tukada,
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Himahleh, deihtakte, nou jaw na ginna siangthou uh tunga noumau leh noumau kilem touin, Kha Siangthoua thumin,
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಪ್ರಿಯರೇ, ನೀವಾ ದರೋ ನಿಮಗಿರುವ ಅತಿಪರಿಶುದ್ಧವಾದ ನಂಬಿಕೆಯ ಮೇಲೆ ನಿಮ್ಮನ್ನು ನೀವೇ ಕಟ್ಟಿಕೊಂಡು ಪರಿಶುದ್ಧಾತ್ಮನಲ್ಲಿ ಪ್ರಾರ್ಥಿಸಿರಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						But ye, beloved, building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Ghost,
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Maar, vrienden, u moet uw allerheiligst geloof sterker laten worden en u bij uw bidden laten leiden door de Heilige Geest.</lang><lang id="Croatian">A vi, ljubljeni, naziđujte se na presvetoj vjeri svojoj  moleći se u Duhu Svetom,</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Ale wy najmilsi! budując się na najświętszej wierze waszej i modląc się w Duchu Świętym,
					</lang><lang id="Thai">ทรงบัญชาให้อธิษฐานและเป็นพยานแต่ท่านทั้งหลายผู้เป็นที่รัก จงก่อสร้างตัวของท่านขึ้นบนความเชื่ออันบริสุทธิ์ยิ่งของท่าน โดยการอธิษฐานด้วยพระวิญญาณบริสุทธิ์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Nguni't kayo, mga minamahal, papagtibayin ninyo ang inyong sarili sa inyong lubhang banal na pananampalataya, na manalangin sa Espiritu Santo, 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 しかし 、 愛 する 者 たち よ 。 あなた がた は 、 最も 神聖 な 信仰 の 上 に 自ら を 築き上げ 、 聖霊 に よ っ て 祈 り 、
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നിങ്ങളോ, പ്രിയമുള്ളവരേ, നിങ്ങളുടെ അതിവിശുദ്ധ വിശ്വാസത്തെ ആധാരമാക്കി നിങ്ങള്‍ക്കു തന്നേ ആത്മികവര്‍ദ്ധന വരുത്തിയും പരിശുദ്ധാത്മാവില്‍ പ്രാര്‍ത്ഥിച്ചും നിത്യജീവന്നായിട്ടു
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Dar voi, prea iubiţilor, zidiţi-vă sufleteşte pe credinţa voastră prea sfîntă, rugaţi-vă prin Duhul Sfînt,
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Ihr aber, meine Lieben, erbauet euch auf euren allerheiligsten Glauben durch den heiligen Geist und betet,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men I, mina älskade, uppbyggen eder på eder allraheligaste tro, bedjen i den helige Ande,
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">ทรง บัญชา ให้ อธิษฐาน และ เป็น พยาน แต่ ท่าน ทั้งหลาย ผู้ เป็น ที่รัก จง ก่อสร้าง ตัว ของ ท่าน ขึ้น บน ความ เชื่อ อัน บริสุทธิ์ ยิ่ง ของ ท่าน โดย การ อธิษฐาน ด้วย พระ วิญญาณ บริสุทธิ์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Aga teie, armsad, rajage endid oma pühimale usule ja palvetage Pühas Vaimus,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.21" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Me te tiaki ano i a koutou i runga i te aroha o te Atua, me te tatari ano ki te mahi tohu a to tatou Ariki, a Ihu Karaiti, a te ora tonu ra ano
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						hãy giữ mình trong sự yêu mến Ðức Chúa Trời, và trông đợi sự thương xót của Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ chúng ta cho được sự sống đời đời.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						maintenez-vous dans l`amour de Dieu, en attendant la miséricorde de notre Seigneur Jésus Christ pour la vie éternelle.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						ary tehirizo ny tenanareo ao amin'ny fitiavan'Andriamanitra, miandry ny famindram-pon'i Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika ho fiainana mandrakizay.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Tartsátok meg magatokat Istennek szeretetében, várván a mi Urunk Jézus Krisztusnak irgalmasságát az örök életre.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Hlalani nihleli eluthandweni lukaThixo, niyilinde inceba yeNkosi yethu uYesu Kristu, kuse ebomini obungunaphakade.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">하나님의 사랑 안에서 자기를 지키며 영생에 이르도록 우리 주 예수 그리스도의 긍휼을 기다리라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						išsilaikykite Dievo meilėje, laukdami mūsų Viešpaties Jėzaus Kristaus gailestingumo amžinajam gyvenimui.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						сохраняйте себя в любви Божией, ожидая милости отГоспода нашего Иисуса Христа, для вечной жизни.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						dan hiduplah selalu di dalam naungan kasih Allah selama kalian menantikan rahmat Yesus Kristus Tuhan kita, yang akan memberikan kepadamu hidup sejati dan kekal
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						bantayi ninyo ang inyong kaugalingon diha sa gugma sa Dios; paabuta ninyo ang kalooy sa atong Ginoong Jesu-Cristo, alang sa kinabuhing dayon.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ဘုရားသခင်ကို ချစ်ခြင်းမေတ္တာ၌ ကိုယ်ကိုကိုယ်စောင့်ရှောက်၍ ထာဝရအသက်အလိုငှါ၊ ငါတို့သခင် ယေရှုခရစ်၏ ကရုဏာတော်ကို မြော်လင့်၍ နေကြာလော့။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Chenauhak nak nequexra li Dios ut inc'a' chicuibânk êch'ôl. Cheroybenihak nak tol-êlk li Kâcua' Jesucristo ut riq'uin lix nimal ruxtân tixq'ue lê yu'am chi junelic.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						modliac sa v Svätom Duchu, strážiac zachovajte sa v láske Božej očakávajúc milosrdenstvo nášho Pána Ježiša Krista cieľom večného života.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमीहरु स्वयंलाई परमेश्वरको प्रेममा राख। तिमीहरुलाई सदाको निम्ति जीवन प्रदान गर्न उहाँका कृपा सहित प्रभु येशू ख्रीष्टको प्रतीक्षा गर।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I sami sebe držite u ljubavi Božijoj, čekajući milost Gospoda našeg Isusa Hrista za život večni.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						og hold eder således i Guds kjærlighet, mens I venter på vår Herre Jesu Kristi miskunn til evig liv! 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Rabbimiz İsa Mesihin sizi sonsuz yaşama kavuşturacak olan merhametini beklerken kendinizi Tanrının sevgisinde koruyun.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						واحفظوا انفسكم في محبة الله منتظرين رحمة ربنا يسوع المسيح للحياة الابدية.
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						conservai-vos no amor de Deus, esperando a misericórdia de nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo para a vida eterna.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">ipsos vos in dilectione Dei servate</lang><lang id="Greek">
						φυλαξατε εαυτους εις την αγαπην του Θεου, προσμενοντες το ελεος του Κυριου ημων Ιησου Χριστου, εις ζωην αιωνιον.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 en julleself in die liefde van God bewaar, terwyl julle die barmhartigheid van onse Here Jesus Christus tot die ewige lewe verwag.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Rete fèm nan renmen nou gen pou Bondye a, pandan n'ap tann Segnè nou, Jezikri, k'ap vin ban nou lavi ki p'ap fini an paske li gen pitye pou nou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						hãy giữ_mình trong sự yêu_mến Ðức_Chúa_Trời , và trông_đợi sự thương_xót của Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ chúng_ta cho được sự sống đời_đời .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ושמרתם את נפשתיכם באהבת אלהים וחכיתם לרחמי אדנינו ישוע המשיח לחיי העולם׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ to eternal life.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						నిత్య జీవార్థమైన మన ప్రభువగు యేసుక్రీస్తు కనికరముకొరకు కనిపెట్టుచు, దేవుని ప్రేమలో నిలుచునట్లు కాచుకొని యుండుడి.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						и Който ни е направил Царство от свещеници на своя Бог и Отец, на Него да бъде слава и господство във вечни векове. Амин.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						ohranite se v ljubezni Božji, pričakujte usmiljenja Gospoda našega Jezusa Kristusa, za večno življenje!
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						خویشتن را در محبت خدا محفوظ دارید ومنتظر رحمت خداوند ما عیسی مسیح برای حیات جاودانی بوده باشید.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						bevarer således eder selv i Guds Kærlighed, forventende vor Herres Jesu Kristi Barmhjertighed til evigt Liv.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						ja pysyttäkää niin itsenne Jumalan rakkaudessa, odottaessanne meidän Herramme Jeesuksen Kristuksen laupeutta iankaikkiseksi elämäksi.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						保守 自己 常在 神 的 愛中 、 仰望 我 們主 耶穌基督 的 憐憫 、 直 到 永生
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Wa araŋ boŋ gaay Irikoy baakasina ra, waati kaŋ araŋ goono g'iri Rabbi Yesu Almasihu suujo batu ka koy fundi hal abada do. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						保 守 自 己 常 在 　 神 的 愛 中 、 仰 望 我 們 主 耶 穌 基 督 的 憐 憫 、 直 到 永 生 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						अपने आप को परमेश्वर के प्रेम में बनाए रखो; और अनन्त जीवन के लिये हमारे प्रभु यीशु मसीह की दया की आशा देखते रहो।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Ostříhejte se v lásce Boží, očekávajíce milosrdenství Pána našeho Jezukrista k věčnému životu.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						konservu vin en la amo al Dio, atendante la kompaton de nia Sinjoro Jesuo Kristo por eterna vivo.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Dhe kini dhemshuri për njëri duke përdorur dallim,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						conservatevi nell'amore di Dio, attendendo la misericordia del Signore nostro Gesù Cristo per la vita eterna
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Varðveitið sjálfa yður í kærleika Guðs, og bíðið eftir náð Drottins vors Jesú Krists til eilífs lífs. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						आणि तुम्हांला अनंतकाळच्या जीवनात घेऊन जाणाऱ्या आपल्या प्रभु येशू ख्रिस्ताच्या कृपेची वाट पाहत, देवाच्या प्रीतीत स्वत:ला राखा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						神の愛の中に自らを保ち、永遠のいのちを目あてとして、わたしたちの主イエス・キリストのあわれみを待ち望みなさい。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						conservaos en el amor de Dios, aguardando con esperanza la misericordia de nuestro Señor Jesucristo para vida eterna
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						nafsaddiinna ku haya jacaylka Ilaah, idinkoo sugaya naxariista Rabbigeenna Ciise Masiix oo idin geeynaysa nolosha weligeed ah.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						khantawn hinna neihsakna khop i Toupa Jesu Kris hehpihna tuh ngak kawmin, Pathian itna a kikem hoih un.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ನಿತ್ಯಜೀವಕ್ಕಾಗಿ ನಮ್ಮ ಕರ್ತನಾದ ಯೇಸು ಕ್ರಿಸ್ತನ ಕರುಣೆಗೋಸ್ಕರ ಎದುರು ನೋಡುತ್ತಾ ನಿಮ್ಮನ್ನು ದೇವರ ಪ್ರೀತಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಕಾಪಾಡಿಕೊಳ್ಳಿರಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Blijf bereikbaar voor de liefde van God. Wacht geduldig op het eeuwige leven, dat onze Here Jezus Christus ons in Zijn goedheid zal geven.</lang><lang id="Croatian">uščuvajte se u ljubavi Božjoj, iščekujući  milosrđe Gospodina našega Isusa Krista za vječni život.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Samych siebie w miłości Bożej zachowajcie, oczekując miłosierdzia Pana naszego, Jezusa Chrystusa, ku żywotowi wiecznemu.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">จงรักษาตัวไว้ในความรักของพระเจ้า คอยพระกรุณาของพระเยซูคริสต์องค์พระผู้เป็นเจ้าของเราจนถึงชีวิตนิรันดร์</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Na magsipanatili kayo sa pagibig sa Dios, na inyong asahan ang awa ng ating Panginoong Jesucristo sa ikabubuhay na walang hanggan. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 神 の 愛 の 中 に 自ら を 保 ち 、 永遠 の いのち を 目あて と し て 、 わたし たち の 主 イエス ・ キリスト の あわれみ を 待ち 望 み なさ い 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						നമ്മുടെ കര്‍ത്താവായ യേശുക്രിസ്തുവിന്റെ കരുണെക്കായി കാത്തിരുന്നുംകൊണ്ടു ദൈവസ്നേഹത്തില്‍ നിങ്ങളെത്തന്നേ സൂക്ഷിച്ചുകൊള്‍വിന്‍ .
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						ţineţi-vă în dragostea lui Dumnezeu, şi aşteptaţi îndurarea Domnului nostru Isus Hristos pentru viaţa vecinică.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						und erhaltet euch in der Liebe Gottes, und wartet auf die Barmherzigkeit unsers HERRN Jesu Christi zum ewigen Leben.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						och bevaren eder så i Guds kärlek, under det att I vänten på vår Herres, Jesu Kristi, barmhärtighet, till evigt liv.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">จง รักษา ตัว ไว้ ใน ความ รัก ของ พระเจ้า คอย พระ กรุณา ของ พระ เยซู คริสต์ องค์ พระผู้เป็นเจ้า ของ เรา จนถึง ชีวิตนิรันดร์</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						ja hoidke endid Jumala armastuses ja oodake meie Issanda Jeesuse Kristuse halastust igaveseks eluks.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.22" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko etahi ano tohungia, e ruarua tonu nei nga whakaaro
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Hãy trách phạt những kẻ nấy, là kẻ trù trừ,
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Reprenez les uns, ceux qui contestent;
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary amindrao fo ny sasany izay miahanahana; [ Na: raha miady aminareo izy]
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						És könyörüljetek némelyeken, megkülönböztetvén õket.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Inxenye okunene yenzeleni inceba, nicalula;
					</lang><lang id="Korean">어떤 의심하는 자들을 긍휼히 여기라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Vieniems, kurie abejoja, būkite gailestingi,
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						И к одним будьте милостивы, с рассмотрением,
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Terhadap orang-orang yang bimbang hatinya, hendaklah kalian menunjukkan belas kasihan
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Ug patooha ninyo ang uban nga nagaduhaduha;
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ပိုင်းခြား၍သိတတ်သော ဥာဏ်ရှိ၍ အချို့တို့ကို သနားကြလော့။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Cheq'uehak xna'lebeb li neque'cuiban xch'ôl.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A nad niektorými majte ľútosť [karhajúc ich a] robiac rozdiel
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						जो मानिसहरु सन्देह गर्छन् तिनीहरुलाई दया देखाऊ। तिमीहरुले कोही मानिसहरुलाई बचाँउनु आवश्यक छ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">I tako razlikujući jedne milujte.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Og nogen skal I tale til rette fordi de tviler, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Kimi kararsızlara merhamet edin.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						وارحموا البعض مميّزين
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						E apiedai-vos de alguns que estão na dúvida,
					</lang><lang id="Latin">et hos quidem arguite iudicatos</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Και αλλους μεν ελεειτε, καμνοντες διακρισιν,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 En aan sommige wat twyfel, moet julle barmhartigheid bewys;
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Gen pitye pou frè yo ki nan doutans toujou
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Hãy trách phạt những kẻ nấy , là kẻ trù_trừ ,
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						הבדילו את אלה והתנהגו עמהם ברחמים׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">On some have compassion, making a distinction,</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						సందేహపడువారిమీద కనికరము చూపుడి.
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Ето, иде с облаците; и ще Го види всяко око, и ония, които го прободоха; и всички земни племена ще възридаят за Него. Така е. Амин.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						In nekatere prepričujte, ki so v dvomih;
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و بعضی را که مجادله می‌کنند ملزم سازید.
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						Og revser nogle, når de tvivle,
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Ja armahtakaa toisia, niitä, jotka epäilevät, pelastakaa heidät, tulesta temmaten;
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						有些 人 存 疑心 、 你 們要 憐憫 他 們
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Wa suuji cabe boro fooyaŋ kaŋ gonda sikkayaŋ se. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						有 些 人 存 疑 心 、 你 們 要 憐 憫 他 們 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						और उन पर जो शंका में हैं दया करो।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						A nad některými zajisté lítost mějte, rozeznání v tom majíce.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj unujn, kiuj sxanceligxas, indulgu;
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						por shpëtojini të tjerët me druajtje, duke ia rrëmbyer zjarrit, dhe duke urryer edhe rroben e ndotur nga mishi.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						Convincete quelli che sono vacillanti
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    Verið mildir við suma, þá sem eru efablandnir, 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						विश्वासात डळमळीत असलेल्या लोकांवर दया करा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						疑いをいだく人々があれば、彼らをあわれみ、
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						De algunos que vacilan tened misericordia
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Kuwa shakisan u naxariista;
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Khenkhatte, ginglaha omte tuh hehpih unla;
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ತಾರತಮ್ಯ ನೋಡಿ ಕೆಲವರಿಗೆ ಕನಿಕರವನ್ನು ತೋರಿ ಸಿರಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And of some have compassion, making a difference:
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Leef mee met de mensen die twijfelen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">I  jedne, svadljivce, karajte,</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A nad niektórymi zmiłujcie się, rozsądkiem się rządząc;
					</lang><lang id="Thai">และจงแสดงความเมตตาต่อบางคน โดยรู้ความต่างกัน</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang ibang nagaalinlangan ay inyong kahabagan; 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 疑い を いだ く 人々 が あ れ ば 、 彼 ら を あわれ み 、
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						സംശയിക്കുന്നവരായ ചിലരോടു കരുണ ചെയ്‍വിന്‍ ;
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Mustraţi pe cei ce se despart de voi;
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Und haltet diesen Unterschied, daß ihr euch etlicher erbarmet,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Mot somliga av dem, sådana som äro tvivlande, mån I vara barmhärtiga
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">และ จง แสดง ความ เมตตา ต่อ บาง คน โดย รู้ความ ต่าง กัน</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Ja halastage teiste peale, kes kahtlevad,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.23" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Ko etahi me whakaora, ka to mai i roto i te kapura; a ko etahi tohungia i runga i te mataku; me te weriweri rawa ki te kakahu i poke i te kikokiko
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						hãy cứu vớt những kẻ kia, rút họ ra khỏi lửa; còn đối với kẻ khác, hãy có lòng thương lẫn với sợ, ghét cả đến cái áo bị xác thịt làm ô uế.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						sauvez-en d`autres en les arrachant du feu; et pour d`autres encore, ayez une pitié mêlée de crainte, haïssant jusqu`à la tunique souillée par la chair.
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						ary ny sasany kosa sariho avy amin'ny afo no famonjy azy; ary ny sasany indray amindrao fo amin-tahotra, ka mankahalà na dia ny akanjo voapentimpentin'ny nofo aza.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Másokat pedig  rettentéssel mentsetek meg, kiragadva õket a tûzbõl, és útálva még a  ruhát is, a melyet a test beszennyezett.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						kodwa inxenye yisindiseni nizoyikela, nibaphanga emlilweni,  niyithiya nengubo edyojiweyo yinyama.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">또 어떤 자를 불에서 끌어내어 구원하라 또 어떤 자를 그 육체로 더럽힌 옷이라도 싫어하여 두려움으로 긍휼히 여기라</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						kitus bijodami gelbėkite, traukdami iš ugnies, bodėdamiesi net jų kūnu suteršto drabužio.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						а других страхом спасайте, исторгая из огня, обличайте же со страхом, гнушаясь даже одеждою, которая осквернена плотью.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Tariklah orang keluar dari dalam api untuk menyelamatkan mereka. Terhadap orang-orang lainnya hendaklah kalian menunjukkan belas kasihan disertai perasaan takut, tetapi bencilah bahkan pakaian mereka pun yang telah dikotori dengan keinginan mereka yang berdosa
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						luwasa ninyo ang uban pinaagi sa pagsakmit kanila gikan sa kalayo; ang uban kaloy-i ninyo dinuyogan sa kahadlok, nga pagadumtan ninyo bisan pa ang bisti nga nabuling sa unod.
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ကိုယ်ကာယနှင့်ညစ်ညူးစွန်းကွက်သော အဝတ်ကိုပင် စက်ဆုပ်ရွံရှာ၍ ကြောက်ရွံ့ခြင်းနှင့်တကွ၊ အချို့ တို့ကို မီးထဲမှ ဆယ်နှုတ်ကယ်တင်ကြလော့။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Q'uehomak lê ch'ôl chixcolbal êras êrîtz'in. Chanchan li yôkex chirisinquileb sa' xxamlel li xbalba. Ut li jun ch'ol chic eb laj k'etol âtin, cheruxtânaheb ru aban tinye êre: cheq'uehak retal. Inc'a' chextz'akônk riq'uineb lix mâusilal xban nak numtajenakeb cui'chic lix mâusilal. Xic' cheril lix mâqueb jo' junak k'el t'icr numtajenak xtz'ajnil ru.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						a iných zachraňujte bázňou vytrhujúc ich z ohňa, nenávidiac ešte len aj tej od tela poškvrnenej sukne.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						तिमीहरु तिनीहरुलाई आगोबाट खोस। तर खुबै सावधान बन जब तिमी अन्य मानिसहरुलाई सहायता गर्छौ। तिनीहरुका वस्त्र समेतलाई घृणा गर जुन पापले फोहोर भएका छन्।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A jedne strahom izbavljajte i iz ognja vadite; a karajte sa strahom, mrzeći i na haljinu opoganjenu od tela.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						andre skal I frelse ved å rive dem ut av ilden, andre igjen skal I miskunne eder over med frykt, idet I hater endog den av kjødet smittede kjortel. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Kimini ateşten çekip kurtarın. Kimine de korkuyla merhamet edin. Ama günahlı bir bedenin lekelediği giysiden bile tiksinin.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						وخلّصوا البعض بالخوف مختطفين من النار مبغضين حتى الثوب المدنس من الجسد
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						e salvai-os, arrebatando-os do fogo; e de outros tende misericórdia com temor, abominação até a túnica manchada pela carne.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">illos vero salvate de igne rapientes aliis autem miseremini in timore odientes et eam quae carnalis est maculatam tunicam</lang><lang id="Greek">
						αλλους δε σωζετε μετα φοβου, αρπαζοντες αυτους εκ του πυρος, μισουντες και τον χιτωνα τον μεμολυσμενον απο της σαρκος.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 maar ander moet julle met vrees red deur hulle uit die vuur te ruk; en ook die kleed moet julle haat wat deur sonde bevlek is.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Lonje men delivre yo, rache yo soti nan mitan dife a. Se pou nou gen pitye pou lòt moun yo tou. Men, fè atansyon, paske se pou nou rayi ata rad ki sou yo nan move lavi y'ap mennen an
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						hãy cứu_vớt những kẻ kia , rút họ ra khỏi lửa ; còn đối_với kẻ khác , hãy có lòng thương lẫn với sợ , ghét cả đến cái áo bị xác_thịt làm ô_uế .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ואת אלה תושיעו באימה וחלצתם אתם מתוך האש וגעלתם גם את הלבוש המגאל בחלאת הבשר׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">and some save, snatching them out of the fire with fear, hating even the clothing stained by the flesh.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						అగ్నిలోనుండి లాగినట్టు కొందరిని రక్షించుడి, శరీర సంబంధమైన వారి అపవిత్ర ప్రవర్తనకు ఏ మాత్రము నొప్పు కొనక దానిని అసహ్యించుకొనుచు భయముతో కొందరిని కరుణించుడి. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Аз съм Алфа и Омега, казва Господ Бог, Който е, и Който е бил, и Който иде, Всемогъщият.
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						nekatere pa rešite, potegnivši jih iz ognja, nekatere pa s strahom milujte, sovražeč tudi obleko, oskrunjeno po mesu.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						و بعضی را ازآتش بیرون کشیده، برهانید و بر بعضی با خوف رحمت کنید و از لباس جسم آلود نفرت نمایید.الان او را که قادر است که شما را از لغزش محفوظ دارد و در حضور جلال خود شما رابی عیب به فرحی عظیم قایم فرماید،
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						frelser andre ved at udrive dem af Ilden, forbarmer eder over andre med Frygt, så I hade endog den af Kødet besmittede Kjortel.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						toisia taas armahtakaa pelolla, inhoten lihan tahraamaa ihokastakin.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						有些 人 你 們要 從火 中 搶出 來 搭救 他 們 ． 有些 人 你 們要 存懼 怕 的 心憐憫 他們．連那 被 情慾 沾染 的 衣服 也 當厭惡
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Afooyaŋ mo, araŋ m'i faaba k'i hamay ka kaa danjo ra. Afooyaŋ mo araŋ ma suuji kaŋ margu nda humburkumay cabe i se, araŋ ma wangu baa bankaaray kaŋ gaaham ziibandi. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						有 些 人 你 們 要 從 火 中 搶 出 來 搭 救 他 們 ． 有 些 人 你 們 要 存 懼 怕 的 心 憐 憫 他 們 ． 連 那 被 情 慾 沾 染 的 衣 服 也 當 厭 惡 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						और बहुतों को आग में से झपटकर निकालो, और बहुतों पर भय के साथ दया करो; बरन उस वस्त्रा से भी घृणा करो जो शरीर के द्वारा कलंकित हो गया है।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Jiné pak strašením k spasení přivozujte, jako z ohně je vychvacujíce, v nenávisti majíce i tu skrze tělo poskvrněnou sukni.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						kaj unujn savu, eltirante ilin el la fajro; kaj aliajn kompatu kun timo;  malamante ecx la veston makulitan de la karno.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Dhe atij që mund t'ju ruajë nga çdo rrëzim dhe t'ju nxjerrë para lavdisë së tij të paqortueshëm dhe me gëzim,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						altri salvateli strappandoli dal fuoco, di altri infine abbiate compassione con timore, guardandovi perfino dalla veste contaminata dalla loro carne
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    suma skuluð þér frelsa, með því að hrífa þá út úr eldinum. Og suma skuluð þér vera mildir við með ótta, og hatið jafnvel kyrtilinn, sem flekkaður er af holdinu. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						त्यांना अग्नीतून ओढून काढून वाचवा. पण दया दाखविण्याच्या वेळी काळजी घ्या. आणि त्यांच्या दैहिक पापामुळे मळीन झालेल्या कपड्यांचा तिरस्कार करा.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						火の中から引き出して救ってやりなさい。また、そのほかの人たちを、おそれの心をもってあわれみなさい。しかし、肉に汚れた者に対しては、その下着さえも忌みきらいなさい。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						a otros haced salvos, arrebatándolos del fuego; y a otros tenedles misericordia, pero con cautela, odiando hasta la ropa contaminada por su carne
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						qaarna dabka ka dhufta oo badbaadiya, qaarna u naxariista idinkoo cabsanaya oo nacaya xataa dharka jiidhka ku wasakhoobay.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Khenkhatte, meia kipanin la khe zok unla, hondam un; khenkhatte, a sa thanghuai banna uh puansilh lam leng kihin, lau kawmin hehpih un.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಬೇರೆಯವರನ್ನು ಬೆಂಕಿಯಿಂದ ಎಳಕೊಂಡು ಭಯದಿಂದ ರಕ್ಷಿಸಿರಿ. ಶರೀರದಿಂದ ಮೈಲಿಗೆಯಾದ ಅಂಗಿಯನ್ನು ಹಗೆಮಾಡಿರಿ.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						And others save with fear, pulling them out of the fire; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Houd hen vast en red hen uit het vuur. Maar bij sommige mensen moet u voorzichtig zijn met uw medeleven; u zou mogelijk door hun zonden kunnen worden beïnvloed. Haat elk spoor van hun zonde.</lang><lang id="Croatian">druge spasavajte otimajući ih  ognju, trećima se pak smilujte sa strahom, mrzeći i haljinu puti  okaljanu.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A drugich przez postrach do zbawienia przywódźcie, z ognia ich wyrywając, mając w nienawiści i suknię, która by była od ciała pokalana.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">และจงช่วยคนอื่นๆให้รอดโดยความกลัวด้วยการฉุดเขาออกมาจากไฟ จงเกลียดชังแม้แต่เสื้อผ้าที่เปรอะเปื้อนด้วยเนื้อหนังเถิด</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						At ang iba'y inyong iligtas, na agawin ninyo sa apoy; at ang iba'y inyong kahabagan na may takot; na inyong kapootan pati ng damit na nadungisan ng laman. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 火 の 中 から 引き出 し て 救 っ て や り なさ い 。 また 、 その ほか の 人 たち を 、 おそれ の 心 を も っ て あわれ み なさ い 。 しかし 、 肉 に 汚れ た 者 に 対 し て は 、 その 下着 さえ も 忌み きら い なさ い 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						ചിലരെ തീയില്‍നിന്നു വലിച്ചെടുത്തു രക്ഷിപ്പിന്‍ ; ജഡത്താല്‍ കറപിടിച്ച അങ്കിപോലും പകെച്ചുകൊണ്ടു ചിലര്‍ക്കും ഭയത്തോടെ കരുണ കാണിപ്പിന്‍ .
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						căutaţi să mîntuiţi pe unii, smulgîndu -i din foc; de alţii iarăş fie-vă milă cu frică, urînd pînă şi cămaşa mînjită de carne.
					</lang><lang id="German">
						etliche aber mit Furcht selig machet und rücket sie aus dem Feuer; und hasset auch den Rock, der vom Fleische befleckt ist.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						och frälsa dem genom att rycka dem ur elden; mot de andra mån I också vara barmhärtiga, dock med fruktan, så att I avskyn till och med deras livklädnad, den av köttet befläckade.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">และ จง ช่วย คน อื่นๆ ให้ รอด โดย ความ กลัว ด้วย การ ฉุด เขา ออก มา จาก ไฟ จง เกลียด ชัง แม้แต่ เสื้อ ผ้า ที่ เปรอะ เปื้อน ด้วย เนื้อ หนัง เถิด</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						päästke nad, kiskuge nad tulest välja; aga teiste peale halastage kartuses, võigastades kuubegi, mis liha läbi on pilastatud.
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.24" langNo="61"><lang id="Maori">
						Na, ki te mea kaha ki te tiaki i a koutou kei hinga, ki te whakatu hoki i a koutou ki te aroaro o tona kororia, he mea kohakore i runga i te hari whakaharahara
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						Vả, nguyền Ðấng có thể gìn giữ anh em khỏi vấp phạm và khiến anh em đứng trước mặt vinh hiển mình cách rất vui mừng, không chỗ trách được,
					</lang><lang id="French">
						Or, à celui qui peut vous préserver de toute chute et vous faire paraître devant sa gloire irrépréhensibles et dans l`allégresse,
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						Ary ho an'izay maharo anareo mba tsy ho tafintohina, ary hametraka anareo tsy hanan-tsiny eo anoloan'ny voninahiny amin'ny firavoravoana,ho an'Andriamanitra tokana, Mpamonjy antsika, amin'ny alalan i Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika anie, ny voninahitra sy ny fahalehibiazana, ny fanjakana sy ny fahefana hatramin'ny taloha indrindra sy ankehitriny ary mandrakizay. Amena.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Annak pedig, a ki titeket a bûntõl megõrízhet, és az õ dicsõsége elé állíthat feddhetetlenségben nagy örömmel,
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						Kulowo ke unako ukunilondoloza ningabi nakukhubeka,  nokunimisa phambi kobuqaqawuli bakhe ningenabala, nigcoba:
					</lang><lang id="Korean">능히 너희를 보호하사 거침이 없게 하시고 너희로 그 영광 앞에 흠이 없이 즐거움으로 서게 하실자</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						Tam, kuris gali išlaikyti jus nenupuolusius ir savo šlovės akivaizdon pastatyti nepriekaištingus su didžiausiu džiaugsmu,
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Могущему же соблюсти вас от падения и поставить пред славою Своею непорочными в радости,
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Allah, yang sanggup menjaga supaya kalian tidak jatuh, dan yang sanggup membawamu ke hadirat-Nya yang mulia dengan sukacita dan tanpa cela
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano">
						Karon ngadto kaniya nga may gahum sa pagbantay kaninyo nga dili mangahulog ug sa pagpasundayag kaninyo nga walay buling diha sa atubangan sa iyang himaya dinuyogan sa dakung kalipay,
					</lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ထိမိ၍ လဲခြင်းနှင့် ကင်းလွတ်စေမည်အကြောင်း သင်တို့ကို စောင့်ရှောက်ခြင်းငှါ၎င်း၊ အပြစ် မရှိဘဲဝမ်းမြောက်ခြင်းနှင့် ပြည့်စုံလျက်ရှိသော သင်တို့ကို ဘုန်းအသရေတော်ရှေ့၌ ဆက်သခြင်းငှါ၎င်း တတ်နိုင်တော်မူသော သူတည်းဟူသော။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Ut anakcuan lok'oninbil taxak li nimajcual Dios. A'an k'axal nim xcuanquil chêcolbal re nak inc'a' texmâcobk. Nim ajcui' xcuanquil chêk'axtesinquil sa' xnimal xlok'al li Dios chi mâc'a'ak êmâc ut chi sa sa' êch'ôl.Lok'oninbil taxak li junaj chi Dios, laj Colol ke sa' xc'aba' li Kâcua' Jesucristo. A'an taxak chinimâk xcuanquil ut xlok'al chalen chak najter k'e cutan, ut toj chalen anakcuan ut chi junelic. Jo'can taxak.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						A tomu, ktorý vás môže zachovať tak, čo neklesnete, a postaviť bezvadných pred tvárou svojej slávy v plesaní,
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						परमेश्वर शक्तिशाली हुनुहुन्छ अनि तिमीहरुलाई पतन हुनबाट जोगाउन सहयोग गर्ने योग्य हुनुहुन्छ। कुनै दोष अनि महा आनन्द बिनै उहाँको महिमामय उपस्थिति अघि तिमीलाई ल्याउन योग्य हुनुहुन्छ।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">A Onome koji vas može sačuvati bez greha i bez mane, i postaviti prave pred slavom svojom u radosti,</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						Men ham som er mektig til å verne om eder, så I ikke snubler, og å stille eder lyteløse frem for sin herlighet i fryd, 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish">
						Kurtarıcımız tek Tanrı, sizi düşmekten alıkoyacak, büyük sevinç içinde lekesiz olarak yüce huzuruna çıkaracak güçtedir. Yücelik, ululuk, güç ve yetki Rabbimiz İsa Mesih aracılığıyla bütün çağlardan önce, şimdi ve bütün çağlar boyunca Tanrı'nın olsun! Amin.
					</lang><lang id="Arabic">
						والقادر ان يحفظكم غير عاثرين ويوقفكم امام مجده بلا عيب في الابتهاج
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						Ora, �quele que é poderoso para vos guardar de tropeçar, e apresentar-vos ante a sua glória imaculados e jubilosos,
					</lang><lang id="Latin">ei autem qui potest vos conservare sine peccato et constituere ante conspectum gloriae suae inmaculatos in exultatione</lang><lang id="Greek">
						Εις δε τον δυναμενον να σας φυλαξη απταιστους και να σας στηση κατενωπιον της δοξης αυτου αμωμους εν αγαλλιασει,
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 Aan Hom nou wat magtig is om julle van struikeling te bewaar en julle sonder gebrek voor sy heerlikheid te stel met gejuig,
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Koulye a tout lwanj, tout grandè, tout pouvwa ak tout otorite pou yon sèl Bondye a, pou Bondye ki ka kenbe nou pou nou pa tonbe, li menm ki kapab fè nou parèt san repròch ak kè kontan devan l' nan tout bèl pouvwa li
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						Vả , nguyền Ðấng có_thể gìn_giữ anh_em khỏi vấp phạm và khiến anh_em đứng trước mặt vinh_hiển mình cách rất vui_mừng , không chỗ trách được ,
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						ולאשר יכול לשמרכם בבלי מכשול ולהעמיד אתכם בששון תמימים לפני כבודו׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">Now to him who is able to keep them from stumbling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory in great joy,</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						తొట్రిల్లకుండ మిమ్మును కాపాడుటకును, తన మహిమ యెదుట ఆనందముతో మిమ్మును నిర్దోషులనుగా నిలువ బెట్టుటకును, శక్తిగల మన రక్షకుడైన అద్వితీయ దేవునికి,
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						Иоан, ваш брат и съучастник в неволите и в царството и в търпението, които са чрез Исуса [Христа], бях на острова, наречен Патмос, за Божието слово и свидетелството за Исуса [Христа].
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						Njemu pa, ki vas more obvarovati brez spotike in postaviti pred obličje slave svoje brez madeža v radovanju,edinemu Bogu, Rešitelju našemu, po Jezusu Kristusu Gospodu našem slava, veličastvo, moč in oblast pred vsem časom in zdaj in na vse veke! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi">
						الان او را که قادر است که شما را از لغزش محفوظ دارد و در حضور جلال خود شما رابی عیب به فرحی عظیم قایم فرماید،
					</lang><lang id="Danish">
						 Men ham, som er mægtig til at bevare eder fra Fald og fremstille eder for sin Herlighed ulastelige i Fryd,
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						Mutta hänelle, joka voi varjella teidät lankeamasta ja asettaa teidät nuhteettomina, riemuitsevina, kirkkautensa eteen,
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						那能 保守 你 們不失腳 、 叫 你 們無瑕無疵 、 歡歡 喜 喜 站 在 他 榮耀 之前 的 、 我們 的 救主 獨 一 的 神
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Irikoy gonda dabari k'araŋ gaay hal araŋ ma si kati, ka kande araŋ ka kayandi nga darza jine, taali si, farhã beeri ra. 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						那 能 保 守 你 們 不 失 腳 、 叫 你 們 無 瑕 無 疵 、 歡 歡 喜 喜 站 在 他 榮 耀 之 前 的 、 我 們 的 救 主 獨 一 的 　 神 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						अब जो तुम्हें ठोकर खाने से बचा सकता है, और अपनी महिमा की भरपूरी के साम्हने मगन और निर्दोष करके खड़ा कर सकता है।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Tomu pak, kterýž mocen jest zachovati vás bez úrazu a postaviti před obličejem slávy své bez úhony s veselím,
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						Kaj al Tiu, kiu povas vin gardi senfalaj, kaj starigi vin senriprocxaj antaux Sia gloro en granda gxojo,
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						të vetmit Perëndi të ditur, Shpëtimtarit tonë, i qoftë lavdi, madhështi, sundim dhe pushtet, tani dhe përjetë. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						A colui che può preservarvi da ogni caduta e farvi comparire davanti alla sua gloria senza difetti e nella letizia
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    En honum, sem megnar að varðveita yður frá hrösun og láta yður koma fram fyrir dýrð sína, lýtalausa í fögnuði, 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						आता, तुम्ही पडू नये म्हणून तुम्हाला राखावयास जो समर्थ आहे आणि तुम्हाला आपल्या गौरवी समक्षतेत शुद्ध असे सादर करायला जो मोठ्या आनंदाने तयार आहे, त्याला आणि आपले तारण करणारा जो
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						あなたがたを守ってつまずかない者とし、また、その栄光のまえに傷なき者として、喜びのうちに立たせて下さるかた、
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						Y a aquel que es poderoso para guardaros sin caída y para presentaros irreprensibles delante de su gloria con grande alegría
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						Oo kan kara inuu turunturada idinka ilaaliyo oo uu ammaantiisa idin hor taago, idinkoo aan iin lahayn oo aad u faraxsan,isagoo ah Ilaaha keligiis ah oo Badbaadiyeheenna ah, ammaan iyo weynaan iyo xoog iyo amar ha u ahaadeen xagga Rabbigeenna Ciise Masiix, wakhtiga oo dhan ka hor iyo haatan iyo weligeedba. Aamiin.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Tuin, na puk louhna ding ua honveng thei leh, a thupina ma taka nakpi taka nuamsaa nin bangloua nou hon koih theipa,Hondampa Pathian tak kia kiangah, i Toups Jesu Kris jiakin, hun himhim om ma leh tu leh khantawn dongin, pahtawinate thupinate, vaihawmate, thuneihnate om hen. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಎಡವಿಬೀಳದಂತೆ ನಿಮ್ಮನ್ನು ಕಾಪಾಡುವದಕ್ಕೂ ತನ್ನ ಪ್ರಭಾವದ ಸಮಕ್ಷಮದಲ್ಲಿ ನಿಮ್ಮನ್ನು ನಿರ್ದೋಷಿ ಗಳನ್ನಾಗಿ ಅತ್ಯಂತ ಹರ್ಷದೊಡನೆ ನಿಲ್ಲಿಸುವದಕ್ಕೂ ಶಕ್ತನಾಗಿರುವಒಬ್ಬನೇ ಜ್ಞಾನವುಳ್ಳ ನಮ್ಮ ರಕ್ಷಕನಾದ ದೇವರಿಗೆ ಪ್ರಭಾವ ಮಹತ್ವ ಆಧಿಪತ್ಯ ಅಧಿಕಾರಗಳು ಈಗಲೂ ಯಾವಾಗಲೂ ಇರಲಿ. ಆಮೆನ್‌.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						Now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory with exceeding joy,
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">God kan ervoor zorgen dat u niet struikelt. Hij kan u zover brengen dat u zonder gebreken en vol blijdschap voor Zijn schitterende troon komt te staan.</lang><lang id="Croatian">Onomu koji vas može očuvati od pada i besprijekorne postaviti  pred svoju Slavu u klicanju -</lang><lang id="Polish">
						A temu, który was może zachować od upadku i stawić przed oblicznością chwały swojej bez nagany z weselem,
					</lang><lang id="Thai">บัดนี้แด่พระองค์ผู้ทรงสามารถคุ้มครองรักษาท่านมิให้ล้มลง และทรงนำท่านให้ตั้งอยู่จำเพาะสง่าราศีของพระองค์โดยปราศจากตำหนิ และมีความร่าเริงยินดีอย่างเหลือล้น</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Ngayon doon sa makapagiingat sa inyo mula sa pagkatisod, at sa inyo'y makapaghaharap na walang kapintasan na may malaking galak, sa harapan ng kaniyang kaluwalhatian. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 あなた がた を 守 っ て つまず か な い 者 と し 、 また 、 その 栄光 の まえ に 傷 な き 者 と し て 、 喜び の うち に 立 た せ て 下さ る かた 、
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam">
						വീഴാതവണ്ണം നിങ്ങളെ സൂക്ഷിച്ചു, തന്റെ മഹിമാസന്നിധിയില്‍ കളങ്കമില്ലാത്തവരായി ആനന്ദത്തോടെ നിറുത്തുവാന്‍ ശക്തിയുള്ളവന്നു, നമ്മുടെ കര്‍ത്താവായ യേശുക്രിസ്തുമുഖാന്തരം നമ്മുടെ രക്ഷിതാവായ ഏകദൈവത്തിന്നു തന്നേ, സര്‍വ്വകാലത്തിന്നുമുമ്പും ഇപ്പോഴും സദാകാലത്തോളവും തേജസ്സും മഹിമയും ബലവും അധികാരവും ഉണ്ടാകുമാറാകട്ടെ. ആമേന്‍ .
					</lang><lang id="Romanian">
						Iar a Aceluia, care poate să vă păzească de orice cădere, şi să vă facă să vă înfăţişaţi fără prihană şi plini de bucurie înaintea slavei Sale,
					</lang><lang id="German">
						Dem aber, der euch kann behüten ohne Fehl und stellen vor das Angesicht seiner Herrlichkeit unsträflich mit Freuden,
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						Men honom som förmår bevara eder ifrån fall och ställa eder inför sin härlighet ostraffliga, i fröjd,
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">บัดนี้ แด่ พระองค์ ผู้ทรง สามารถ คุ้มครอง รักษา ท่าน มิ ให้ ล้ม ลง และ ทรง นำ ท่าน ให้ ตั้ง อยู่ จำเพาะ สง่า ราศี ของ พระองค์ โดย ปราศจาก ตำหนิ และ มีค วาม ร่าเริง ยินดี อย่าง เหลือล้น</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						Aga Temale, Kes teid võib hoida komistamast ja teid veatuina seada Oma auhiilguse palge ette hõiskamisega,
					</lang></verse><verse id="b.JUD.1.25" langNo="57"><lang id="Maori">
						Ki a ia, ko ia anake nei te Atua, ki to tatou Kaiwhakaora, i roto i a ihu Karaiti, i to tatou Ariki, waiho atu i a ia te kororia, te nui, te kaha, te mana, i mua atu o nga wa katoa, aianei, a ake ake. Amine
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese">
						là Ðức Chúa Trời có một, là Cứu Chúa chúng ta, bởi Ðức Chúa Jêsus Christ là Chúa chúng ta, được sự vinh hiển, tôn trọng, thế lực, quyền năng thuộc về Ngài từ trước vô cùng và hiện nay cho đến đời đời! A-men.
					</lang><lang id="French">
						à Dieu seul, notre Sauveur, par Jésus Christ notre Seigneur, soient gloire, majesté, force et puissance, dès avant tous les temps, et maintenant, et dans tous les siècles! Amen!
					</lang><lang id="Malagasy">
						ho an'Andriamanitra tokana, Mpamonjy antsika, amin'ny alalan i Jesosy Kristy Tompontsika anie, ny voninahitra sy ny fahalehibiazana, ny fanjakana sy ny fahefana hatramin'ny taloha indrindra sy ankehitriny ary mandrakizay. Amena.
					</lang><lang id="Hungarian">
						Az egyedül bölcs Istennek, a mi megtartónknak, dicsõség, nagyság, erõ és hatalom most és mind örökké. Ámen.
					</lang><lang id="Xhosa">
						kuThixo olumkileyo yedwa, uMsindisi wethu, makubekho uzuko nobukhulu, amandla negunya, nangoku, kude kuse nasemaphakadeni onke. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Korean">곧 우리 구주 홀로 하나이신 하나님께 우리 주 예수 그리스도로 말미암아 영광과 위엄과 권력과 권세가 만고 전부터 이제와 세세에 있을지어다 아멘</lang><lang id="Lithuanian">
						vieninteliam išmintingajam Dievui, mūsų Gelbėtojui, per mūsų Viešpatį Jėzų Kristų tebūna šlovė, didybė, galybė ir valdžia dabar ir per amžius! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Russian">
						Единому Премудрому Богу, Спасителю нашему чрез Иисуса Христа Господа нашего, слава и величие, сила и власть прежде всех веков, ныне и во все веки. Аминь.
					</lang><lang id="Indonesian">
						Dialah satu-satunya Allah, Penyelamat kita melalui Yesus Kristus Tuhan kita. Dialah Allah yang mulia, agung, berkuasa dan berwibawa sejak dahulu kala sampai sekarang dan untuk selama-lamanya! Amin
					</lang><lang id="Cebuano"></lang><lang id="Myanmar">
						ငါတို့ကို ကယ်တင်တော်မူသောအရှင်၊ တဆူတည်းသောဘုရားသခင်သည်၊ ငါတို့သခင်ယေရှုခရစ် အားဖြင့်၊ ယခုမှစ၍ကမ္ဘာ အဆက်ဆက်ဘုန်းတန်ခိုး အာနုဘော်နှင့် အစွမ်းသတ္တိအာဏာ စက်ရှိတော်မူစေ သတည်း။ အာမင်။
					</lang><lang id="Q'eqchi'">
						Lok'oninbil taxak li junaj chi Dios, laj Colol ke sa' xc'aba' li Kâcua' Jesucristo. A'an taxak chinimâk xcuanquil ut xlok'al chalen chak najter k'e cutan, ut toj chalen anakcuan ut chi junelic. Jo'can taxak.
					</lang><lang id="Slovak">
						jedinému múdremu Bohu, nášmu Spasiteľovi, nech je skrze Ježiša Krista, nášho Pána, sláva a veličenstvo, sila a vrchnostenská moc, ako pred všetkými veky, tak pred všetkými veky, tak i teraz i na všetky veky. Ameň.
					</lang><lang id="Nepali">
						उहाँ एक मात्र परमेश्वर हुनुहुन्छ जसले हामीलाई बचाँउनु सक्नुहुन्छ। सबै बितेका समय, अहिले, अनि सदासर्वदा हाम्रा प्रभु येशू ख्रीष्ट मार्फत महिमा, महानता, शक्ति अनि अधिकार उहाँका साथ रहुन। आमिन।
					</lang><lang id="Serbian">Jedinom premudrom Bogu i Spasu našem, kroz Isusa Hrista Gospoda našeg, slava i veličanstvo, država i vlast pre sviju vekova i sad i u sve vekove. Amin.</lang><lang id="Norwegian">
						den eneste Gud, vår frelser ved Jesus Kristus, vår Herre, ham tilhører herlighet, storhet, styrke og makt før all tid og nu og i all evighet. Amen. 
					</lang><lang id="Turkish"></lang><lang id="Arabic">
						الاله الحكيم الوحيد مخلّصنا له المجد والعظمة والقدرة والسلطان الآن والى كل الدهور. آمين
					</lang><lang id="Portuguese">
						ao único Deus, nosso Salvador, por Jesus Cristo nosso Senhor, glória, majestade, domínio e poder, antes de todos os séculos, e agora, e para todo o sempre. Amém.
					</lang><lang id="Latin">soli Deo salvatori nostro per Iesum Christum Dominum nostrum gloria magnificentia imperium et potestas ante omne saeculum et nunc et in omnia saecula amen</lang><lang id="Greek">
						εις τον μονον σοφον Θεον τον σωτηρα ημων, ειη δοξα και μεγαλωσυνη, κρατος και εξουσια και νυν και εις παντας τους αιωνας αμην.
					</lang><lang id="Afrikaans">
						 aan die alleenwyse God, ons Verlosser, kom toe heerlikheid en majesteit, krag en mag, nou en tot in alle ewigheid! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Creole">
						Li menm, sèl Bondye ki delivre nou gremesi Jezikri, Segnè nou an, wi, se pou li tout lwanj, tout grandè, tout pouvwa ak tout otorite, depi nan tan lontan, koulye a ak pou tout tan. Amèn
					</lang><lang id="Vietnamese-tok">
						là Ðức_Chúa_Trời có một , là Cứu_Chúa chúng_ta , bởi Ðức_Chúa_Jêsus_Christ là Chúa chúng_ta , được sự vinh_hiển , tôn_trọng , thế_lực , quyền_năng thuộc về Ngài từ trước vô_cùng và hiện_nay cho_đến đời_đời ! A-men .
					</lang><lang id="Hebrew">
						לאלהים אשר לו לבדו החכמה המושיע אתנו לו הכבוד והגדלה והעז והממשלה מעתה ולעולמי עד אמן׃
					</lang><lang id="English-WEB">to God our Savior, who alone is wise, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and forever. Amen.</lang><lang id="Telugu">
						మన ప్రభువైన యేసు క్రీస్తుద్వారా, మహిమయు మహాత్మ్య మును ఆధిపత్యమును అధికారమును యుగములకు పూర్వ మును ఇప్పుడును సర్వయుగములును కలుగును గాక. 
					</lang><lang id="Bulgarian">
						В Господния ден бях в изстъпление чрез Духа; и чух зад себе си силен глас като от тръба, който казваше:
					</lang><lang id="Slovene">
						edinemu Bogu, Rešitelju našemu, po Jezusu Kristusu Gospodu našem slava, veličastvo, moč in oblast pred vsem časom in zdaj in na vse veke! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Farsi"></lang><lang id="Danish">
						den eneste Gud, vor Frelser ved vor Herre Jesus Kristus, tilkommer Ære og Majestæt, Vælde og Magt, forud for al Tid og nu og i alle Evigheder! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Finnish">
						hänelle, ainoalle Jumalalle ja meidän pelastajallemme Herramme Jeesuksen Kristuksen kautta, hänelle kunnia, majesteetti, voima ja valta ennen kaikkia aikoja ja nyt ja iankaikkisesti! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Chinese-tok">
						願榮耀 、 威嚴 、 能力 、 權柄 、 因我 們 的 主 耶穌基督 、 歸與 他 、 從萬 古 以前 、 並現 今 、 直 到 永永遠遠 。 阿們
					</lang><lang id="Zarma">
						 Nga, Irikoy follonka din, kaŋ ti iri Faabakwa iri Rabbi Yesu Almasihu do, darza nda beeray da koytaray da dabari ma bara a se, za zamaney kulu mana te hala ka kaa sohõ ka koy hal abada abadin. Amin! 
					</lang><lang id="Chinese">
						願 榮 耀 、 威 嚴 、 能 力 、 權 柄 、 因 我 們 的 主 耶 穌 基 督 、 歸 與 他 、 從 萬 古 以 前 、 並 現 今 、 直 到 永 永 遠 遠 。 阿 們 
					</lang><lang id="Hindi">
						उस अद्वैत परमेश्वर हमारे उद्धारकर्ता की महिमा, और गौरव, और पराक्रम, और अधिकार, हमारे प्रभु यीशु मसीह के द्वारा जैसा सनातन काल से है, अब भी हो और युगानुयुग रहे। आमीन।।
					</lang><lang id="Czech">
						Samému moudrému Bohu, Spasiteli našemu, budiž sláva a velebnost, císařství i moc, i nyní i po všecky věky. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Esperanto">
						al la sola Dio, nia Savanto, per Jesuo Kristo, nia Sinjoro, estu gloro,  majesto, potenco, kaj auxtoritato, antaux cxiu mondagxo, kaj nun, kaj gxis la eterneco. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Albanian">
						Zbulesa e Jezu Krishtit, që Perëndia ia dha për t'u treguar shërbëtorëve të tij gjërat që duhet të ndodhin për së shpejti dhe e bëri të ditur, duke ia dërguar nëpërmjet engjëllit të tij, shërbëtorit të vet Gjon,
					</lang><lang id="Italian">
						all'unico Dio, nostro salvatore, per mezzo di Gesù Cristo nostro Signore, gloria, maestà, forza e potenza prima di ogni tempo, ora e sempre. Amen
					</lang><lang id="Icelandic">
			    einum Guði, sem frelsar oss fyrir Jesú Krist, Drottin vorn, sé dýrð, hátign, máttur og vald fyrir allar aldir, nú og um allar aldir. Amen. 
		    </lang><lang id="Marathi">
						एकच देव आहे, त्याला आपला प्रभु येशू ख्रिस्त याच्याद्वारे गौरव, मान, पराक्रम आणि अधिकार काल, आज आणि अनंतकाळ असो. आमेन.
					</lang><lang id="Japanese">
						すなわち、わたしたちの救主なる唯一の神に、栄光、大能、力、権威が、わたしたちの主イエス・キリストによって、世々の初めにも、今も、また、世々限りなく、あるように、アァメン。
					</lang><lang id="Spanish">
						al único Dios, nuestro Salvador por medio de Jesucristo nuestro Señor, sea la gloria, la majestad, el dominio y la autoridad desde antes de todos los siglos, ahora y por todos los siglos. Amén
					</lang><lang id="Somali">
						isagoo ah Ilaaha keligiis ah oo Badbaadiyeheenna ah, ammaan iyo weynaan iyo xoog iyo amar ha u ahaadeen xagga Rabbigeenna Ciise Masiix, wakhtiga oo dhan ka hor iyo haatan iyo weligeedba. Aamiin.
					</lang><lang id="Paite">
						Hondampa Pathian tak kia kiangah, i Toups Jesu Kris jiakin, hun himhim om ma leh tu leh khantawn dongin, pahtawinate thupinate, vaihawmate, thuneihnate om hen. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Kannada">
						ಒಬ್ಬನೇ ಜ್ಞಾನವುಳ್ಳ ನಮ್ಮ ರಕ್ಷಕನಾದ ದೇವರಿಗೆ ಪ್ರಭಾವ ಮಹತ್ವ ಆಧಿಪತ್ಯ ಅಧಿಕಾರಗಳು ಈಗಲೂ ಯಾವಾಗಲೂ ಇರಲಿ. ಆಮೆನ್‌.
					</lang><lang id="English">
						To the only wise God our Saviour, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and ever. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Dutch">Hij is de enige God; Hij redt ons door onze Here Jezus Christus. Voor Hem is alle heerlijkheid en majesteit, alle kracht en macht, sinds het begin, nu en voor eeuwig. Amen.</lang><lang id="Croatian">jedinomu Bogu, Spasitelju našemu, po Isusu Kristu, Gospodinu našemu: slava, veličanstvo, vlast  i moć i prije svakoga vijeka, i sada, i u sve vijeke. Amen.</lang><lang id="Polish">
						Samemu mądremu Bogu, Zbawicielowi naszemu, niech będzie chwała i wielmożność, moc i zwierzchność, i teraz i po wszystkie wieki. Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Thai">สง่าราศี พระอานุภาพ การครอบครอง และศักดานุภาพจงมีแด่พระเจ้าผู้ทรงพระปัญญาแต่เพียงพระองค์เดียว พระผู้ช่วยให้รอดของเรา ทั้งปัจจุบันกาล และในกาลต่อๆไปเป็นนิตย์ เอเมน</lang><lang id="Tagalog">
						Sa iisang Dios na ating Tagapagligtas, sa pamamagitan ni Jesucristo na ating Panginoon, ay sumakaniya nawa ang kaluwalhatian, ang karangalan, ang paghahari, at ang kapangyarihan, sa kaunaunahang panahon, at ngayon at magpakailan man. Siya nawa. 
					</lang><lang id="Japanese-tok">
						 すなわち 、 わたし たち の 救 主な る 唯一 の 神 に 、 栄光 、 大能 、 力 、 権威 が 、 わたし たち の 主 イエス ・ キリスト に よ っ て 、 世々 の 初め に も 、 今 も 、 また 、 世々 限り な く 、 あ る よう に 、 アァメン 。
					</lang><lang id="Malayalam"></lang><lang id="Romanian">
						singurului Dumnezeu, Mîntuitorul nostru, prin Isus Hristos, Domnul nostru, să fie slavă, măreţie, putere şi stăpînire, mai înainte de toţi vecii, şi acum şi în veci. Amin
					</lang><lang id="German">
						dem Gott, der allein weise ist, unserm Heiland, sei Ehre und Majestät und Gewalt und Macht nun und zu aller Ewigkeit! Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Swedish">
						honom som allena är Gud, och som är vår Frälsare genom Jesus Kristus, vår Herre, honom tillhör ära, majestät, välde och makt, såsom före all tid, så ock nu och i alla evigheter.  Amen.
					</lang><lang id="Thai-tok">สง่า ราศี พระ อานุภาพ การ ครอบครอง และ ศักดา นุ ภาพ จง มี แด่ พระเจ้า ผู้ทรง พระ ปัญญา แต่ เพียง พระองค์ เดียว พระ ผู้ ช่วย ให้ รอด ของ เรา ทั้ง ปัจจุบัน กาล และ ใน กาล ต่อๆ ไป เป็นนิตย์ เอ เมน</lang><lang id="Estonian">
						ainule Jumalale, meie Õnnistegijale, Jeesuse Kristuse, meie Issanda läbi olgu au, auhiilgus, võimus ja valitsus enne kõike maailmaajastut ja nüüd ja kõigi ajastuteni! Aamen.
					</lang></verse></chapter></book></text>
